<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[photo | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/photo/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-19T21:17:42-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Photo Management Quest, Part 3: Dropbox and Friends]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/13/pq3-dropbox-and-friends/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/13/pq3-dropbox-and-friends</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(Note: You might want to read my other <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/photo/">posts about photo management</a> for context first.)</p>

<p>{% img right /images/hv-dropbox.jpg %}</p>

<p>I am extremely happy to report some actual forward progress in this episode of My Photo Management Quest.  The short story is that all my photos now live on Dropbox in a nice hieararchical folder structure where I can browse and share them from any of my computers or iOS devices. My new system isn’t perfect, but it’s pretty good and I think it’s a solid foundation for the future.</p>

<h2 id="moving-from-iphoto-to-dropbox">Moving from iPhoto to Dropbox</h2>

<p>iPhoto is fundamentally an application for doing light editing and organization of photos on a single computer. Any new system that involves access from multiple different devices is going to require getting your photos out of iPhoto’s black box. My first step was to do <a href="http://www.macstories.net/tutorials/moving-from-iphoto-to-dropbox/">what Federico Vittici at MacStories did</a> through a combination of <a href="http://code.google.com/p/phoshare/">PhoShare</a> and <a href="http://www.noodlesoft.com/hazel.php">Hazel</a>.  The process created a set of year folders, and in each of those, a set of month folders that contain all my photos named and sorted by date. I also followed his lead and created a Hazel rule to move files from the Camera Uploads folder (where Dropbox puts my just-taken photos and videos) into my new Photos hierarchy. That means I need do absolutely nothing after I click my iPhone’s shutter button for my photos to be organized and accessible (by me) forever in the cloud. What a breath of fresh air compared to Apple’s Photo Stream!</p>

<p>My photos currently take up about 20GB, and Dropbox charges $99 per 100GB. Give how rock solid Dropbox is and how many iOS apps support it, I think that’s a great deal. </p>

<h2 id="further-organization-and-editing-on-the-mac">Further Organization and Editing on the Mac</h2>

<p>I’ve been manually adding a bit more organization in two ways. First, I’ve split some months into separate events. For example, I created a “2013-10-halloween” folder (inside the “2013” folder) that contains the requisite costume and pumpkin photos. These photos no longer live in the generic “2013-10” folder. I’ve also created a few special folders (e.g., “yummy-things”) outside the date-based hierarchy that have <em>copies</em> of some pictures in the date-based hierarchy.  That way I can find those pictures by date or subject. I can also easily share these folders (read-only) with friends and family using Dropbox shared links. </p>

<p>The best way I’ve found so far to actually create these new folders is Coverflow view in Finder. It’s <a href="https://discussions.apple.com/message/23562534#23562534">buggy in Mavericks</a> and it doesn’t let me see enough at the same time, but it works. I’m sure there are better ways (maybe <a href="http://unboundformac.com">Unbound for Mac</a> when it’s more stable, maybe <a href="http://www.arcsoft.com/photoplus/">Photo+ by Arcsoft</a>, maybe <a href="http://www.lynapp.com">Lyn</a>) but I haven’t settled on one yet.</p>

<p>One of the biggest advantages of having my photos live in the file system is that I’m not locked into iPhoto for editing–I can now use whatever app I want. <a href="http://www.pixelmator.com">Pixelmator</a> is nice and I’m sure I’ll eventually settle on an even lighter weight app for easy stuff (e.g., cropping/red-eye reduction/brightness adjustment).</p>

<h2 id="browsing-on-ios">Browsing on iOS</h2>

<p>Now that my photos live in Dropbox, I have at least three choices of iOS apps to browse them.  The <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/iphoneapp">Dropbox app</a>’s photo tab lets me scroll through thumbnails of all my photos sorted by date and download full resolution versions as needed. I can also browse the folder structure through the standard file browing UI and grab photos, though I don’t get a pretty set of big thumbnails.  Playing videos and sharing links to files and folders is easy.</p>

<p>{% img left /images/hv-heliog.png %}</p>

<p><a href="http://www.heliogapp.com">Heliog</a> is fast and pretty–it preserves my folder hierarchy and shows nice screens of thumbnails. I can share folders or sets of photos and easily move photos between folders. The downsides are that it doesn’t play video and I can’t delete photos from the photo view (have to be in the album view). These both seem easily fixable.</p>

<p>{% img right /images/hv-unbound.jpg %}</p>

<p>Right now, I think <a href="http://unboundapp.com">Unbound</a> is the best of the bunch.  Unlike Heliog, it plays videos and let’s me delete photos from the photo view. Like Heliog, sharing Dropbox links is easy and browsing is fast–you can even make the app cache folders for quicker (or offline) access. Unbound will show you all the photo’s EXIF data and even show where a photo was taken on a map. Moving pictures between folders is easy, but I don’t think it’s possible to copy pictures to other albums. It shows me all my folders, but flattens the hierarchy–i.e., my month folders are no longer grouped by year. The ordering is correct, so this isn’t actually so bad.</p>

<h2 id="the-future">The Future</h2>

<p>The next step for my photo management system is to integrate the rest of our family photos. Right now they’re scattered across several computers, folders and hard drives with tons of duplicates. Dropping these photos into my Camera Uploads folder will immediately sort them into my master folder structure, but it won’t remove duplicates. There are lots of apps out there that promise to remove duplicates, but I’m scared to death that they’ll remove too much and the one app I tried (<a href="http://www.duplicatephotofixer.com/PhotoCleaner.aspx">Photos Duplicate Cleaner</a>) didn’t come close to catching everything. </p>

<p>In the early days of the internet, companies like Yahoo tried organizing the web by manually creating big hiearchical lists of sites. Now we just Google for what we want and leave it to racks of servers and fancy algorithms to index it. The same thing has happened to mail. I used to carefully file all my mail into topic-specific folders, but now I just dump it all into one archive folder and rely on search when I need to find something. Photos will eventually be handled the same way. People won’t have to spend gobs of time dividing stacks of photos into events or tagging photos with their friends’ names–that’s what EXIF data and face recognition are for.  Everpix (may they rest in peace) was moving in this direction and I’ve heard <a href="http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2013/12/honan-photography/">great things about what Google+ is doing with pictures</a>. </p>

<p>I am very excited to try some more cutting edge services as they roll out. With our photos safely backed up and accessible on Dropbox, I won’t have to worry about being locked into a deadend or that the service will mess up my photos.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> I’ll have the best of both worlds.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>For the record, Everpix did both: they made export very difficult and compressed photos, losing detail that I might eventually want. <a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Photo Management Quest, Part 2: Loom]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/29/pq2-loom/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/29/pq2-loom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(Note: You might want to read <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/09/im-not-happy/">my first photo management rant</a> and <a href="/blog/2013/04/30/pq1-adobe-revel-and-everpix">Part 1</a> for context.)</p>

<p>{% img right /images/hv-loom.png %}</p>

<p>Ever since
<a href="http://www.theverge.com/2013/11/5/5039216/everpix-life-and-death-inside-the-worlds-best-photo-startup">Everpix went belly up</a>,
photo management has been a common topic on the blogs I read and the
podcasts I listen to. The current
<a href="http://thesweetsetup.com/apps/our-favorite-photo-stream-alternative/">consensus favorite</a>
is <a href="http://www.loom.com">Loom</a> and when I read their feature list I was
pretty excited. They seemlessly sync your iOS Camera Roll and your Mac’s
iPhoto Library with the cloud. Unlike Everpix, they store original files
instead of lossy compressed versions. Unlike Everpix and Adobe Revel,
they store photos AND videos. Their web app lets you browse your photo
collection from anywhere. I loved that you could create and manage
albums of photos from anywhere. Even their pricing ($40/yr for 50GB and
$99/yr for 255GB) was reasonable.</p>

<p>I signed up for the service, and while it took longer than I thought it
should, the iOS app eventually pushed my 300 photo Camera Roll up to the
cloud.  After enjoyably browsing this little collection on my phone,
iPad, and Mac (using the web app), I decided to pony up for a month of 255GB
of storage and try uploading my whole iPhoto library.  I won’t bore you
with the details, but after six days of synchronization hangs, duplicate
photos, and unanswered support email, I gave up.</p>

<p>It’s possible that the problem was just me as I haven’t found anyone
else complaining about Loom synchronization on the web.  My internet
connection’s upload speed is not that great–just 1.5 Mbps–but this is
the first time I’ve had a product give me trouble. Dropbox has been
successfully syncing more than 50 GB of files for about three years now
and I have used BackBlaze to successfully replicate about a terabyte of data.</p>

<p>I found the whole experience rather depressing. The service even on paper
wasn’t perfect. They don’t remove duplicate photos. They don’t offer
even rudimentary editing tools. They won’t stream videos through any of
their apps. They won’t synchronize folders on Windows machines with the
cloud. That said, their feature set was above my bar and they seemed
like they were moving in the right direction.  This time software
quality was the show stopper. </p>

<p>Sigh. The quest continues.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Photo Management Quest, Part 1: Adobe Revel and Everpix]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/30/pq1-adobe-revel-and-everpix/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/30/pq1-adobe-revel-and-everpix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am frustrated and I know I’m not the only one. I want
want a photo management system that requires minimum maintenance and gives me maximum flexibility. I’ve complained about this <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/09/im-not-happy/">before</a>, but I’m tired of waiting for Apple to hand me a gift-wrapped solution.  They didn’t last summer in iOS 6 and I have no faith that they will in iOS 7.</p>

<p>In my household, we take most of our photos with our phones, but we also have a big digital SLR which we break out for big events (if we remember to). Ideally, all our pictures would be automatically whisked away into a shared database in the cloud as soon as they are taken. From there we should be able to browse, organize, edit, and share them from any of our device, be they Macs, PC’s, iPads, or iPhones. In 2013, I don’t think that’s unreasonable to ask for.</p>

<p>In the next few weeks, I’ll be looking at several products and hopefully finding answers.  Today the journey starts with two separate app/service combos.  One is Adobe Revel and the other is Everpix.</p>

<h2 id="adobe-revelhttpwwwadoberevelcom"><a href="http://www.adoberevel.com">Adobe Revel</a></h2>

<p>{% img right /images/hv-adobe-revel.png %}</p>

<p>I was super-excited when I heard about Adobe Revel.  The service stores all your pictures in the cloud, and they give you free iOS and Mac apps to edit and manage them. Pictures are streamed to your iOS devices as needed freeing up a whole lot of space.  The apps are (supposedly) built on top of the same editing/browsing engine powering LightRoom and they are (actually) very well done.  The service is expensive ($5.99/month) but it promises a lot.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, it’s missing some important features.  First, it won’t store video clips and that means I need an entirely different workflow for them.  With two little kids, we take lots of these “long photos” and I like having them mixed in with the traditional photos. Second, my wife lives in a Windows world and Revel doesn’t provide a Windows app or even a web app. That means she can only browse our library on her phone and that’s a show stopper.</p>

<h2 id="everpixhttpwwweverpixcom"><a href="http://www.everpix.com">Everpix</a></h2>

<p>{% img right /images/hv-everpix.png %}</p>

<p>After my experience with Revel, I was cautiously optimistic about Everpix. It also stores all your photos in the cloud and has terrific iOS apps for browsing your collection, but it differentiates itself in three ways:</p>

<ol>
  <li>They automatically import photos from lots of places you might care about including your photo roll, Facebook, Instagram, and Flickr. That’s nice, but not terribly useful for me since I’m not exactly tied into the social network world.</li>
  <li>They have a terrific web app that works well on Mac and Windows.</li>
  <li>They don’t allow you to create albums or tag photos but instead rely on “science” to organize your photos for you.  Since I always plan to do more manual organization than I actually do, it’s nice that this is done for me. I tend to take several pictures of the same thing but never delete the bad ones–Everpix does a decent job picking the good ones and showing you those first.  In fact, I have Everpix configured to email me “random” “reminder” pictures from my collection everyday and it’s a lot of fun.</li>
</ol>

<p>The package is expensive ($4.99/month) if you want them to store more than the previous year’s worth of photos, and I’d be happy to pay if it weren’t for the downsides:</p>

<ol>
  <li>They don’t store video clips.</li>
  <li>You can’t edit pictures within the apps.</li>
  <li>They don’t store original images. Instead, Everpix stores compressed versions. I’m no photo snob, but I also don’t like losing information.</li>
  <li>You can’t easily export pictures. Once your pictures are inside, you can only get them out piece meal. I hate <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vendor_lock-in">lock-in</a>.</li>
</ol>

<p>I’m keeping an eye on Everpix because except for the editing, these issues seem eminently fixable and I’d consider using an external editor if I had to.</p>

<p>The quest continues.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Photos + iPhoto + iOS + iCloud = i'm underwhelmed]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/09/im-not-happy/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/09/im-not-happy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You may have heard that Apple announced a new iPad this week and that
they released a version of iPhoto that runs on iPads and iPhones. Most
folks seem to
<a href="http://daringfireball.net/linked/2012/03/07/iphoto-for-ios">like it quite a bit</a>,
while a few people have complained that it’s
<a href="http://brooksreview.net/2012/03/iphoto-confusion/">unintuitive</a> with
all its mysterious icons and gestures.  The problems with Apple’s
“system” for managing and editing photos go much deeper and I find it
incredibly frustrating because Apple has all the pieces for something
truly fantastic.</p>

<p><strong>What’s Crappy About the Current System:</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>The new iPhoto doesn’t run on the original iPad. I get it that I’m in
the minority of people who like to buy a product and run into into the
ground before upgrading.  And I get it that it that some of the filters
might be a little slow.  But Adobe Photoshop Express runs well.  I think
their public reasoning is that the experience on my iPad would be
sub-par.  And it conveniently gives me another reason to upgrade.
Fine.  I’ll give Apple a pass on this one.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Why are Photos and iPhoto separate apps?  I would understand if
iPhoto had a superset of Photos’ features, but it doesn’t.  Photos
allows me to move photos between albums, create new albums, and do some
minor editing.  iPhoto has more powerful editing tools and lets me share
photos with friends in different ways, but it doesn’t manage albums.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Any album management you do with Photos doesn’t get sync’ed back to
the desktop version of iPhoto.  So why would I possibly go to the
trouble of organizing my photos on the phone itself?  I would say this
was a bug, but it’s been there since iOS 5 was released in October.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Photo Stream is a feature that doesn’t fit into my work flow.  I can
easily access all the photos I’ve taken over the last 30 days on any of
my devices.  If I want a photo that I took earlier than that, I must
have moved it someplace more permanent during that 30 day window or I
have to go back to the device where I took the picture.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I can’t easily share photos between my Mac and my wife’s PC.  While
Apple might think this increases the chance that she will upgrade to a
Mac one of the days, this sort of thing just makes her dig her feet in
and resent the “Apple’s walled garden” even more than she already does.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><strong>What Would Be a Lot Better:</strong></p>

<p>It doesn’t have to be this way.  My perfect world looks more like this:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>iPhoto stores all my photos (and albums and events) in iCloud and
replicates them on my Mac.  Besides giving me a central repository that
I can access from anywhere, it’s also my off-site backup.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>iPhoto gets merged with the Photos app and it also accesses my photos
in iCloud.  This means any organization I do (e.g., moving photos
between albums) happens in one place: iCloud.  It also means that I
don’t have to actually store all the photos (and home video clips) on
the device itself—it can stream them as needed and manage a cache of
them so it seems fast.  </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Apple provides a web app for browsing and organizing photos that
could be used from a PC.  Even better, they would open up the iCloud API
so someone could write a version of iPhoto for the PC that used the same
iCloud photo store, but that seems unlikely to happen.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Photostream gets replaced by something simpler that just dumps all
photos taken by my devices into my iCloud photo store.  If they get
grouped as events (ala desktop iPhoto import) they’ll be easy to find
when I want to organize them.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>This dream system isn’t easy to build, but it’s not impossible either.
I just hope that Apple isn’t sitting there thinking their current system
is good enough or that it just needs a few minor tweeks.  And I really
hope that some improvements are in the pipeline.  If iOS 6 isn’t a lot
better, I might just have to switch my photo management to Google
Picasa.  And this Apple fan-boi certainly doesn’t want to do that.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
