<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[zebras | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/zebras/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-03T22:45:54-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zebras and Expertise on the Internet]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/12/07/zebras-and-expertise-on-the-internet/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/12/07/zebras-and-expertise-on-the-internet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Internet is full of people talking about stuff they don’t know much about. It’s common at <a href="https://answers.yahoo.com">Yahoo Answers</a> and <a href="http://www.answers.com">Answers.com</a>, but <a href="http://amazon.com">Amazon</a> reviews and <a href="https://www.wikipedia.org">Wikipedia</a> are rife with it too. Even when bloggers are experts in one area, they often write much more broadly. As <a href="http://idlewords.com/about.htm">Maclej Ceglowski</a> delightfully points out in <a href="http://www.idlewords.com/2005/04/dabblers_and_blowhards.htm">his article about Paul Graham’s lack of expertise on painting</a>, even the top of the food chain is not immune. </p>

<p>I think it’s fantastic. You don’t need to be an expert to have something interesting to say. Regular people notice things experts don’t, and they often have a perspective closer to mine. Non-experts can also be <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Funniest-Amazon-Product-Reviews/lm/RM0256CJKINZJ">incredibly entertaining</a>.</p>

<p>As a consumer I’m careful not to take anything too seriously, but many folks are more trusting than me of the average blogger. As a producer, I worry about this all the time, as I love thinking and writing about things on the edge (or well over the edge) of my expertise. When I wildly speculate I try to be clear about it, but I feel a little bad that some readers might not notice. </p>

<p>It has turned out that the most common way for people to find this site is by searching for “are zebras mean” or “do zebras bite.” I don’t know jack about this subject, but that didn’t stop me from writing <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/01/why-are-zebras-so-mean-and-horses-so-nice/">a few hundred words about it</a> a couple years ago.  African Safari guide <a href="http://www.quora.com/Rory-Young-1">Rory Young</a> recently wrote <a href="http://www.quora.com/Can-zebras-be-domesticated-and-trained/answer/Rory-Young-1">a terrific article on Quora</a> that shares real knowledge about why zebras can be so nasty.  It makes me very happy to be able to send my potentially disappointed visitors on to some real answers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why are zebras so mean and horses so nice?]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/01/why-are-zebras-so-mean-and-horses-so-nice/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/01/why-are-zebras-so-mean-and-horses-so-nice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In Jared Diamond’s
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Guns-Germs-Steel-Fates-Societies/dp/0393317552">Guns Germs and Steel</a>,
he asserts that zebras cause more injuries to zoo keepers than any other
animal. At least that’s how I remember it–I gave my copy away years ago
and never replaced it. In any event, it’s common knowledge that <a href="http://www.theblaze.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/Woman-bitten-by-Zebra.jpg">zebras are mean</a> and you can’t really tame them. Horses on the other hand are
every little girl’s best friend and they are happy to wear <a href="http://michellewrighton.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/dsc_4039.jpg">garlands of flowers</a> and <a href="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3111/2659658105_d8bccd69f1.jpg">nibble apples out of your hand</a>.  Why such a difference when
on the surface zebras just seem like striped horses?</p>

<p>Before I go any further I should say that the rest of this post is a
pure mixture of Wikipedia and armchair theorizing. You have been warned.</p>

<p>The answer has to be geography. The savanna is a
<a href="http://babeinthebush.blogspot.com/2009/08/luangwa-battlefield-of-hippo-part-5.html">tough place</a>. It’s
got cheetahs, hyenas, wild dogs (that also make <a href="http://kids.nationalgeographic.com/kids/stories/animalsnature/african-wild-dogs/">terrible pets</a>),
crocodiles (near the water anyway) and of course lions. Friendly and
laid back on the savanna equals dead. You have to be fierce
(zebras/meerkats), big (elephants/hippos/rhinos/giraffes) or fast and
high strung (impalas and ostriches) to survive.  But what about those friendly
monkeys that like to sit on shoulders in the bazaar?  Don’t they live on
the savanna? Well they can watch the action from the tops of trees and
eat their bananas in peace.  Zebras don’t have that option.</p>

<p>The temperate grasslands where horses evolved are a whole different
story. A lot more empty space and a lot fewer predators mean horses
could afford to just horse around all day before humans came along and
domesticated them.  Even the
<a href="http://www.fws.gov/rockymountainarsenal/kids/puzzles/PredatorsofthePrairie.pdf">temperate grassland predators</a>
are basically wild house pets. Wolves are genetically identical to dogs
and nothing else is big enough to give a horse more than a kick in the
shin.</p>

<p>Of course this very reasonable explanation doesn’t change the fact that
it’s grossly unfair that we can’t ride zebras around for fun–I mean
that would be so cool!  Maybe someday someone will splice nice genes
into the zebra (or striped genes into the horse) and I’ll get to live
the dream. Until then I’ll stick to the mountain bike for my riding
adventures. Oh well.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> This is <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014-12-07-zebras-and-expertise-on-the-internet.md">wild speculation</a> by someone who doesn’t know jack about zebras. If you want an expert’s opinion, based on real knowledge, check out <a href="http://www.quora.com/Can-zebras-be-domesticated-and-trained/answer/Rory-Young-1">Rory Young’s post on quora.com</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
