<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-24T08:35:07-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2011/12/21/first-post/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2011/12/21/first-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m sure there are hundreds (if not thousands) of articles on the web
about why one should (or shouldn&#8217;t) blog, but I think this is a very
personal question.  For me, the first (but not the only) reason is that
I want to consume less and create more.  Of course, blogging is
something I&#8217;ve thought about for a long time and
<a href="http://www.quora.com/Chris-Wake/Hidden-habits-of-ineffective-people">this article</a> was the straw that filled the camel&#8217;s stomach.</p>

<p>I also feel the only way to write better and more comfortably is to
write, and blogging is a natural and fun form of writing.  I think it
lends itself to the 15-30 minute chunks that I&#8217;m planning to invest.  I
tried Twitter a few months ago as way to scratch my blogging itch and
the experience confirmed for me that tweeting isn&#8217;t writing. Even my
tiny attention span is too long for Twitter.</p>

<p>But these two goals could have been accomplished with a personal
journal.  That didn&#8217;t feel right either, because I also aspire to
providing entertaining, useful, and inspiring content, though achieving
just one or two of these at a time is probably a more achievable goal.
Having an audience also has perks: It&#8217;s a great incentive to not put out
junk.  You don&#8217;t even need an audience to get this benefit&#8211;just a
potential audience.  I&#8217;m also looking forward to hearing occasional
feedback on stuff I write.</p>

<p>So what&#8217;s on the horizon?  To be honest, this might be one of those
projects I start that fizzles almost immediately.  I almost named this
Ghost Blog in honor of that possibility.  But instead, I went with a
more optimistically descriptive title because I have eclectic plans for
this space.  And while this is most definitely not a purely professional
blog, I don&#8217;t plan write anything that will prevent me from holding
elected office.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
