<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-26T10:15:30-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bathroom Fan Love Letters]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/10/30/bathroom-fan-love-letters/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/10/30/bathroom-fan-love-letters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two of my favorite bloggers (<a href="http://www.marco.org">Marco Arment</a> and <a href="http://brooksreview.net">Ben Brooks</a>) recently
published passionate <a href="http://www.marco.org/2012/05/06/bathroom-fan-timer-switches">love</a> <a href="http://brooksreview.net/2012/03/amazon-item/">letters</a> to the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B003TJAGPS">Panasonic WhisperCeiling</a> bathroom
fan, and in Marco&#8217;s case, a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00313JXB0">Leviton electronic timer switch</a>.  Since
our downstairs bathroom has had no fan at all for more than a year, and
our upstairs bathroom fan sounded like a jet engine (and took 20 minutes
to de-fog a mirror), I took this as a sign that it was time to upgrade.
It was harder than expected to find an electrician to install them, but
today was the big day.  It&#8217;s worked out pretty well for our upstairs
bathroom, but not so much for the downstairs bathroom.  In fact, I was
surprised by three issues that were unmentioned in the &#8220;reviews&#8221; I read:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>The Panasonic WhisperLite fan/light combo unit is approximately
square and it doesn&#8217;t fit in our downstairs bathroom because we have a
cast-iron drain pipe running 8.5&#8221; away from the stud where the fan has
to be mounted.  Drat.</p></li>
<li><p>The bulbs in the WhisperLite are compact-fluorescent and they send
out a very white light.  I like it, but my wife calls it &#8220;institutional&#8221;
and she says it reminds her of a public restroom.  This isn&#8217;t exactly
where anyone wants to be taking a shower, and if she doesn&#8217;t acclimate, I&#8217;m
hoping we can just change the bulbs to something a little softer.</p></li>
<li><p>The Leviton switch requires three wires (including a neutral) and our
downstairs bathroom only has two.  If I want a timer switch we either
spend $200 to run a new line (I&#8217;m not <em>that</em> crazy) or we get one of
those <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Intermatic-FD15MWC-15-Minute-Spring-Loaded/dp/B000EVS4WG">spring-loaded knobs</a> that screams hotel sauna.  For now, we&#8217;re
sticking with the old manual switch.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>To be fair, the new fan is very quiet and is working like a champ&#8211;our
upstairs bathroom isn&#8217;t small and during a leisurely shower the mirror
never fogged up.  And the Leviton timer is far more reliable than I was
about remembering to turn off the fan when it&#8217;s done its job.  But I
think there is a bigger lesson here: Some products that are perfect for
some people (or bathrooms) are not perfect for others, and we shouldn&#8217;t
let ourselves be blinded by the opinions of fan-bois.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A few comments on Apple's Big October Event]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/10/25/apple-observations/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/10/25/apple-observations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Apple&#8217;s big October product announcements are now behind us and I&#8217;ve
read more blogger reactions than I care to admit.  Even I&#8217;m surprised
that I still have a few somewhat original thoughts of my own to share.
Instead of simply being an &#8220;iPad mini&#8221; event Apple announced a whole
slew of products.  While some folks predicted some of the &#8220;extra&#8221;
stuff, I don&#8217;t think anyone expected the sheer quantity we saw.  That
said, I&#8217;m most excited about two products Apple did not announce:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>A new Thunderbolt display:</strong> The new iMac is beautiful and I can&#8217;t
wait until they translate it into a stand-alone display.  Less glare and
pixels closer to the glass will be terrific.  It will also give Apple a
chance to add a few ports that they neglected on the first rev: USB 3
and analog audio out.  And imagine how thin it will be when it doesn&#8217;t
have to also house a whole computer?</p></li>
<li><p><strong>The Fusion Drive:</strong> I know, I know, they DID announce this as an
option for the new iMac and Mac Mini, but I&#8217;m hoping they will sell it
separately so I can stick one in my 2010 iMac.  I really like the idea
of having the speed of an SSD and the size of a traditional HD without
the hassle of managing the pair.  We&#8217;ll have to wait for the iFixit
teardown to see if it has a new interface (and is thus incompatible) and
something tells me even if it has standard wiring, Apple will want to
reserve this feature as reason for folks to upgrade their old (but
perfectly usable) iMacs.  I can still dream.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>There&#8217;s been a lot of talk about how Apple is making a mistake by
pricing the iPad mini at $329 and leaving breathing room for the other
cheaper small tablets in the market.  I think Apple priced the product
as high as possible such that they will sell all the mini&#8217;s they can make
before the holidays.  If they didn&#8217;t, they would simply be leaving money
on the table.  When their supply chain gets up to speed some time in the
spring, I predict they will drop the price below $300.</p>

<p>I have very mixed feelings about the new iMac.  While it&#8217;s gorgeous and
powerful, I&#8217;m not sure I agree with the sacrifices Apple had to make to
achieve its super-model-thin curves.  Most iMac owners spend
the bulk of their time in <em>front</em> of their iMac where they never even
see the curves&#8211;my own is right up against a wall, and I&#8217;d have to lean
over and around my desk to appreciate the sides and back.</p>

<p>Apple loves to be first to cast old standards aside: Remember when the
iMac dropped the floppy drive?  I think they were the first PC maker to
stop using special keyboard and mouse ports and just rely on USB.  And
just a month ago they said goodbye to the venerable Dock Connector.  Now
they want to do the same thing to the optical drive.  For a notebook,
this makes perfect sense: In the last year there was exactly one time
when it would have been nice to mount a CD on my Air and that is
certainly not enough to justify the added weight and bulk of a drive.
At my desk, I do rip the occasional DVD or used CD.  And I&#8217;m certainly
not throwing my iMac in my bag when I head out on the town.  But maybe
Apple&#8217;s right.  Maybe folks should just keep an ugly old SuperDrive in a
drawer for those rare occasions when they need it.  Then they can
appreciate beautiful design every day.  Even if it means leaning over
their desks to do so.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Got My Country On]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/05/20/country/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/05/20/country</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There have been times in my life when I&#8217;ve listened to whatever music I
wanted whenever I wanted, but these days, I have a lot more constraints.
At work, I&#8217;m pretty underslept and need all the concentration I can
get&#8212;that means a silent work environment.  At home, I don&#8217;t feel right
cranking up Swedish death metal or even <a href="http://www.directlyrics.com/katy-perry-last-friday-night-lyrics.html">Katy Perry</a> in front of the
kids.  I get my classic rock fix while shopping in the supermarket late
at night, and in the car, all the trashy dance music stations I like are
full of static.</p>

<p>So I&#8217;ve started listening to <a href="http://licountry.com/">97.1, My Country</a>.
It comes in crystal clear and plays terrific new country.  Trust me that
I&#8217;m as surprised as you are as I&#8217;ve always been an &#8220;I don&#8217;t like
country&#8221; guy.  The twang and the stories and the guitar always bugged
me.  I&#8217;m not totally sure what&#8217;s changed, but over the last few weeks
I&#8217;ve Shazamed several songs that I&#8217;ve had to buy on iTunes.  Here are my
current favorites:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8peBUdlUNmM&amp;ob=av2e">&#8220;Country Must Be Country Wide&#8221;</a>
(by Brantley Gilbert): This is a straight-up country anthems and it&#8217;s so
rockin I swear Bon Jovi could have recorded
it in the mid 80&#8217;s.  It&#8217;s got awesome guitar and great lines like
&#8220;In every state there&#8217;s a station playing Cash, Hank, Willie, and
Waylon&#8221;.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SCuaCDPR0ao">&#8220;Got My Country On&#8221;</a> (by
Chris Cable): Another anthem, this reminds me of all those
rap songs that brag about being the biggest gangsta around.  Except this
gangsta is &#8220;Gonna do some chillin, chicken grillin and guitars&#8221;.  He
even says he&#8217;s &#8220;Trickin [his] truck like a Cadillac&#8221;.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bjKFb-4t_vg&amp;ob=av2e">&#8220;This&#8221;</a> (by Darius Rucker): This song couldn&#8217;t be more earnest: &#8220;Thank
God for all I missed Cause it led me here to this.&#8221;  I&#8217;ve never been a
Hootie and the Blowfish fan, but maybe I need to give them a chance.  Yikes.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7UCGzawJ1yg">&#8220;Drink On It&#8221;</a> (by Blake Shelton): This one is less sweet, but just as
earnest.  It&#8217;s about a country boy trying to get a girl drunk so he can
sleep with her.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Maybe this will country thing be a fad for me.  Or maybe I&#8217;ll be wearing Wranglers and
cowboy boots by this time next year.  I&#8217;ll definitely pass on the <a href="http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/factsheet/Tobacco/smokeless">Skoal</a> though.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Carle vs. Lionni: No Accounting for Taste]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/05/10/carle-vs-lioni/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/05/10/carle-vs-lioni</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most grown-ups, even those without kids, have heard of Eric Carle&#8212;He is
an extremely popular children&#8217;s book author who illustrates using
collage.  In fact, his <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Brown-Bear-What-You-See/dp/0805047905">Brown Bear Brown Bear What Do See</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Very-Hungry-Caterpillar-Eric-Carle/dp/0399226907">The
Very Hungry Caterpillar</a> have now supplanted Margaret Wise Brown&#8217;s
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Goodnight-Moon-Margaret-Wise-Brown/dp/0694003611">Goodnight Moon</a> as the standard gift for newborn kids.</p>

<p>Both my daughters celebrated Eric Carle week at school last month
and it got me thinking (again) just how over-rated he is.  He&#8217;s
either today&#8217;s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman_Rockwell">Norman Rockwell</a> or the kids&#8217; version of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Kinkade">Thomas Kinkade</a>
(&#8220;Painter of Light&#8221;).<a href="My">^1</a>  With a few exceptions (like <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Secret-Birthday-Message-Board-Book/dp/0694011487">The Secret Birthday
Message</a>), his books couldn&#8217;t be more repetitive and formulaic.</p>

<p>never miss a chance to bring up my favorite abusive alcoholic
religious nut-job artist, even if he did pass away recently.  And the
truth is, I think his work is pretty.  Just like Eric Carle&#8217;s.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m not saying his books have no redeeming qualities&#8212;the pictures are
pretty and they do appeal to the 1-2 year old crowd. But thats not
exactly the most demanding audience and his collage style isn&#8217;t even
unique. Leo Lionni started publishing picture books with collage back in
1959 and Lois Ehlert won a Caldecott in 1989 for <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Color-Board-Book-Lois-Ehlert/dp/0694010677">Color Zoo</a>.</p>

<p>Leo Lionni in particular deserves far more attention than he gets. The
only good thing about many of his books being out of print is that it
made it slightly easier to pick four Lionni books to send to my sister&#8217;s
family for Christmas.</p>

<p>Lionni was a late bloomer as a children&#8217;s book author as he had a full
career as a &#8220;real&#8221; artist before writing
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Little-Blue-Yellow-Leo-Lionni/dp/0688132855">Little Blue and Little Yellow</a>. His stories are quirky and many push
the envelope on what&#8217;s possible in a kids&#8217; book.  And every one has a
positive message.  For example in his first book, the characters are
splotches of color who get mixed up and turn green.  Their parents don&#8217;t
recognize them until they cry themselves apart, but then the parents recognize
their mistake and learn not to be so judgmental.</p>

<p>In <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Flea-Story-Leo-Lionni/dp/0905478266">A Flea Story</a>, you never even see the main characters. Instead you
only hear a dialog that&#8217;s reminiscent of Herman Hesse&#8217;s odd couple
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Narcissus-Goldmund-Hermann-Hesse/dp/B003NQOS4M">Narcissus and Goldmund</a>. One flea just wants to stay home on their
dog&#8217;s butt while the other longs for adventure. They travel together for
a while and then split to follow their own paths. Stories that appeal to
both adults and children are rare and those that do usually have two
sets of jokes (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rocky_and_Bullwinkle_Show">Rocky and Bullwinkle</a> is the classic example). Lionni
manages to make the same things funny to all ages.</p>

<p>One of R&#8217;s favorite Lioni stories is <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Matthews-Dream-Leo-Lionni/dp/067987318X">Matthew&#8217;s Dream</a>. Matthew is a poor
mouse who visits a museum with his school and is inspired to be an
artist. He dreams fantastic versions of his mundane world and paints
them into reality.  Often when R paints her own pictures she says &#8220;I&#8217;m
Matthew!&#8221;</p>

<p>In <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Alexander-Wind-Up-Mouse-Leo-Lionni/dp/0394829115">Alexander and the Wind-Up Mouse</a>, Alexander yearns to be a windup
mouse who is loved by the family instead of hated and chased with a
broom. He finds a magical lizard who will grant him his wish in exchange
for a purple pebble.  By the time he acquires one, the world has changed
and he learns to be careful what he wishes for.  R still looks for
purple pebbles to give to the lizard.</p>

<p>My one year old does like flipping through Eric Carle board books, but
as soon as she will sit still and let us read to her, she&#8217;s graduating to
Leo Lionni. The pictures are even more beautiful, the stories are
awesome, and the whole family can enjoy the ride.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[E-books and Kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/02/13/ebooks-and-kids/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/02/13/ebooks-and-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my house we read a lot of books to our kids.  We read after school,
on weekends, while traveling, during meals and (of course) right before
bed.  I was a voracious reader as a kid and I hope to impart this habit
and pure love of reading to my kids.  There&#8217;s something about reading a
book and visualizing the scenes and action in your mind that expands
your imagination much more than watching a movie ever could.  Reading
with your kids is also a just high quality parent-child time.  You never
have to press pause to stop and talk about issues raised in the story.</p>

<p>We also run a fairly gadget-friendly household.  My wife and I often
work at our computers, we both have iPhones, and our iPad is pretty much
our living room computer.  My three-year old has almost as many apps as
I do.  You would think we would be actively transitioning all our
reading to e-books, but we&#8217;re not.</p>

<h3><strong>The Good</strong></h3>

<p>E-books have a lot of advantages over physical books.  I love that you
can load up an iPad with a few hundred and it weighs no more than a
couple paperbacks.  While picture books look like junk (if they are
available at all) on the Kindle, they look fine on the iPad.  Some
e-books have a &#8220;read aloud&#8221; option and will repeat words and sentences
with a touch.  We don&#8217;t use these features much as a parent is usually the one
reading, but it&#8217;s nice to have the option.</p>

<p>Pricing of e-books is generally higher than the used physical book
price, but I think (hope?) it&#8217;s only a matter of time before that changes.
I especially hope that the publishers realize that parents would love to
buy &#8220;boxed sets&#8221; for a reasonable price.  If I could buy all 26 of the Curious
George books in the iBooks store for $52 (that&#8217;s $2 each) I&#8217;d jump on
it.  Instead, they charge between $3.99 and $8.99 each and I end up
spending a total of $3.99 on George.  We all lose out.</p>

<p>Availability is a similar story&#8211;it&#8217;s lousy now but I have high hopes it
will get better.  The great thing will be that once a book is in digital
format, there&#8217;s no reason it should ever go out of print.  So when I
want a mint condition copy of Amy Tan&#8217;s
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Sagwa-Chinese-Siamese-Cat-Amy/dp/0689846177">Sagwa, The Chinese Siamese Cat</a>
I don&#8217;t have to wait a single minute.  And if libraries can get in on
the action, their catalogs will be amazing.</p>

<h3><strong>The Bad</strong></h3>

<p>As I&#8217;ve already mentioned, the current pricing and availability
situation is atrocious for kids&#8217; books.  But these aren&#8217;t the only
problems.</p>

<p>My iPad has a 9.7 inch display.  The vast majority of the kids&#8217; books in
our house are a lot bigger.  That means you either see a small version
of the page or you&#8217;re constantly panning and zooming.  Graeme Bass&#8217;
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Legend-Golden-Snail-Graeme-Base/dp/0810989654">Legend of the Golden Snail</a>
is 12 inches by 22 inches open.  That&#8217;s 25 inches diagonal
(according to Pythagoras) and it&#8217;s going to be a long time before tablet
displays get that big.  The resolution on a printed page is a lot better
than my iPad today, but that could presumably <a href="http://www.macrumors.com/2012/02/12/ipad-3-to-pave-way-for-1080p-itunes-content-and-a-new-apple-tv/">change in the next month
or so</a>.
And you can completely forget about duplicating the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0394873742">Richard Scarry&#8217;s
Biggest Word Book Ever!</a>
experience&#8211;it opens to 32 inches by 24 inches.</p>

<p>Even if I&#8217;m willing to give in on all this stuff for my three-year-old,
there&#8217;s no way an e-book works for a one-year-old.  We have close to 100
board books, touch and feel books, and cloth books that can withstand
constant mouthing and provide good tactile feedback.</p>

<h3><strong>The Worrying</strong></h3>

<p>I&#8217;m mostly optimistic about the future of e-books for kids, but there
is a trend that worries me.  The kids&#8217; e-books that get the most praise
from critics and the highest ratings in the iOS app store tend to be the
flashiest and most movie-like.  Sesame Street&#8217;s
<a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/monster-at-end-this-book...starring/id409467802">The Monster at the End of This Book</a>
is a perfect example.  It lasted about 5 minutes on my iPad before I saw
my daughter&#8217;s eyes glaze over and I deleted it.  The Critter books
(e.g.,
<a href="http://itunes.apple.com/app/just-me-and-my-dad-for-ipad/id364723303">Just Me and My Dad</a>)
aren&#8217;t much better.  They at least let you read the story while you
click around the page trying to make animals do funny things.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s not that I think interactive features are a bad thing in e-books,
but I think they are a lot more appropriate in books for adults like
<a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/the-elements-a-visual-exploration/id364147847">The Elements: A Visual Exploration</a>
and Al Gore&#8217;s <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/id432753658">Our Choice</a>.
Even textbooks has a lot to gain from embedded movie clips, social
network integration, and dynamic graphs.  And I&#8217;m excited about the new
<a href="http://www.apple.com/ibooks-author/">iBooks Author</a> software enabling a
whole new wave of these kinds of books.</p>

<p>But God help us if children&#8217;s book publishers suddenly think they have tart up old
content to get us to buy it electronically.  Let my daughters and I
imagine <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Curious-George-Rides-Bike-Rey/dp/0395174449">George riding his bike</a> in the circus without turning it into
mini-game.  Let us laugh about <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Franklin-Messy-Paulette-Bourgeois/dp/0590486861">Franklin&#8217;s messy closet</a> without having to
interactively explore it.  And let us imagine the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Goodnight-Moon-Book-Margaret-Brown/dp/0061119776">old lady whispering
&#8220;hush&#8221;</a> without having to hear it out loud.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Albums]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/02/06/albums/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/02/06/albums</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m old. I grew up wandering around record stores trying to decide
whether to buy albums based on one or two songs I might have heard on
the radio, cover art, and what I knew about the band. These were big
decisions when I didn&#8217;t have much money and cd&#8217;s were $15-17 each.</p>

<p>Today&#8217;s online music world couldn&#8217;t be more different.  Kids these days
think about albums like they&#8217;re rotary dial phones&#8211;they download gobs of
music for free (e.g., BitTorrent) or they just listen to whatever they
want through Pandora or Spotify.  And when they do actually shell out cash,
it&#8217;s 99 cents per song.</p>

<p>But I live in the past and still agonize over album purchases.  Prices have
gone down and my income has gone up a little, but I like owning my
music legally and I still like listening to the set of songs an artist
chose to package together as an album.  Over time though, I&#8217;ve developed
a few rules to guide me in the decision process.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Learn from previous purchases if the band produces albums with a few
good tracks and filler.  Madonna and Metallica both produce tremendous
quality throughout while Katy Perry is more up and down.  The younger
the artist, the more careful you have to be (Yes I&#8217;m looking at you
Justin Bieber!)</p></li>
<li><p>&#8220;Best of&#8221; albums can be a treasure trove (e.g., Electric Light
Orchestra or Heart) if original album quality is spotty.</p></li>
<li><p>Beware of bargains&#8211;it&#8217;s those dreaded filler albums that are
most often on sale.</p></li>
<li><p>If you can restrain yourself from the impulse purchase, listen to the
album a couple times through on Spotify first.  A minute and a half
sample often isn&#8217;t enough.</p></li>
<li><p>iTunes has deluxe versions of many albums that contain remixes and
the occasional music video.  With YouTube, the video&#8217;s not much of a
draw, but I never regret the remixes which are often better than the
original versions.</p></li>
<li><p>Just because it&#8217;s a concept album doesn&#8217;t you shouldn&#8217;t. cherry pick
the best tracks. Judas Priest&#8217;s <em>Nostradamus</em> just isn&#8217;t that good even
though the second track (&#8220;Prophecy&#8221;) rocks.</p></li>
<li><p>As bends enter the twilight of their careers, albums get worse and
worse even though they can still produce individually good
songs. Metallica and Depeche Mode are great examples. This is the bright
side of a great band breaking up mid-career like The Beatles, Led
Zeppelin, or The Smiths.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Bottom line: The album may be dying, but it&#8217;s not dead yet.  At least
not in my little fantasy world.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[All Men Play on 10]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/01/28/all-men-play-on-10/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/01/28/all-men-play-on-10</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<pre>
  All men play on ten,
  Never gonna turn down again.
  All men play on ten,
  Never gonna turn down.
 
           "All Men Play on 10" 
           <em>Manowar, Sign of the Hammer</em>, 1984
</pre>


<p>Songs that celebrate rock and roll are a dime a dozen.  I mean, I love
Joan Jett&#8217;s &#8220;I Love Rock and Roll&#8221; and Ozzy Osbourne&#8217;s &#8220;You Can&#8217;t Kill
Rock and Roll&#8221; and even Huey Lewis&#8217; &#8220;Heart of Rock and
Roll&#8221; as much as anyone, but the idea is a little played out.</p>

<p>On the other hand, songs that literally <strong>demand</strong> to be played loud and
explicitly proclaim the band&#8217;s love of loud music are tremendously
under-appreciated.  It&#8217;s a much smaller genre, but I can (and do) listen
to these songs over and over.</p>

<p>Here&#8217;s a list of my favorites (<a href="http://c.itunes.apple.com/us/imix/play-it-loud!/id497298702">Ping version</a>):</p>

<ol>
<li>&#8220;All Men Play on 10&#8221; <em>Manowar</em></li>
<li>&#8220;Turn Up the Radio&#8221; <em>Autograph</em></li>
<li>&#8220;I Love It Loud&#8221; <em>Kiss</em></li>
<li>&#8220;Shout It Out Loud&#8221; <em>Kiss</em></li>
<li>&#8220;Louder than Hell&#8221; <em>Motley Crue</em></li>
<li>&#8220;We Like It Loud&#8221; <em>Rough Cutt</em></li>
<li>&#8220;Turn It Up&#8221; <em>Ted Nugent</em></li>
<li>&#8220;The Right to Rock&#8221; <em>Keel</em></li>
<li>&#8220;I Wanna Rock&#8221; <em>Twisted Sister</em></li>
</ol>


<p>The first track, &#8220;All Men Play on 10&#8221; by Manowar is not the most
popular, but definitely has the most testosterone.  Everyone has
probably heard &#8220;Turn Up the Radio&#8221; by Autograph as it got tons of
airplay during the eighties, but Kiss has to be the undisputed king of
the category with two contributions: &#8220;I Love It Loud&#8221; and &#8220;Shout it Out
Loud&#8221;.  &#8220;Louder than Hell&#8221; from Motley Crue wasn&#8217;t one of their hits,
but it&#8217;s always been one of my favorites.  Rough Cutt&#8217;s &#8220;We Like it
Loud&#8221; and Ted Nugent&#8217;s &#8220;Turn It Up&#8221; are more obscure, but still
classics.</p>

<p>The last two songs on my list are honorable mentions because they&#8217;re
really more straight up rock anthems than only tangentially suggest that
music shouldn&#8217;t be turned down.  Keel&#8217;s &#8220;The Right to Rock&#8221; says</p>

<pre>
  Don't let anyone tell you
  How to live your life
  We won't turn it off
  We won't turn it down
  'Cause it's our way of life
</pre>


<p>while Twisted Sister&#8217;s &#8220;I Wanna Rock&#8221; says:</p>

<pre>
  Turn it down you say,
  Well all i got to say to you is 
  Time and time again i say, "no!"
  No! no, no, no, no, no!
</pre>


<p>I&#8217;m absolutely certain I&#8217;ve left out some important tracks.  So any
suggested additions will be much appreciated!</p>

<h2>Update:</h2>

<p>I asked for help on
<a href="http://www.classicrockforums.com/forum/f7/play-loud-19367/">Classic Rock Forums</a> and got some
great suggested additions:</p>

<ol>
<li>&#8220;Loud&#8221; <em>Sammy Hagar</em></li>
<li>&#8220;Shout&#8221; <em>Grand Prix</em></li>
<li>&#8220;Blow Your Speakers&#8221; <em>Manowar</em></li>
<li>&#8220;Loud and Clear&#8221; <em>Autograph</em></li>
<li>&#8220;Play It Loud&#8221; <em>Diamond Head</em></li>
<li>&#8220;Play It Loud&#8221; <em>Saxon</em></li>
</ol>


<p>I can&#8217;t believe I forgot to include &#8220;Blow Your Speakers&#8221;, but the other five tracks
are new to me.  Every one is worth a listen&#8211;cranked up all the way of
course!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Downfall]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/01/14/downfall/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/01/14/downfall</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<object width="420" height="315"><param name="movie"
value="http://www.youtube.com/v/6Xx6Q77psrc?version=3&amp;hl=en_US&amp;rel=0"></param><param
name="allowFullScreen" value="true"></param><param
name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"></param><embed
src="http://www.youtube.com/v/6Xx6Q77psrc?version=3&amp;hl=en_US&amp;rel=0"
type="application/x-shockwave-flash" width="420" height="315"
allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true"></embed></object>




<object width="420" height="315"><param name="movie"
value="http://www.youtube.com/v/-VRBWLpYCPY?version=3&amp;hl=en_US&amp;rel=0"></param><param
name="allowFullScreen" value="true"></param><param
name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"></param><embed
src="http://www.youtube.com/v/-VRBWLpYCPY?version=3&amp;hl=en_US&amp;rel=0"
type="application/x-shockwave-flash" width="420" height="315"
allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true"></embed></object>




<object width="560" height="315"><param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/jD6B1CXXgM0?version=3&amp;hl=en_US&amp;rel=0"></param><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"></param><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"></param><embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/jD6B1CXXgM0?version=3&amp;hl=en_US&amp;rel=0" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" width="560" height="315" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true"></embed></object>


<p>These three videos are objectively hilarious.  I was going to write a
pithy insightful post about the humor found in the juxtaposition of the
contemporary and the mundane with one of the most evil and destructive
dictators of all time. It turns out I&#8217;m a little late to the
<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0363163/">Downfall</a> parody party.  If you are too, I highly recommend reading
this 2010 <a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/8617454.stm">BBC article</a> and of course browsing Youtube for <a href="http://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=downfall+parody">hundreds more</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Does School Suck?]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/01/11/does-school-suck/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/01/11/does-school-suck</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/5513063?portrait=0"
width="600" height="337" frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen
mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>The beginning of the semester has me thinking about
<a href="http://vimeo.com/5513063">this 30 minute video</a> I saw about a year ago
on teaching and schools by <a href="http://drtae.org">Dr. Tae</a>.  It&#8217;s
provocative and if you care about teaching, especially at the university
level, I encourage you to watch it.  I agree with most of what he&#8217;s
saying and try to incorporate a lot of his ideas in my own classes.  But
he&#8217;s just wrong about a few things.</p>

<p>Dr. Tae is unhappy with the state of schools in America&#8211;he says
they &#8220;suck&#8221; for a variety of reasons, but the main one is that they are
full of big impersonal lecture classes where the teacher/professor
stands at the front and pontificates while the students sit there
and take notes (best case) or update their Facebook status (worst case).</p>

<p>I don&#8217;t think lecture classes have to be all that bad&#8211;I had some very
good ones when I was an undergrad science major at
<a href="http://rpi.edu">Rensselaer</a> in the mid 1980&#8217;s.  At the time (and maybe
still) the institution took a lot of pride in it&#8217;s teaching.  Big physics
and chemistry lectures were full of very entertaining and illuminating
experiments and I definitely learned in that environment.  The
main problem with this set up is that it isn&#8217;t optimal&#8211;there are much
better ways to teach when the professor and students are in close
proximity.  I actually think the days of the big lecture are numbered as
there are several places people can go to get free high quality
impersonal video lectures on the internet.  You may have heard of
<a href="http://www.khanacademy.org/">Kahn Academy</a>,
<a href="http://www.apple.com/education/itunes-u/">iTunes U</a>, and
<a href="http://ocw.mit.edu/index.htm">MIT&#8217;s Open Courseware</a>.  I was very happy
to see one of Yale&#8217;s very best economics professors on the front page of
<a href="http://www.academicearth.org/">Academic Earth</a> earlier this week.
<a href="http://www.academicearth.org/courses/game-theory">Ben Polak&#8217;s game theory class</a>
is legendary here, and now anyone on earth can experience it (as a
non-interactive lecture) for free.  The point is that if you&#8217;re paying
gobs of money for an in-person university education, you deserve better
than that.</p>

<p>Dr. Tae goes on to say that university teaching is bad because schools
don&#8217;t hire great teachers&#8211;they hire and promote based on research. He&#8217;s
exactly right about this.  Not only is teaching ability ignored
during hiring, all the incentives for tenure track faculty are to spend
as little time as possible on teaching.  You just have to keep your
enrollments and student evaluations above pretty low thresholds.  I
don&#8217;t see how universities can improve without changing these hiring
practices and incentives.</p>

<p>As an aside, he&#8217;s pretty critical of the certification process that&#8217;s
required for getting most secondary school jobs.  In order to teach
science at the high school level, I think you should not only know a lot
about science, you should also know how to teach.  The certification
process (flawed as it is) is supposed to make sure you do.  I bet
Dr. Tae would be an amazing high school science teacher, but I&#8217;m not so
sure about all of his Northwestern physics faculty colleagues.</p>

<p>Dr. Tae hates grades; he calls them &#8220;coercive&#8221;&#8211;he feels that teachers
make students think the way they want them to think by holding grades
over their head.  I&#8217;ll concede that there are better ways to motivate
students to work hard than grades, but at the end of the day, the grade
is how someone who wasn&#8217;t in the classroom (like a prospective employer
or admissions committee) can judge what you learned in that classroom.
It provides information that&#8217;s just not readily apparent in an
interview.  So I&#8217;m not ready to just throw out grades all together.</p>

<p>Dr. Tae loves for kids (even adult kids) to ask questions and do
experiments to answer them.  I agree this is a great way to learn and
stay excited about science.  It&#8217;s also true that having a strong base of
knowledge (be that facts or methods) is important and that means
students have to read and listen to stuff they might think is boring in
the moment.</p>

<p>Dr. Tae is exactly right when he says the secret to learning is to &#8220;Work
your ass off until you figure it out&#8221;.  Failure is far more common than
success in science and learning.  So often I have students who come to
me and say &#8220;I read the article for today and didn&#8217;t understand it.
Something is terribly wrong!&#8221;  No it&#8217;s not.  Learning is hard.  Reading
science, doing math, writing well, making an argument, they all take
serious effort.  None of it is supposed to be like reading a newspaper
article or watching tv.  It&#8217;s totally normal to have to read something
several times to get it.</p>

<p>Dr. Tae talks a bunch about how fundamentally broken our schools are
with their bad teachers and semester-long courses and grades.  But then
he says there are a lot of ways we can &#8220;polish the turd&#8221;.  He&#8217;s right about
this too.  My students ask their own questions, work in small groups,
and spend big chunks of time one-on-one with me.  I reward curiosity,
creativity, and hard work in my grading.  Many of them continue research
they started in my classes after the semester is over.  My bet is that
all this is true of Dr. Tae&#8217;s classes when he teaches physics.</p>

<p>Before you throw out schools as currently conceived, you have to be
ready to replace them with something better.  Here&#8217;s where I think
Dr. Tae&#8217;s train goes off the rails.  His ideas about &#8220;distributed
teaching&#8221; are totally crazy.  He seems to think that we should all teach
what we know part-time and all together, this will give people a better
educational experience than they would get in college.  He gives
Wikipedia as an example.  I love Wikipedia, but reading about a topic
there is a far cry from taking a course on it with someone who has spent
their life studying it.</p>

<p>Like so many things, it all comes down to incentives.  Knowledge is a
public good, but someone has to produce it and communicate it.  That&#8217;s
not free.  A system that depends on people volunteering their time is a
system that produces an extremely sub-optimal amount of knowledge.
There&#8217;s probably a role for government in subsidizing this production,
and I think this a great argument for not
<a href="http://www.universityofcalifornia.edu/news/article/21271">dismantling our public universities</a>.
But I do think there&#8217;s vast room for improvement to the education
system.  In the meantime I&#8217;ll continue to polish turds in my own
classes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comments on Blogs]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/01/06/comments-on-blogs/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/01/06/comments-on-blogs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s become very trendy on tech blogs to not allow comments on articles.
And at least a couple of folks
(<a href="http://mattgemmell.com/2011/11/29/comments-off/">Matt Gemmell</a> and
<a href="http://brooksreview.net/2011/11/gemmell-comments/">Ben Brooks</a> have been
actively trying to convince other bloggers to turn off their comments too.  I
agree that if you&#8217;ve got a popular blog (and maybe a thin skin), turning
off comments can make your life easier.  I would even agree that on
popular blogs (and websites more generally) many (most?)  comments don&#8217;t
really further the discussion.  In fact, I read most of my blogs
(including Matt&#8217;s and Ben&#8217;s) inside
<a href="http://reederapp.com/">an RSS reader</a> and so I don&#8217;t even see any of
the comments that might or might not be there unless I click through to
the site itself.</p>

<p>But I have three objections to their position on comments.  First, when
you don&#8217;t get much traffic (I&#8217;m looking at you High Variance) and you
know most of the people reading your blog, it&#8217;s really nice to get as
much feedback as possible and I think comments are the best way to do
that.  If someone reading my article has something interesting to say
about it, the comment gives them an audience.  They can always email if
they want to say something privately,</p>

<p>Second, I often like to read what other people have to say about an
article (whether I&#8217;ve written it or not), even when I have to wade
through some less than insightful stuff.  Again, the signal-to-noise
ratio is particularly high in the early days of a blog when it&#8217;s mostly
friends reading, but even on a big messy site like
<a href="http://www.espn.com">espn.com</a> I think it&#8217;s fun to see the popular
reaction to a story.  And yes, I get it that the sample is not even
representative of the readership let alone the general population.  I
think <a href="http://slashdot.org">Slashdot</a> is a terrific example of how
constructive (and entertaining) discussion of an issue can happen on the
web through comments.</p>

<p>Third, there&#8217;s this high horse attitude that if people have something to
say about an article, they should just write it up as an article on
their own blog.  And if the original author reads it and wants to
comment back, they will write another article on their blog.  I&#8217;m sorry,
but this just doesn&#8217;t happen.  I mean, I&#8217;ve seen blogs comment on other
blogs, but in almost every case the debate stops there.  And it&#8217;s
impossible for someone visiting the original site to see the
conversation at all.  And, believe it or not, there are people with
intelligent things to say that don&#8217;t have a blog.</p>

<p>Maybe I&#8217;ll change my tune in the future when I&#8217;m drowning in haters and
forum-spam, but I have a feeling that&#8217;s going to be a while.  Until
then, comments will stay turned on.</p>

<p><a href="http://highvariance.net/post/15402930759/update-comments-on-blogs">UPDATE HERE</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bad Behavior in Kids' Books]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2011/12/30/bad-behavior/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2011/12/30/bad-behavior</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We do a lot of reading in my house and I don&#8217;t pay much attention to
age/reading levels.  R (who just turned three) likes books geared to her
own age as well as lots that are for older kids.  Most of the time, this
works out well.  She misses some nuance (e.g., the rich description of
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Wizard-Oz-Puffin-Classics/dp/0141321024">The Wizard of Oz</a>)
and sometimes the main point (e.g., the literalness of
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Amelia-Bedelia-Collection-Read-Book/dp/0060542381">Amelia Bedelia</a>),
but she&#8217;s almost always entertained.  And I think she gets a lot out of
pushing the envelope.  The best examples of this are science and nature
books.  We&#8217;ve been reading the Pooh Encyclopedias
(<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Very-First-Encylopedia-Winnie-Friends/dp/0786834064">Nature</a>
and
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Very-First-Encylopedia-Winnie-Friends/dp/0786834080">Animals</a>)
and
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Chickens-Arent-Only-World-Nature/dp/0698117786">Chickens Aren&#8217;t the Only Ones</a>
for months and she&#8217;s learned a ton.</p>

<p>The place where we get in trouble is when we read books for older kids with bad
behavior.  I don&#8217;t mean where the main characters are having fun and
they do bad stuff like jumping on the bed (like those damn
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Five-Little-Monkeys-Jumping-Along/dp/0618732764">monkeys</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Skippyjon-Jones-Judy-Schachner/dp/0142404039">Skippyjon Jones</a>)
even though these are also inspiring in the wrong way.  I mean those
books that try to teach kids to behave by showing them how not to
behave.  The prototypical example is
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Berenstain-Bears-Too-Much-Teasing/dp/0679877061">Berenstein Bears and Too Much Teasing</a>
which we read over Thanksgiving.  What we learned is that saying &#8220;Nah
nah na nah nah&#8221; and calling your father &#8220;Flub-a-dub&#8221; are hilarious.  The
novelty wore off fast (for me, not her).  When we read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Best-Friends-Frances-Read-Book/dp/0060838035">Best Friends for Frances</a> we learned
that doing things with No Boys Allowed is fun.  When we read
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Dinosaurs-Play-Their-Friends/dp/B001VF5I1Y">How do Dinosaurs Play with Their Friends?</a> we learned to hog up toys
and say &#8220;Mine!&#8221; and when we read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Do-Dinosaurs-Say-Goodnight/dp/0590316818">How do Dinosaurs Say Goodnight?</a> we
learned to demand even more stories than usual before bed.  R learned
that fighting (and making up) with your friends is fun from the otherwise truly wonderful <a href="http://www.amazon.com/What-Busy-Day-Gyo-Fujikawa/dp/1402768192">Oh What a Busy Day</a>.</p>

<p>In fact, the only case I can think of where the authors actually pull
off this trick is
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Be-Friend-Friends-Families/dp/0316111538">How to Be a Friend</a>
which is a remarkably great manual from which most adults would learn a
thing or two.  R has yet to copy the bad stuff and is on the edge of her seat
throughout.  It even gets a lot of requests (i.e., &#8220;Excuse me, will you
read this?&#8221;)</p>

<p>The lesson we&#8217;ve learned in our house is to recognize and quarantine
these books as fast as possible and hope we remember to bring them out
again when the girls are ready.  Of course, we&#8217;ll probably be reading
them to R as her younger sister A listens in and then goes and jumps on her bed!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2011/12/21/first-post/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2011/12/21/first-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m sure there are hundreds (if not thousands) of articles on the web
about why one should (or shouldn&#8217;t) blog, but I think this is a very
personal question.  For me, the first (but not the only) reason is that
I want to consume less and create more.  Of course, blogging is
something I&#8217;ve thought about for a long time and
<a href="http://www.quora.com/Chris-Wake/Hidden-habits-of-ineffective-people">this article</a> was the straw that filled the camel&#8217;s stomach.</p>

<p>I also feel the only way to write better and more comfortably is to
write, and blogging is a natural and fun form of writing.  I think it
lends itself to the 15-30 minute chunks that I&#8217;m planning to invest.  I
tried Twitter a few months ago as way to scratch my blogging itch and
the experience confirmed for me that tweeting isn&#8217;t writing. Even my
tiny attention span is too long for Twitter.</p>

<p>But these two goals could have been accomplished with a personal
journal.  That didn&#8217;t feel right either, because I also aspire to
providing entertaining, useful, and inspiring content, though achieving
just one or two of these at a time is probably a more achievable goal.
Having an audience also has perks: It&#8217;s a great incentive to not put out
junk.  You don&#8217;t even need an audience to get this benefit&#8211;just a
potential audience.  I&#8217;m also looking forward to hearing occasional
feedback on stuff I write.</p>

<p>So what&#8217;s on the horizon?  To be honest, this might be one of those
projects I start that fizzles almost immediately.  I almost named this
Ghost Blog in honor of that possibility.  But instead, I went with a
more optimistically descriptive title because I have eclectic plans for
this space.  And while this is most definitely not a purely professional
blog, I don&#8217;t plan write anything that will prevent me from holding
elected office.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
