<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[kids | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/kids/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-02T10:50:14-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fun and Games at the Library]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/21/fun-and-games-at-the-library/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/21/fun-and-games-at-the-library</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-alphabet-rug.jpg"></p>

<p>Consumption, analysis, and <a href="http://randsinrepose.com/archives/the-builders-high/">creation</a>. A lot of my time can be assigned to one of these three categories, and while all three have their place, I find it very easy to slouch into consumption and shirk creation. I feel better about myself when I’m in balance, so I’m always looking for opportunities to make things. That’s one reason the girls and I have been making up so <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/12/pretty-pretty-princess/">many</a> <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/21/non-violent-dungeons-and-dragons-for-kids/">new</a> <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/17/sequence-for-kids/">games</a> lately. </p>

<p>Our trips to the library have always been more than simply dropping off and picking up bags of books. We like to take our time and hang out too. These are our three favorite games to play while we’re there:</p>

<p><strong>1. The Rug Game:</strong> The main branch of the New Haven Free Public Library has a huge children’s room and in the middle is a big circular rug with the alphabet and associated pictures printed around the edge. Since R was little we’ve played a game where I tell her to find something and she has to run to an appropriate letter. We started with the basics:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Run to the octopus!</li>
  <li>Where is the dog?</li>
  <li>Find the birthday cake!</li>
</ul>

<p>We moved on to more tricky questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What keeps you dry in the rain? (Umbrella)</li>
  <li>Who has 8 arms? (Octopus)</li>
  <li>Find a red fruit! (Apple)</li>
</ul>

<p>When other kids join in, the questions have to have at least two correct answers so everyone can find their own letter:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Who swims in the water? (Fish, octopus, turtle)</li>
  <li>Find a fun toy! (yoyo, kite)</li>
  <li>What has a shell? (Turtle, egg)</li>
</ul>

<p>As the kids get older, the questions get downright tricky:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What rhymes with cry? (Pie)</li>
  <li>Who has a princess for a daughter? (Queen)</li>
  <li>Who is black and white? (Zebra)</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>2. Rainbow Magic:</strong> R is currently obsessed with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rainbow_Magic">this series</a> of beginning chapter books. They are formulaic in the same way <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dora_the_Explorer">Dora and Boots</a> are formulaic beginning readers and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hardy_Boys">The Hardy Boys</a> are formulaic tween boy schlock. The books come in sets of seven (e.g. <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0545175178/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0545175178&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=highvari-20">The Pet Fairies</a>) and each book involves two girls (Rachel and Kirsty) helping a particular fairy retrieve some magic item before Jack Frost and/or his goblins can get it. The books are quite harmless, and the thing is kids <em>like</em> formula–figuring it out is like solving a puzzle. B is not so into the stories yet, but she’s been swept up in R’s enthusiasm, and at the library she loves to gather up a big pile of the books, pore over the covers, and flip for pictures of goblins. We recently made up a game where she files her books by the first letter of the fairy’s name on the alphabet rug. Fun and even a little educational!</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-picture-book-scavenger-hunt.jpg"></p>

<p><strong>3. Picture Book Scavenger Hunt:</strong> This is a game I’ve been trying to get the girls excited about for years, and during our last library outing it finally took hold. I made a list of animals, characters and objects, and the girls had to find a picture of each in a book. We settled in between two big shelves and started digging. It was surprisingly difficult–I would have told you that a third of all picture books contain princesses, fairies, pirates, and dogs. It turns out dogs are easy to find, but everything else took a little hunting. </p>

<p>I’ve written a lot recently about games we’ve made up and had a good time playing. I hope some of you are inspired to try a few out. I hope even more that you are inspired to create your own games. That’s the most fun of all.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pretty Pretty Princess!]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/12/pretty-pretty-princess/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/12/pretty-pretty-princess</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-pretty-pretty-princess.jpg"></p>

<p>I was talking to one of R’s former pre-school teachers the other day, and she mentioned a board game she used to play with her daughter and husband called <em>Pretty Pretty Princess</em>. It involved moving pieces around the board (ala Candy Land) and collecting real jewelry that you get to wear. You win when you put on the tiara and shout out “I’m a Pretty Pretty Princess!” My first thought was that both of my girls would love this game and I should look for it on Amazon as soon as possible.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> My second thought was that we already owned most of the parts and it would be even more fun to make the game ourselves.</p>

<p>We started by rolling out a big piece of paper and taping it to the dining room table. I drew a winding track and divided it into spaces. The girls went to town with their markers and drew bracelets, necklaces, rings, and earrings all over the board while I tracked down some dice (<a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/21/non-violent-dungeons-and-dragons-for-kids/">not hard</a>) and our tiaras. We selected our game pieces from our bag of <a href="http://www.schleich-s.com/en/US/toys/">Schleich animals</a> and My Little Ponies, grabbed our kids’ jewelry box, and started playing.</p>

<p>Rolling the dice and moving her piece the right number of spaces were challenges for B (not quite three years old), but picking jewelry out of the box made it all worthwhile. R enjoyed the game even though the pace was a little bit slow. We’ll play this version a few more times, but I’m already looking forward to making it more complicated by adding forks in the road, special squares, and some weird rules. </p>

<p><strong>Footnotes:</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I did eventually look up <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00000IWHP/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B00000IWHP&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=highvari-20">the game on Amazon</a> and it doesn’t look any more fun than our homemade version.  And holy mackerel, it’s $99!<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Our Favorite Board Game: Sequence for Kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/17/sequence-for-kids/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/17/sequence-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/hv-sequence-for-kids.jpg"></p>

<p>With the holidays upon us it seems like every geek blogger I read has been recommending family-friendly board games. <a href="http://macsparky.com/blog/2013boardgames">MacSparky</a> sent me to <a href="http://fannypackmafia.com/blog/2013/12/8/my-favorite-board-games-from-2013-part-one">Fanny Pack Mafia</a>, <a href="http://www.marco.org/2013/12/12/gift-guide-actually-used-for-a-year">Marco</a> says <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0007YDBLE/?tag=marcoorg-20">Power Grid</a> is really good, and <a href="http://kottke.org/13/11/how-to-quickly-get-good-at-chess">Kottke</a> is sending me to <a href="http://www.gautamnarula.com/how-to-get-good-at-chess-fast/">Gautam Narula</a> to improve my chess game. This is all well and good, but these games are a bit much for my 2.5 and 5 year old kids.  Maybe that’s why our favorite game hasn’t been on any of these lists.</p>

<p>The rules for <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00005UM9P/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B00005UM9P&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=highvari-20">Sequence for Kids</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=highvari-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B00005UM9P" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
are simple. The game starts with each player getting three cards and a pile of their own colored chips. The cards have animals on them as does the board which is a 6x7 square grid. A turn consists of playing a card and putting one of your chips on a square that has the same animal that was on the card. Players replenish their hand by picking another card from the deck at the end of their turn. The goal is to get four chips in a row. There are two “magical” animals: The Unicorn card lets a player put their chip on any square while the Dragon card lets a player remove any chip from the board.</p>

<p>Many games for little kids are designed simply to teach rule following and maybe some hand-eye coordination as the player spins a spinner or picks a card and moves their token along a track. Chutes and Ladders and Candyland are the canonical examples of a genre that rots adult brains. Sequence includes enough strategy that kids are challenged, and enough randomness that they have a chance to win against adults.</p>

<p>The set of skills kids can learn (or practice) while playing is surprisingly rich:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Forward thinking:</strong> Players need to make sequences of two before they can make three and then four to win. They need to recognize when their opponent is about to win, and then block them if possible. </li>
  <li><strong>Patience:</strong> Players should save their special cards for when they need them for defense or offense.</li>
  <li><strong>Reasoning about uncertainty:</strong> I wonder if my opponent has a Lion in their hand and could win next turn?  I wonder if I could pick a Lion from the deck for my next turn? Maybe two Lions have already been played and none are left!</li>
  <li><strong>Pattern recognition:</strong> Where are my winning opportunities? Four in a row wins whether it is across, down or diagonal.</li>
  <li><strong>Creativity:</strong> R thinks the magic animals are the best part of the game and we often make up our own rules to create more. Sometimes the Kangaroo card lets you put down a chip on a Kangaroo and another square next to it. Sometimes the Shark can eat another animal and let you put your own chip in its place. The possibilities are endless.</li>
  <li><strong>Reading:</strong> The game even promotes reading in a subtle way. The cards have pictures of the animals for non-readers, words for the animal  (e.g. “Penguin”) for learning readers, and even a fun name for the animal (e.g., “Percy”) for actual readers. </li>
</ul>

<p>Perhaps the best part of the game is that it’s easy to modify the game for players of any age. We often play with cards face up.  This makes reasoning about your opponent’s next move a little clearer and has two other big advantages: Little uncoordinated hands don’t have to try to hold three cards at once, and it’s a lot easier to teach strategy when you can see what cards your kid is holding.  I’ve also played a fairly rule-free version of the game with one and two year-olds where we just deal out cards and place chips on the board. These kids love the animals and the bright colors of the chips and even like matching the animals to the squares on the board. </p>

<p>Sequence for Kids really is fun for the whole family!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Second Time Around]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/16/kid-book-review-second-time-around/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/16/kid-book-review-second-time-around</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the best things about having a second child is getting to do all your favorite little kid things again.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Near the top of that list for me is re-reading our best picture books, and L, at 2.5 years old is just now appreciating the stories as well as the pictures. These five books have been particularly popular over the last few weeks:</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-uncle-elephant.jpg" title="[title “Uncle Elephant”]" ></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Uncle-Elephant-Can-Read-Book/dp/0064441040">Uncle Elephant</a> (written and illustrated by Arnold Lobel) Like all of Arnold Lobel’s books, the illustrations are classic, the stories are clever, and the messages are deep. A boy loses his parents at the beginning and he bonds with his Uncle who takes care of him until his parents come back. Among other things, they walk in the garden, sing songs, and grant wishes to spiders. Uncle Elephant is the grandfather everyone wanted when they were growing up. We’ve also been enjoying Lobel’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s?url=search-alias=aps&amp;field-keywords=lobel%20frog%20and%20toad">Frog and Toad stories</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="">Pup and Hound Catch a Thief</a> (written by Susan Hood, illustrated by Linda Hendry) This criminally under-rated series of books is published by Kids Can Press where it gets lost in a slew of mediocre tales of poorly behaved cats (<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mittens-My-First-Can-Read-ebook/dp/B006JQTQNG">Mittens</a>) and dogs (<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Pizza-Sam-Kids-Can-Read/dp/1553373316">Sam</a>). The rhymes and artwork are cute, and the stories have twists at the end that both L and I can appreciate.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/hv-lyle-walks-the-dogs.jpg" title="[title “Lyle Walks the Dogs”]" ></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lyle-Crocodile-Walks-Dogs/dp/B006Z31NI4">Lyle Walks the Dogs</a> (written by Bernard Waber, illustrated by Paulis Waber) Not to be confused with <a href="">Zack’s Alligator</a> Bridget, Lyle the Crocodile is as sweet as Bridget is sassy. In this counting book Lyle builds a business through competent hard work and positive word of mouth.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Curious-George-Rides-Bike-Rey/dp/B0099R035M">Curious George Rides a Bike</a> (written and illustrated by H.A. Rey) My personal favorite George book when I was a kid, I’m happy to report that L loves it too, even if she does admonish George for not wearing a helmet.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-there-are-cats-in-this-book.jpg" title="[title “There are cats in this book”]" ></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/There-Are-Cats-This-Book/dp/0763639230">There Are Cats in This Book</a> (written and illustrated by Viviane Schwarz) I’m cheating here since we just discovered this book a month ago at the library, but it’s just so good and so perfect for the two year old age group that I had to include it. It follows in the interactive mode of Herve Tullet’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Press-Here-Herve-Tullet/dp/0811879542">Press Here</a> asking the reader to do things (like toss a ball of yarn or look inside a box) and reacting to them. The only potential downside is that the pop-up features are not totally robust, but isn’t that what Scotch tape is for? I just realized there’s a well-reviewed sequel (<a href="http://www.amazon.com/There-Are-Cats-this-Book/dp/0763649546">There are no cats in this book</a>) and can’t wait to check that out too!</li>
</ul>

<hr />
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>One of the worst things about a second child is having to do all your least favorite things again, but I’m a glass-half-full guy. <a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Scepter and the Crown]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/26/scepter-and-crown/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/26/scepter-and-crown</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-scepter-and-crown.jpg"></p>

<p>R turned five this weekend and we celebrated with a party, some amazing cupcakes, a trip to the carousel, and a brand new <a href="/blog/11/21/non-violent-dungeons-and-dragons-for-kids/">Nonviolent Dungeons and Dragons for Kids</a> adventure. This one was more puzzle-based and less monster-focused than The Haunted Castle. It was also a little longer and more open to different routes through it.</p>

<p><strong>Props (all optional)</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>a scepter</li>
  <li>a crown</li>
  <li>Some sort of horn</li>
  <li>box with coins and jewels</li>
  <li>frog boots</li>
  <li>rope</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Introduction</strong></p>

<p>King Ricardo (your father, if you’re a princess) has a special mission for you: You must deliver this scepter and crown to your cousin Princess Soldina for her birthday in three days. He gives you a <a href="/images/nvdndfk/land-of-the-scepter-and-the-crown-map.pdf">map of the area</a>–it looks very far and there is no direct route. The King then smiles and gives the players a beautiful magic flying carpet. He says it is very fast and should get you there in plenty of time. It will also return to the King as soon as you step off of it.</p>

<p>What do you do?</p>

<p>Your flight is very pleasant until you start to cross the Black Mountains. That’s when a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roc_(mythology)">roc</a> notices you and starts swooping in for a closer look.</p>

<p>What do you do? </p>

<p>The player can try to avoid each roc capture attempt by rolling 3d6 under her dexterity, but eventually the roc will get them. If they roll exactly their dexterity, they fall and just barely grab the edge of the carpet where they are gently plucked off by the roc.</p>

<p><strong>1. The roc’s cave</strong></p>

<p>The roc flies north and brings you to her nest and then flies off again, in search more food for her chicks. The nest is in a cave high on a mountain (see <a href="/images/nvdndfk/land-of-the-scepter-and-the-crown-dm-map.pdf">DM’s version of the map of the land</a>).  There are two hungry baby rocs in the nest.  They don’t like jokes, but can be soothed to sleep with a lullaby. The cave entrance is a cliff dropping thousands of feet to sharp rocks. You get a little dizzy looking down. In the back of the cave, it looks like a tunnel goes further into the mountain.</p>

<p>There is a weird glowing mold growing on almost all the walls of the caverns that provides enough light to see.</p>

<p>The DM should draw the roc’s cave on a blank sheet of paper for the players and extend the map as the players explore without showing <a href="/images/nvdndfk/caverns-of-the-scepter-and-the-crown-dm-map.pdf">his own complete map of the caverns</a>.</p>

<p><strong>2. The abandoned bedroom</strong></p>

<p>It looks like someone has been living in here recently, but they aren’t here now. There are dirty clothes and some fresh food and drink.  If the players search the room, they will also find a long coil of silk rope, a sharp knife, and some magic green boots with frog eyes on the toes.  These will let the wearer jump long distances.</p>

<p><strong>3. The giant spider nest</strong></p>

<p>The giant spider is working in the back of a giant web–she is busily wrapping her silk around something large and doesn’t notice the players. In fact, she has caught Boris, the human who lived in the bedroom on food stolen from the roc’s babies.  He made his rope from the spider’s silk, but he got too close to the spider recently.  The group may try to rescue him, though the spider is a tough opponent. She is scared of fire though. The web is extremely sticky.  Players will need to either be very strong to escape or use a knife to get out.</p>

<p><strong>4. The chasm</strong></p>

<p>The bridge that once crossed this chasm broke long ago.  Players will need the frog boots and possibly rope to get across. The cave turns into a tunnel on the other side and winds down for a long way on the other side to the underground river.</p>

<p><strong>5. The underground river</strong></p>

<p>The tunnel opens up into a small cave with a low ceiling and a fast-moving river running through it. Next to the river is a small boat. If you want to make the adventure tougher, you could put a hole in the boat and make the players figure out a way to repair it. The river flows underground for several miles and then exits the mountain flowing another several miles to the ocean. Show players on the King’s map.</p>

<p>Just before the river takes a sharp turn and joins the ocean is an unusual multi-colored arched rock about the size of a horse. It is called rainbow rock, but the players don’t know that yet. It can’t be seen directly from the ocean.</p>

<p><strong>6. The Pirates</strong></p>

<p>After being swept past the odd arch-shaped rock, the players’ boat is caught in the ocean’s current moving south.  They soon encounter a pirate ship.  The pirates (led by Pink Beard) are a rough crew but not very hostile.  They are looking for a treasure chest that is supposed to be buried under something called Rainbow Rock.  The pirates have been unable to find it thus far. The players have the option of telling the pirates where it is or keeping quiet.</p>

<p><strong>7. Rainbow Rock</strong></p>

<p>If the players dig under the rainbow rock, they will find a treasure chest. Inside are gold coins, jewels, and a horn covered with intricately carved animals of all kinds.  It is a magical Horn of Animal Summoning.  When blown, some animal will come to the aid of the player.  Some animals are more helpful than others. Aquarius the whale will come if the players blow the horn at this point. He can tow their boat along with the chest all the way to Princess Soldina’s Castle in time for the birthday party.</p>

<p><strong>How it went</strong></p>

<p>R started by creating a new Princess character and enjoyed coloring her map of land throughout her adventure. R was initially very cautious exploring the caves–I had to goad her into moving down the tunnels–but by the end she was feeling quite comfortable underground. She was also wary of the frog boots and certainly didn’t want to tangle with the giant spider. The whole adventure took about half an hour and my favorite moment was at the very end, when she said “Can we play another story now?”</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
