<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[kids | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/kids/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-10-08T07:29:24-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let's Wait Awhile]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2016/10/11/lets-wait-awhile/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2016/10/11/lets-wait-awhile</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/la-et-ms-janet-jackson-control-30-years-later-20160204.jpeg"></p>

<p>My girls are precocious. The seven year-old reads beyond her age, climbs trees higher than she should, and seems pretty interested in boys. The five year-old wants to do anything her older sister does. Right now, I feel like I have a handle on the situation, but the future scares the heck out of me. As Kelly Oxford has made <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/10/11/us/politics/sexual-assault-survivor-reaction.html">abundantly clear</a>, girls are vulnerable and many boys out there take advantage of it. And as <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/trump-recorded-having-extremely-lewd-conversation-about-women-in-2005/2016/10/07/3b9ce776-8cb4-11e6-bf8a-3d26847eeed4_story.html">Donald Trump has personified</a>, many of these boys never grow up and instead just move to more powerful positions.</p>

<p>My plan is to continue to keep a close eye on my girls and try to keep the lines of communication open. I’ll also do my best to encourage friendships with kids that aren’t quite so risk-loving. Another idea I’ve had is to start playing more music with positive messages–Maybe it can be a subliminal influence. Here’s the start of a play list and I’d appreciate suggestions for additions:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mxS_f1JWBfc">“Let’s Wait Awhile” (Janet Jackson)</a> Abstinence isn’t something usually <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super_Bowl_XXXVIII_halftime-show_controversy">associated with Janet</a>, but this song (and <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/08/09/arts/music/janet-jackson-control-anniversary.html">this whole album</a> are just so good.</li>
</ul>

<pre>
There's something I want to tell you
There's something I think that you should know
It's not that I shouldn't really love you
Let's take it slow
When we get to know each other
And we're both feeling much stronger
Then let's try to talk it over
Let's wait awhile longer
</pre>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HWZisnZ-RGE">“We Don’t Have to Take Our Clothes Off” (Jermaine Stewart)</a>  This song was huge when I was in high school, and I might have to wait until the girls are in high school to play it. If it hasn’t yet occurred to you to take your clothes off to have to have a good time, I’d rather not implant the idea. And drinking cherry wine? That’s just going to lead to taking clothes off!</li>
</ul>

<pre>
So come on baby, won't you show some class
Why do you have to move so fast?
We don't have to take our clothes off
To have a good time
Oh no
We could dance and party all night
And drink some cherry wine, oh
</pre>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=v_yTphvyiPU">“Just a Kiss” (Lady Antebellum)</a> In my mind, this might be the perfect country song. Beautiful singing, catchy as heck, and a great message.</li>
</ul>

<pre>
Just a kiss on your lips in the moonlight
Just a touch of the fire burning so bright
And I don't want to mess this thing up
I don't want to push too far
Just a shot in the dark that you just might
Be the one I've been waiting for my whole life
So baby I'm alright, with just a kiss goodnight
</pre>

<p>I’ve put <a href="https://open.spotify.com/user/126603624/playlist/7EDMZEBVhg3Fl1T6CUSoc9">the list on Spotify</a> too.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adi Gildor (1969-2015)]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2015/09/05/adi/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2015/09/05/adi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-adi.jpg"></p>

<p>Adi Gildor was my best friend. He died last week. I still can’t believe it, but this is what I said at his memorial service:</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;">
I know I'm not the only person here who thought of Adi as their best friend.  He was that kind of guy. We grew up together. We were still growing up together and we were supposed to grow old together. I gave the best man toast at his wedding, but I <strong>never</strong> ever thought I would be up here speaking today.
</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;">
I can't tell you how many times Adi called me over the last few years and said "We should go back to Moab to go mountain biking again" or "Let's road trip to Mexico again," and I would say "Definitely, but not yet." Just like Adi, I've got two little kids, but my wife isn't as cool with me going off on adventures without her as Rose was. We won't get to do those things together now, but at least we did them the first time.
</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;">
Adi and I met when we were in high school. We were just a couple of nerdy teenagers who thought we knew more than we actually did. Adi taught me how to curse in Spanish, how to appreciate Shakespeare, and how to recognize the hot peppers in Thai food. That last one, he taught me only <strong>after</strong> I ate one. He thought it was hilarious. We learned together how to avoid getting stuffed into lockers by the football players. And then we both grew four inches in college and didn't have to worry about that sort of thing anymore.
</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;">
There were things about Adi that never changed over the years.
</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;">
He was the most generous guy I knew. He would literally <strong>give you the shirt</strong> off his back. One of my favorite shirts is one that Adi left at my house a few years ago. When I said I liked it he told me I should keep it. It was brown and a little shiny and had snaps. Rose remembers it. He would send me shoes and jackets too. We even had an ugly t-shirt club where we would send each other shirts and dare each other to wear them. I think I still have a My Little Pony shirt he sent me.
</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;">
Adi knew how to have a <strong>good time</strong>. We went snorkeling in the South Pacific in a tiny country called Palau. We hiked and camped all over the 4 corners. We even bike-packed in Baja California where we drove on some of the worst roads you'll ever see in my Honda CRX. It was never the same after that trip. I mostly stopped doing these adventures with him when kids were born, but he certainly didn't stop!
</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;">
You always <strong>knew where you stood with Adi</strong>. When he was mad, he would say I'm mad at you. And he would tell you why. Sometimes it was reasonable: I called you a week ago; Why haven't you called me back? Sometimes it wasn't: I told you to watch that movie a week ago; Why haven't you watched it yet?
</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;">
And he always had a keen sense of <strong>justice</strong>. I remember one time he was living in Colorado Springs walking his dog Eloise late at night. Some guys drove real fast right by them and Adi ran after them yelling. The car stopped and three of them got out of the car to ask if he had a problem. The guy talking was a lot bigger than Adi, so Adi hit him first. When he went down, the guy's two "friends" took off. After giving the guy a pretty hard time, Adi felt sorry for him and I'm pretty sure Adi ended up giving him a ride home.
</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;">
When Adi realized that the artsy Colorado Springs movie theater only gave student discounts to students at four year colleges, he wrote a letter about it to the local newspaper. And just a couple months ago he told me about confronting a couple guys at his gym who had the nerve to be drinking smoothies in the hot tub. 
</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;">
Adi would listen to advice, but at the end of the day, Adi <strong>followed his heart</strong>. Well after he finished college, he enlisted in the army and went through boot camp. Then he got tired of living in Massachusetts and moved to Colorado Springs. Why? He liked the high desert, the cheap living, and the great hiking, biking, and snowboarding. And it had a very good public library. 
</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;">
Adi figured out what he wanted and just did it. The best example of all is that he married the woman he loved. Sure, she was a lot younger than him. Sure, she wasn't Jewish. He didn't care. He loved her so he married her.
</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;">
I never thought I'd see Adi "settle down", but he did and he did it on his own terms. He grew up, he took responsibility, but he never stopped having fun. He had two kids, but they only made his life <strong>more</strong> fun. When I talked to him last week he told me about how had been running in the woods with Henry. They would play crazy make-believe games and when Henry got tired, Adi would put him on his back and run around some more.
</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;">
Adi never cared about stuff. He cared about his friends, his family, and his lived experience. He loved <strong>doing</strong> stuff. Snowboarding, hanging out with people, arguing about ideas, making plans, reading. That's why the way he died is so shocking. He <strong>loved living</strong>.
</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;">
In my heart I believe that what happened that night was an aberration. It shouldn't have happened and it was not who he was 99% of the time. I'm not going to deny what happened at the end, but I'm going to remember the Adi in my heart that loved his family, loved his friends, and loved life.
</p>

<p>You can also watch the whole <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=T5Ax2diXNzY">Memorial Service</a> (including this eulogy) on YouTube. You can learn more about Adi and give money to his sons Henry and Arlo at <a href="https://www.youcaring.com/sons-henry-joe-arlo-ben-419264">YouCaring</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Growing up with a single mom]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2015/06/21/single-mom/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2015/06/21/single-mom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-mommy-and-me.jpg"></p>

<p>A good friend who is a single mom recently published <a href="https://singlemomintheivyleagues.wordpress.com/2015/06/20/fathers-male-role-models-and-raising-a-boy/">an article about the angst she feels on Father’s Day</a>. She wonders aloud what her son might or might not be missing out on by growing up with only a mom in the house. I think there are a lot of misconceptions out there, and wanted to share my personal experience as an only (and male) child of a single mom.</p>

<p>Let’s get the biology nonsense out of the way first. I did not need a man around to teach me how to pee, how to shave, or about the birds and the bees. Holding your penis and aiming it at the toilet just isn’t that hard. Shaving a face is not that different from shaving legs. As for sex, my friends told me about the basics, and my mom taught me to treat women decently. There isn’t any secret knowledge about sex that fathers have to transmit to their sons. Or if there is, I seem to be getting by just fine without it.</p>

<p>I didn’t live with a “male role model,” and I’m not sure what I would have gained from it. People are different in many ways beyond gender. I didn’t have an athlete role model or a computer nerd role model in the house either but still managed to be a decent amateur swimmer and eventually a professional programmer. Then there’s the fact that role models don’t have to live with you. Teachers, neighbors, coaches, parents of friends can all be role models. My local <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/?title=TRS-80_Color_Computer">Radio Shack Color Computer</a> Club was loaded with role models. And finally, my mother was a terrific role model as a teacher, an artist, and a lifelong learner.</p>

<p>I did grow up with many “traditionally male” interests, and sure, it would have been nice to have a dad around who could show me how to hold a bat or identify sports cars we saw in the wild. But I had many other interests too. My mom took me to concerts, and plays and museums. She indulged my creative side and brought me to the beach all summer long. I got to have long uninterrupted conversations with her because it was just the two of us.</p>

<p>To be honest, the only thing I feel like I missed out on by having a single mom was getting to closely observe two adults in a healthy relationship. It took me some extra time to figure out how to create and maintain these kinds of relationships since they were new. On the other hand, many kids in two parent families don’t get to see that either and instead learn bad tastes and behaviors that are hard to break. I got to start with a clean slate.</p>

<p>The bottom line is that my mom did a wonderful job raising me, and I think most single moms have all the tools they need: Their kids are in great hands.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Are they laughing with me or at me? #IMWAYR]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2015/03/23/kbr-laughing/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2015/03/23/kbr-laughing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-book-with-no-pictures.jpeg"></p>

<p>Over the last couple weeks, the most popular book in our house, by far, has been <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Book-No-Pictures-B-J-Novak/dp/0803741715">The Book with No Pictures</a> by B.J. Novak. The gimmick is simple: When someone reads the book out loud, they have to say all the words. No matter how silly or ridiculous or preposterous or even nonsensical they might be. The reader may even have to sing the occasional song about eating ants for breakfast. Novak takes full advantage of this rule to induce huge laughs from the audience. The idea is partially ripped off from (inspired by?) Mo Willems’ <a href="http://www.amazon.com/We-Are-Book-Elephant-Piggie/dp/1423133080">We are in a Book</a>, but it’s executed so well I can’t really complain.</p>

<p>Ever since we got this book, both kids (age 3 and 6) beg every grown-up that enters our house to read it. And how can you say to no to a kid begging you to read a book? Especially when you don’t know what’s coming? With many funny kids books, we can all laugh together. With this one, the kids are definitely laughing <em>at</em> the reader. Luckily this is a situation where quantity matters more than quality.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/imwayr.jpg"></p>

<p>Sheila at <a href="http://bookjourney.wordpress.com/">Book Journey</a> started <strong>It’s Monday! What are You Reading?</strong>, and Jen over at <a href="http://www.teachmentortexts.com/">Teach Mentor Texts</a> along with Kellee and Ricki at <a href="http://www.unleashingreaders.com/">Unleashing Readers</a> host kidlit versions.  All three sites are great places to find new books for yourself and your kids.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Winter Classics #IMWAYR]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2015/02/16/kbr-winter-classics/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2015/02/16/kbr-winter-classics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/hv-brave-irene.jpeg"></p>

<p>Now that we are deep into a winter that will seemingly never end, it’s time to look at a few classic children’s books that can carry us through.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Brave-Irene-William-Steig/dp/0312564228">Brave Irene</a> (by William Steig, 1986) William Steig is one of the few authors I know who doesn’t shy away from true drama. He’s better known for <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Sylvester-Magic-Pebble-William-Steig/dp/1442435607">Sylvester and the Magic Pebble</a> which features parents bawling their eyes out over their long lost son, but in this book Irene has to brave a serious winter storm at night to deliver a dress her mom has made:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Irene pushed forward with all her strength and–sloosh! thwump!–she plunged downward and was buried. She had fallen off a little cliff. Only her hat and the box in her hands stuck out above the snow.
Even if she could call for help, no one would hear her. Her body shook. Her teeth chattered. Why not freeze to death, she thought, and let all these troubles end. Why not? She was already buried.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Don’t worry, it all turns out wonderfully at the end, but boy, both my girls (and I) were on the edge of our seats the whole time!</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-100-dresses.jpeg"></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Hundred-Dresses-Eleanor-Estes/dp/0152052607">The Hundred Dresses</a> (written by Eleanor Estes, illustrated by Louis Slobodkin, 1945) R and I really enjoyed this Newberry Honor winning chapter book about two girls who tease a poor immigrant girl from Poland into moving out of town. Both girls feel bad, but one feels worse about it than the other. I don’t want to give anything away, but the story feels amazingly real, right down to the messy ending. </p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/hv-moominland-midwinter.jpeg"></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Moominland-Midwinter-Moomins-Tove-Jansson/dp/0312625413">Moominland Midwinter</a> (by Tove Jansson, 1957) Last week I was a <a href="http://teachinginhighered.com/podcast/035-eliciting-using-feedback-students/">guest on the Teaching in Higher Ed podcast</a> and I one of my recommendations was <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Finn-Family-Moomintroll-Moomins-Jansson/dp/0312608896">Finn Family Moomintroll</a>, another book in this amazing series of stories about Moomintroll and his friends and family which take place in magical land far to the north. The stories and characters are rich enough to appeal to adults but clear and exciting enough to capture kids’ imaginations too. It’s criminal how under-appreciated (and unknown) these books are in the United States.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/imwayr.jpg"></p>

<p>Sheila at <a href="http://bookjourney.wordpress.com/">Book Journey</a> started <strong>It’s Monday! What are You Reading?</strong>, and Jen over at <a href="http://www.teachmentortexts.com/">Teach Mentor Texts</a> along with Kellee and Ricki at <a href="http://www.unleashingreaders.com/">Unleashing Readers</a> host kidlit versions.  All three sites are great places to find new books for yourself and your kids.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
