<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[kids | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/kids/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-06T01:40:06-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Recycling Monsters]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/06/recycling-monsters/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/06/recycling-monsters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-monster-manual1.jpg" alt="The Monster Manual, First Edition--Sweet!" /></p>

<p><a href="kids">Mommy blogs</a> are full of articles about how to reuse stuff you have lying around the house as toys for your kids, but for whatever reason, the trappings of my teens and twenties have not proven very entertaining for the girls. The awesome car stereo I had in my Honda CRX is long gone and it might be a while before the girls age into my dartboard and collection of heavy metal cd’s. Even my old volleyballs are not as fun as the purple and pink balls we picked up for 99 cents at the drug store. </p>

<p>So I was thrilled the other day to find my four year old happily flipping through my First Edition <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monster_Manual">Monster Manual</a>. If you didn’t spend big chunks of high school playing Dungeons and Dragons, you might not have heard of it. It’s basically an encyclopedia of monsters with illustrations that look a lot like what a high school student might doodle on their notebook. Check out this <a href="http://www.somethingawful.com/d/dungeons-and-dragons/wtf-monster-manual.php?page=1">review</a> at <a href="http://www.somethingawful.com">Something Awful</a> to get a flavor for it.</p>

<p>The big question you’re probably asking yourself right now is “Good God! How is that appropriate for kids?” If you happen to have a <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/10/13/mythical-creatures/">kid that loves monsters</a>, the pictures won’t give her (or him) nightmares–they’re that cheesy.  The only real issue is the occasional topless demon or mermaid, but that’s not much different than the average clothing catalog. The only caveat is that you probably don’t want to read the monster descriptions out loud. I made this mistake with the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ochre_jelly">ochre jelly</a> and won’t make it again. </p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Update: The World's Most Underrated Kids' Toy]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/22/couch-cushions-update/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/22/couch-cushions-update</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Three important points I forgot to make when <a href="/blog/2013/01/20/couch-cushions-rule/">talking about couch cushions</a> the other day:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Turning the cushions into toys wasn’t actually my idea. I went into the kitchen to get a drink, and when I returned to the living room, the girls had already started the party!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Unless you run an unbelievably clean house, tossing your cushions around is going to raise a fair amount of dust and maybe even fire retardant.  Not great for kids with bad allergies or asthma.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You may have noticed in my picture that the seen was augmented with dog beds. We don’t currently have any pets, but our old dog beds do let us slightly reduce the probability of this whole exercise ending up at the emergency room.</p>
  </li>
</ol>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The World's Most Underrated Kids' Toy]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/20/couch-cushions-rule/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/20/couch-cushions-rule</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m always looking for toys that will give the kids good exercise indoors for the winter.  Last Christmas, we bought <a href="http://www.magiccabin.com/Toys-and-Creative-Play/Wooden-Indoor-Climbing-Dome.htm">this climbing dome</a> (on sale) and it’s been awesome.  I can’t even count the number of rainy days, snowy days, even plain-old cold days when the girls have monkeyed around on it while I sort, fold, and hang laundry in our basement.  This year I spent a bunch of time trying to decide whether or not to buy <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Constructive-Playthings-Soft-Play-Forms/dp/B0010AN0JC">these fancy soft play forms</a>.  I’m so glad I didn’t, because I had something even better right under my nose (actually my butt) the whole time.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-cushion-runway.jpg"></p>

<p>Our couch has three bouncy seat cushions and three cushy back cushions.  It’s amazing how many cool things you can do with them.  Just today, we piled them all up to make a cushion mountain.  We surrounded it with pillows and tried jumping up and over the whole thing.  Then we slowed down and made a cushion fort where the cushions were the walls and blankets were the roof.  The finale was the cushion runway shown here.</p>

<p>Not only are couch cushions a ton of fun for all ages, the price is right and they don’t require any storage.  Hurray!</p>

<p>Update: <a href="/blog/2013/01/22/couch-cushions-update/">Here</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Toy Trains for Little Kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/29/toy-trains-for-little-kids/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/29/toy-trains-for-little-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-trains.jpg" alt="Fisher-Price Geotrax…and a few fairies…OK, a lot of fairies" /></p>

<p>When I was a kid, a big part of the Christmas season was visiting my grandmother and immediately racing down to her basement to run the trains around the track.  I loved the big styrofoam mountain, the rumbling of the engine on the metal tracks, and the feeling of industrial omnipotence when holding the controls in my hand.  </p>

<p>Now that I have my own kids, I want them to have fun with trains during the holidays too.  But my kids are little and a big <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lionel-Pennsylvania-Flyer-Freight-Train/dp/B004L3IKQI">Lionel rig</a> isn’t good match yet.  Traditional train sets are expensive, delicate, and a ton of work to set up.  And I don’t feel good about having toddlers poking around in the miles of requisite electric wiring.</p>

<p>Last year my brother and sister-in-law sent us their old <a href="http://www.fisher-price.com/en_US/brands/geotrax/index.html">Fisher Price Geotrax</a> and it’s absolutely perfect for kids under six years old.  The exact set we inherited is no longer for sale, but the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Fisher-Price-GeoTrax-Control-Timbertown-Railway/dp/B001W1YG56">Timbertown Railway</a> is pretty close.  Ours is made up of a whole bunch of snap-and-go plastic tracks and includes bridges, a windmill, and even a station that will load packages onto your train.  The engine is battery-operated and makes a pleasant chug-chug noise, while the remote control is big, wireless, and easy for small hands to operate.  It looks good, is super-easy to put together,  and happily chugs around our tree.    We have enough track to try out several configurations and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Fisher-Price-GeoTrax-Train-Rail/dp/B000NW2D4Q">expansion packs</a> are just an Amazon one-click away.</p>

<p>Another great thing about the set is that it’s seemingly  indestructible.  It’s been stepped on, kicked, and disassembled (by kids and adults) numerous times and nothing’s ever actually broken.  You can’t even forget to turn it off and run down the batteries because it stops automatically after ten minutes of non-interaction.</p>

<p>Bottom line: We all love it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Neighborhood Caroling]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/26/neighborhood-caroling/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/26/neighborhood-caroling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Our neighborhood is so awesome. For the last three years (at least) on the evening before Halloween nearly all the kids gather for the Pumpkin Parade.  Everyone wears their costumes and brings their carved pumpkins in a wagon or a stroller and we all proceed to march around the block.  Afterward we have hot cider and cookies and catch up with our friends.</p>

<p>This summer a new neighbor hosted the world’s greatest barbecue block party.  There was terrific turnout and highlights included a hammock filled with up to 10 little girls at any given moment, a sunshine piñata, and a giant cannoli.  The party gave birth to an email list which spawned a Facebook group which then led to last week’s first annual neighborhood Christmas caroling.  We are positively swimming in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/aw/d/0743203046">social capital</a>!</p>

<p>About 40 kids and grown ups arrived at Cathy and John’s house at 5:45 for cookies and hot cocoa and some warm up songs. R especially enjoyed belting out The Twelve Days of Christmas as she had been practicing it over dinner all week. Then we all walked and sang along the Pumpkin Parade route and finished with even more cookies and cocoa.</p>

<p>In the interests of making a super-fun event even better next year, I’ve done some thinking and I’ve got some ideas:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Plan on singing a lot of songs.  We had a printout of about 7 that didn’t last long enough and folks weren’t ready to repeat them after the first round.  And very few people knew more than the first verse of even the most popular carols.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Suggest that folks download a caroling app that has lyrics.  I think the best one is <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/sing-along-to-50+-christmas/id481902746?mt=8">Sing Along to 50+ Christmas Carols</a> but it’s $4.99 which might be more than most folks (not me!) want to spend.  It’s got the music and big fonts and karaoke style moving lyrics.  A cheaper option is <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/christmas-carols/id296111618?mt=8">Christmas Carols</a> for 99 cents that has they lyrics for more than 100 songs but no fancy graphics.  The best part about having an app is that it only requires one hand–you don’t need a hand for the lyric printout and another for the flashlight.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Have someone in front that sets a slow pace.  Our group quickly spread out such that the back couldn’t hear what the front was singing.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Put up signs so everyone in the neighborhood knows it’s happening.  One of the best parts of the experience was when families would come out on their stoops to listen.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Pick a charity and collect money for it along the way. This might make some people uncomfortable, but I think it would be worth it.  Certainly to the folks who would receive the donations  would appreciate it and this seems like a great opportunity to exercise (not exorcise) the Christmas spirit.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Merry Christmas everyone!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
