<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[kids | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/kids/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-16T11:13:21-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Stars Align]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/09/05/the-stars-align/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/09/05/the-stars-align</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-bike-and-shoes.jpg" title="[title “R’s bike and my shoes”]" ></p>

<p>Several years ago my wife and I spent a week in Costa Rica during the rainy season. As expected, it rained most of our trip but was warm and fun nonetheless. And those brief windows when the sun came out were magical. I think raising kids is a little like this–mostly great, but some periods when all the stars align that are truly amazing. </p>

<p>When R was born, my exercise regime changed.  I stopped going to the gym or training for particular events, but I still managed to get out a couple times a week for a run and stay in reasonable shape. When B was born, planned exercise (i.e., beyond chasing kids and racing to work) disappeared as two kids is a bit more work than one and something had to give.</p>

<p>Some people are good at combining exercise with parenting.  They backpack with their kids and push them around with jogging strollers.  My kids don’t like activities where they aren’t active–they like pushing strollers more than sitting in them.  Also, sleep is like gold in our house and our kids sleep best in beds. I would never risk waking a sleeping child miles from home because I hit a pot hole.  I’ve also seen other parents go bike riding with their kids.  These parents sometimes look like they are having fun, but they certainly aren’t getting more exercise than if they were out for a leisurely stroll.</p>

<p>Last week, I entered a fantastic window in my parenting career where I can finally join the ranks of the co-exercising parents.  R is getting pretty comfortable on her bike and I’ve been putting on my running shoes to run next to her on her rides. Yesterday she said she loved the feel of the wind in her face as she rode down a long hill. She calls the bike trail near our house “the country” even though it runs behind the local strip malls on one side, and the highway and an office park on the other.  To her credit, we also saw a ground hog cross the trail and watched ducks congregate in a little pond.</p>

<p>I’m terribly out of shape and she currently tires easily, but we’re both getting better as she learns the fine arts of balance and pacing. It also helps that R and I have had a fair amount of one-on-one time as B’s school started full-time last week but R’s won’t be full-time until next week. Unfortunately, I think this window is destined to be brief.  R will eventually want to ride faster and longer than I want to run.  I don’t know when that time will come, but it won’t surprise me if it’s soon given the current trend.  Every day she’s substantially more comfortable on the bike and she loves speed.</p>

<p>Going on these bike rides has been incredibly fun and I’m just trying to focus on the moment and appreciate them.  I’m also already hoping to do it all again in a couple years with B.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Too Soon?]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/06/09/too-soon/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/06/09/too-soon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I loved the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Oz_books">Wizard of Oz</a> when I was a kid. Not the movie and not just the book, but the whole series of books and the whole world of Oz and the whole host of amazing characters. L. Frank Baum wrote 14 books and by the end of second grade I had read them all. The Scarecrow, the Patchwork Girl, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Gump#The_Gump">the Gump</a>, the Cowardly Lion, and the Hungry Tiger (just to name a few) were some of my best friends. Given that my daughter R has a wild imagination and a voracious appetite for books, you can’t blame me for introducing  these stories as soon as possible. Actually, it was too soon.</p>

<p>We started reading a seriously condensed picture book version when she was about two years old. She thought it was terrific and for months all she wanted to do was to act out the story. She was Dorothy for Halloween last year, and right around R’s 4th birthday, we read a chapter of the unabridged <em>Wizard of Oz</em> every night. She loved it and even though it revved her up a little right before she was supposed to go to sleep, we finished it and dove right into the <em>Land of Oz</em>. Jack Pumpkinhead and the Sawhorse were as fun as the original characters and we zipped through <em>Ozma of Oz</em> where we got to meet our first Oz princess.</p>

<p>We hit a wall with <em>Dorothy and the Wizard of Oz</em>. The invisible bears were just too scary. That night it took a little longer than usual to get to sleep and the next night, R wanted to read something else. </p>

<p>Last weekend we had a similar experience.  As soon as it got warm enough, R has been zooming around on her pink Dora bike with training wheels. We would go as fast as we caould around the block and I would run down the hills to keep up with her. She was looking a little cramped and since the seat wouldn’t go up any higher, I thought it was time for a new bike. Our awesome local shop (<a href="http://www.thedevilsgear.com">The Devil’s Gear</a>) had a used 16” bike that was perfect and we picked it up. It didn’t have training wheels and R said that was fine with her.</p>

<p>I also thought since B just turned two, she was ready for her first bike. We decided to pick up a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/MyKick-Balance-Bike-Cotton-Candy/dp/B009T2SITU">Burley MyKick</a>. It’s got two wheels and no pedals so you learn to balance right away. My friend Google tells me it’s easier to transition to a “real bike” from one of these than from a bike with training wheels.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, we did not have the fun-filled weekend of bike-riding that I was hoping for.  As soon as we got home, we learned  that both kids were too little for their new bikes. Seats only go so low. The only short term benefit was that R enjoyed racing the MyKick up and down the driveway.</p>

<p>This weekend things got a lot better. R decided she was ready to ride her new bike and this evening we did 4 laps around the block!  It didn’t take long for her to master the straight-aways up hill and down hill. But the seat is still too high and she needs support to start or stop. She’s going to be a menace to herself and our neighbors for a while yet.</p>

<p>Books and bikes are pretty low stakes things, and I don’t feel so bad starting them on the early side. We’ll return to Oz at some point. Our new bikes will be be there when the girls are totally ready. But some decisions are a lot harder to recover from if you make a mistake. Parents of kids who were born late in the year know where I’m going with this: When is the right time to start school?</p>

<p>I’m a December birthday and I started first grade when I was 5. My mom had to convince the principal to bend the rules since technically I was supposed to be 6 by September 1. Throughout elementary, middle school, and high school I was the youngest kid in the class. I was pretty emotionally immature. I had regular “accidents” until third grade. I always had trouble with girls and I think at least part of that was being younger than they were. And yet I feel strongly that it was the right decision for me. I was curious and intellectually ambitious and competitive. I would have been bored silly if I had been held back and even as it was, I wish I’d been challenged more. </p>

<p>I’ve also met lots of people with late in the year birthdays that were pushed into school early, and they’re bitter about it to this day. They really believe they would have had a more comfortable and successful school experience had their parents waited. And maybe their parents should have waited.</p>

<p>The trendy thing to do now is to wait. I swear it all started when Malcolm Gladwell’s book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Outliers-Story-Success-Malcolm-Gladwell/dp/0316017922">Outliers</a> came out in 2008.  In the first chapter, he tells a story about how elite Canadian hockey players were all born in January or February. When these guys started playing, they were the biggest, most skilled kids on their age-graded teams and so were plucked out and given additional training/coaching. Maybe being the oldest kid in kindergarten or first grade helps with academics too. Maybe.</p>

<p>I strongly believe the “right” answer about when to start school depends on the kid (and the school). R was born in late November and will be starting kindergarten next year (before she turns 5). We will be watching her closely. The academic part of school will be no problem. She’s already got great reading and math skills and she loves to learn. On the social/emotional side, she acts her age. That might be hard when most of her friends are older. We are definitely open to having her repeat kindergarten at a new school. We’re also open to her moving on to first grade. We’re not open to doing something just because everyone else is doing it. We’ll make the decision based on her.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Feeling Negative]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/25/feeling-negative/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/25/feeling-negative</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spend a lot of time on this blog raving about <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/11/kid-book-review-library-trip-report-3/">great kid books</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/02/22/not-dead-yet/">great music</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/01/17/mincer-1958/">great writing for grown ups</a>, and even <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/08/an-homage-to-chris-welty/">great teaching</a>, but don’t get the idea that I think everything is all sunshine and roses. There are plenty of things I don’t appreciate. Here are just three:</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-grateful-dead.jpg" title="[title “Maybe the Ugliest Shirt of All-Time”]" ></p>

<h2 id="the-grateful-dead">1. The Grateful Dead</h2>

<p>When I think of the Dead, the first things that come to mind are dirty feet, ugly tie-dyed shirts, drugs, and silly annoying songs that just go on and on and on.  If you’re into that sort of thing, then I’m really sorry you can’t follow them around anymore.  At least you’ve got Phish.</p>

<h2 id="ezra-jack-keats">2. Ezra Jack Keats</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/hv-willie.jpg" title="[title “Whistle for Willie”]" ></p>

<p>This is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ezra_Jack_Keats">Ezra Jack Keats</a> week at my girls’ preschool and besides <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/05/10/carle-vs-lioni/">Eric Carle</a>, there isn’t a more over-rated children’s book author/illustator.  I’m not an expert on Jack Keats, but I have read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Snowy-Day-Board-Book/dp/0670867330">The Snowy Day</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Whistle-Willie-Board-Book-Keats/dp/0670880469">Whistle for Willie</a> and thus feel perfectly justified generalizing to his whole body of work. I like that he his stories take place in cities. I like that he’s got African-American characters. And I’m not arguing he wasn’t an important trail blazer–he was. I’m just arguing that the books themselves are uninspired and boring.  In the last forty years lots of authors have taken the torch and done a better job with it. My favorites are <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Rain-Stomper-Addie-Boswell/dp/0761453938">The Rain Stomper</a> (by Boswell Addie, illustrated by Eric Velasquez), <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Corduroy-Don-Freeman/dp/0140501738">Corduroy</a> (by Don Freeman), and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bear-Bike-Stella-Blackstone/dp/1905236980">Bear on a Bike</a> (by Stella Blackstone, illustrated by Debbie Harter)</p>

<h2 id="new-orleans">3. New Orleans</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-voodoo.jpg" title="[title “VOODOO”]" ></p>

<p>For some people, New Orleans is a great city. It’s got world class sea food and its own brand of jazz. It’s got a casino downtown and a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bourbon_Street">whole street</a> full of daiquiris and debauchery. But for a vegetarian who doesn’t drink, doesn’t gamble, and whose musical tastes are a little less hip, New Orleans doesn’t have much to offer. I used to think the best thing about the city was voodoo and while that sounds all cool and mysterious, when you take a closer look, it’s not. Chicken blood, bits of hair, and stabbing little dolls to hurt real people is just creepy. Of course, there is <a href="http://www.auduboninstitute.org/visit/insectarium">the Insectarium</a> which is also a little creepy, but was a lot of fun with the girls when we visited a couple weeks ago. </p>

<p>OK, I’ll admit it: I’m not usually such a Debby Downer, but  accumulated sleep debt from a busy winter and spring has taken a toll on my normally sunny disposition. Hopefully the end of the semester will take care of this I’ll soon be back to being a Cheerful Charlie!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Library Trip Report 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/11/kid-book-review-library-trip-report-3/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/11/kid-book-review-library-trip-report-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We haven’t read much new in the last six months, and while I’d like to take the blame and say it’s because we’ve been busy with work and other commitments, I’m instead going to throw my almost two year old daughter under the bus. While R (who is 4.5 now) is an extreme reader, L has not been very excited about reading. Or about anyone else reading. So instead of all of us enjoying a long cuddle on the couch working through a stack of books, this would quickly devolve into yelling and then R going off to read on her own, L going off to cook in her kitchen, and just me and Curious George sitting there wondering what to do next.  I’m happy to say we have recently turned a corner and L now actually seeks out the social reading experience and we’re back to moving big stacks of books back and forth from the library.</p>

<p>Our last two trips have yielded some keepers, some honorable mentions, and even a couple dishonorable mentions.</p>

<h2 id="keepers">Keepers:</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-cowboy-and-octopus.jpg" title="[title “Cowboy and Octopus”]" ></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Cowboy-Octopus-Jon-Scieszka/dp/0670910589">Cowboy and Octopus</a> (by Jon Scieszka, illustrated by Lane Smith) This collection of 7 very short stories about two good friends has something for everyone. L loves the characters and how the cowboy says “Yee Haw!”. Roxana loves the knock-knock joke and when Octopus gets hammered by Cowboy. I love the adult layer of humor and the style that is a combination of collage and old-school comic book illustration. Win win win.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mrs-Crumps-Cat-Linda-Smith/dp/0060283025">Mrs. Crump’s Cat</a> (by Linda Smith, illustrated by David Roberts) A hungry stray cat shows up at an annoyed Mrs. Crump’s door. But as soon as she describes him as “exquisite” and “golden” you know how the story is going to end. So cute.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Cook---Doodle-Doo-Janet-Stevens/dp/0152056580">Cook-a-Doodle-Doo!</a> (by Janet Stevens and Susan Stevens Crummel, illustrated by Janet Stevens) Rooster is tired of the same old food and decides to bake a cake. Turtle, Iguana, and Pot-bellied Pig “help” and along the way we learn a whole bunch about baking. It’s a great combination of funny, sweet, and truly educational.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Frog-Inside-My-Hat-First/dp/0816731306">A Frog Inside My Hat: A First Book of Poems</a> (compiled by Fay Robinson, illustrated by Cyd Moore) Both girls love the simple fun poems collected in this book and L especially loves flipping through it on her own and looking at the pictures–she calls it “the froggie book”. At these ages reading poetry is completely normal and I hope we can keep it that way.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/At-Supermarket-Anne-Rockwell/dp/080507662X">At the Supermarket</a> (by Anne Rockwell) L’s favorite of the bunch is about a boy who goes to the supermarket with his mom. The big twist is that they buy the ingredients for his birthday cake and make it the next day for the party. The author wrote and illustrated a similar book called <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-SUPERMARKET-Anne-Rockwell/dp/0027775801">Supermarket</a> in 1979 and this “updated” version was published in 2010. My favorite part is that it still seems like a 1980’s period piece: There are no laser scanners. No one uses reusable shopping bags. Everyone’s driving station wagons. I can’t wait until Amazon sends me a copy of the original so I can see what actually got updated.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Yard-Full-Birds-Anne-Rockwell/dp/002777273X">Our Yard is Full of Birds</a> (by Anne Rockwell, illustrated by Lizzy Rockwell) Both girls love looking at birds in our yard and this helps them identify who is who.  Only downside is it makes them want a bird bath even more than they already did. And when your kids are little, bird bath = extra dirty outdoor kid bath.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="honorable-mentions">Honorable mentions:</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-jims-lion.jpg" title="[title “Jim’s Lion”]" ></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Jims-Lion-Russell-Hoban/dp/0763611751">Jim’s Lion</a> (by Russell Hoban, illustrated by Ian Andrew) On the first page, Jim says from his hospital bed that “People who have what I have, mostly they die, don’t they?” It gave me the chills and I immediately realized that neither of my girls are old enough for this story. But what a vivid and hopeful story it is. Wow.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Dawn-Uri-Shulevitz/dp/0374416893">Dawn</a> (by Uri Shulevitz) The art is beautiful and the story is subtle–The sky and the silence are the stars and the grandfather and his son are just supporting characters.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Hero-Cat-Eileen-Spinelli/dp/0761458379">Hero Cat</a> (by Eileen Spinelli, illustrated by Jo Ellen McAllister Stammen) I am a sucker for true stories about animals helping other animals. This one has a mom cat rescuing her babies from a burning building. If you read it with feeling, it’s pretty dramatic.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Sarahs-Little-Ghosts-Thierry-Robberecht/dp/B003NHR7D0">Sarah’s Little Ghosts</a> (by Thierry Robberecht, illustrated by Philippe Goossens) This story is very creative and has a great message. Sarah sneaks into her mom’s jewelry box, breaks her favorite necklace, and then hides the evidence. She feels terribly guilty and everytime she lies about it, another ghost flies out of her mouth. Finally, she can’t take it anymore, comes clean, and feels a lot better. R and I read this one very carefully, and I think she even understood what was going on.  Score one for the good guys!</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="dishonorable-mentions">Dishonorable mentions:</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-big-elephant.jpg" title="[title “The Big Elephant in the Room”]" ></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Big-Elephant-Room-Lane-Smith/dp/1423116674">The Big Elephant in the Room</a> (by Lane Smith) This story revolves around two donkeys.  One says they need to talk about the “big elephant in the room” and the other is sure he is asking about the myriad of terrible things he’s been doing and confesses to all of them. These include eating all the ice cream, breaking the computer, stealing a video game, and even telling a mutual friend about a pee accident. My girls do not need <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2011/12/30/bad-behavior/">books giving them more ideas for bad behavior</a>–they’ve got that covered already.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Ladybug-Girl-Beach-Jacky-Davis/dp/0803734166">Ladybug Girl at the Beach</a> (by David Soman and Jacky Davis) I like Ladybug Girl, R loves Ladybug Girl, and we own several Ladybug Girl books. She’s curious, creative, and adventurous. Our best guess is that she and R are both about the same age (between 4 and 5) Her parents are mostly absent, and that’s OK when the story takes place in the backyard or at the playground. At the beach, however, very bad things can happen when parents aren’t around. Like kids drowning bad. In this book Lulu wanders all around the beach by herself and almost gets pulled out to sea without anyone even noticing. As far as I can tell, the message is that you shouldn’t be afraid of sneaking off by yourself to play in the waves when you’re four years old. My four year old already thinks she can swim–I’d rather not encourage that delusion.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[App Review: My Little Pony: Twilight Sparkle: Teacher for a Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/03/25/my-little-pony/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/03/25/my-little-pony</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-mlp-ts-tfad.png" title="[title “Twilight Sparkle: Teacher for a Day”]" ></p>

<p>My first introduction to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/My_Little_Pony">My Little Pony</a> wasn’t terribly positive. I was about eight years old and this “girl stuff” was advertised relentlessly on Saturday morning cartoons. I was far more interested in being a pawn of the corporations that marketed branded soldiers, spaceships, and robots to boys.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>Then in my early twenties, I ran across this <a href="http://brunching.com/pornorpony.html">Internet quiz</a> that gives you names like “Daisy Sweet” and “Misty Rain” and asks you to identify each as either a My Little Pony or a porn star. I failed miserably and while I was horrified at the quiz’s difficulty, I was also a little relieved that I was not an expert on either topic.</p>

<p>And now, it seems that the third time is the charm. The girls have been in a serious MLP phase the last few weeks and our collection now includes 12 little Little Ponies, each with its own colors, personality, and <a href="http://mlp.wikia.com/wiki/Cutie_mark">cutie mark</a>. <a href="http://mlp.wikia.com/wiki/Applejack">Apple Jack</a> is the hard working farmer with the southern drawl while <a href="http://mlp.wikia.com/wiki/Rainbow_Dash">Rainbow Dash</a> is the adventurous one with the mischievous streak. You might have guessed we’ve also watched a couple <a href="http://mlp.wikia.com/wiki/My_Little_Pony_Friendship_is_Magic">tv episodes</a>.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-mlp-in-app-purchases.png" title="[title “What a Scam”]" ></p>

<p>On our last long distance trip we expanded our collection to include a couple iOS apps. The first was Gameloft’s <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/nz/app/my-little-pony-friendship/id533173905?mt=8">My Little Pony - Friendship is Magic</a> and it is an awful scam. You create a magical pony land by buying gems for real money–your parents’ real money to be specific. And if you don’t invest, you can’t actually do anything fun.</p>

<p>The second app (<a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/my-little-pony-twilight-sparkle/id465213808?mt=8">Twilight Sparkle: Teacher for a Day</a>) gets pretty mixed reviews on iTunes but frankly is pretty cute and has no crazy-making in-app purchases. It’s a 40 page appified book that you can read with your kid or will read itself. It has a few built-in animations and four mini-games. Two of the games are simple tilt the iPad to negotiate a maze and two are point-out-the-difference between two picture games. R likes all of them though she sometimes accidentally hits the home button when tilting the iPad and that starts the whole thing over. The story itself filled in some history of the pony’s homeland and could have been titled MLP: Origin of Equestria.  Did you know the unicorn ponies, pegasus ponies and earth ponies started out with cold hearts? And of course, there is a positive message about friendship since (as everyone knows) friendship is magic! R’s favorite part of the app is the set of pony bios that includes pictures and descriptions.</p>

<p>There are three distinct groups of MLP fans. First, little girls, second, parents of little girls, and third, the <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2012/oct/01/my-little-pony-bronies-rebels">bronies</a>. That third group is mostly adult men who self-identify as straight and just love the MLP stories, characters, and positive messages.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> For all these fans, I think this app will be a lot of fun.  I doubt it will appeal much to a broader audience, but I’m also glad that we live in a world that’s big enough for that to be OK.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Micronauts">Micronauts</a> totally ruled.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>We saw a brony in the wild on the plane back from Los Angeles–he was sporting a full beard, a Hawaiian shirt, and was having an awesome time laughing and carrying on while feeding his laptop a steady stream of MLP dvds. I thought it was great and am kicking myself I didn’t get a picture to capture the moment.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
