<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[kids | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/kids/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-13T22:37:38-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Scepter and the Crown]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/26/scepter-and-crown/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/26/scepter-and-crown</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-scepter-and-crown.jpg"></p>

<p>R turned five this weekend and we celebrated with a party, some amazing cupcakes, a trip to the carousel, and a brand new <a href="/blog/11/21/non-violent-dungeons-and-dragons-for-kids/">Nonviolent Dungeons and Dragons for Kids</a> adventure. This one was more puzzle-based and less monster-focused than The Haunted Castle. It was also a little longer and more open to different routes through it.</p>

<p><strong>Props (all optional)</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>a scepter</li>
  <li>a crown</li>
  <li>Some sort of horn</li>
  <li>box with coins and jewels</li>
  <li>frog boots</li>
  <li>rope</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Introduction</strong></p>

<p>King Ricardo (your father, if you’re a princess) has a special mission for you: You must deliver this scepter and crown to your cousin Princess Soldina for her birthday in three days. He gives you a <a href="/images/nvdndfk/land-of-the-scepter-and-the-crown-map.pdf">map of the area</a>–it looks very far and there is no direct route. The King then smiles and gives the players a beautiful magic flying carpet. He says it is very fast and should get you there in plenty of time. It will also return to the King as soon as you step off of it.</p>

<p>What do you do?</p>

<p>Your flight is very pleasant until you start to cross the Black Mountains. That’s when a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roc_(mythology)">roc</a> notices you and starts swooping in for a closer look.</p>

<p>What do you do? </p>

<p>The player can try to avoid each roc capture attempt by rolling 3d6 under her dexterity, but eventually the roc will get them. If they roll exactly their dexterity, they fall and just barely grab the edge of the carpet where they are gently plucked off by the roc.</p>

<p><strong>1. The roc’s cave</strong></p>

<p>The roc flies north and brings you to her nest and then flies off again, in search more food for her chicks. The nest is in a cave high on a mountain (see <a href="/images/nvdndfk/land-of-the-scepter-and-the-crown-dm-map.pdf">DM’s version of the map of the land</a>).  There are two hungry baby rocs in the nest.  They don’t like jokes, but can be soothed to sleep with a lullaby. The cave entrance is a cliff dropping thousands of feet to sharp rocks. You get a little dizzy looking down. In the back of the cave, it looks like a tunnel goes further into the mountain.</p>

<p>There is a weird glowing mold growing on almost all the walls of the caverns that provides enough light to see.</p>

<p>The DM should draw the roc’s cave on a blank sheet of paper for the players and extend the map as the players explore without showing <a href="/images/nvdndfk/caverns-of-the-scepter-and-the-crown-dm-map.pdf">his own complete map of the caverns</a>.</p>

<p><strong>2. The abandoned bedroom</strong></p>

<p>It looks like someone has been living in here recently, but they aren’t here now. There are dirty clothes and some fresh food and drink.  If the players search the room, they will also find a long coil of silk rope, a sharp knife, and some magic green boots with frog eyes on the toes.  These will let the wearer jump long distances.</p>

<p><strong>3. The giant spider nest</strong></p>

<p>The giant spider is working in the back of a giant web–she is busily wrapping her silk around something large and doesn’t notice the players. In fact, she has caught Boris, the human who lived in the bedroom on food stolen from the roc’s babies.  He made his rope from the spider’s silk, but he got too close to the spider recently.  The group may try to rescue him, though the spider is a tough opponent. She is scared of fire though. The web is extremely sticky.  Players will need to either be very strong to escape or use a knife to get out.</p>

<p><strong>4. The chasm</strong></p>

<p>The bridge that once crossed this chasm broke long ago.  Players will need the frog boots and possibly rope to get across. The cave turns into a tunnel on the other side and winds down for a long way on the other side to the underground river.</p>

<p><strong>5. The underground river</strong></p>

<p>The tunnel opens up into a small cave with a low ceiling and a fast-moving river running through it. Next to the river is a small boat. If you want to make the adventure tougher, you could put a hole in the boat and make the players figure out a way to repair it. The river flows underground for several miles and then exits the mountain flowing another several miles to the ocean. Show players on the King’s map.</p>

<p>Just before the river takes a sharp turn and joins the ocean is an unusual multi-colored arched rock about the size of a horse. It is called rainbow rock, but the players don’t know that yet. It can’t be seen directly from the ocean.</p>

<p><strong>6. The Pirates</strong></p>

<p>After being swept past the odd arch-shaped rock, the players’ boat is caught in the ocean’s current moving south.  They soon encounter a pirate ship.  The pirates (led by Pink Beard) are a rough crew but not very hostile.  They are looking for a treasure chest that is supposed to be buried under something called Rainbow Rock.  The pirates have been unable to find it thus far. The players have the option of telling the pirates where it is or keeping quiet.</p>

<p><strong>7. Rainbow Rock</strong></p>

<p>If the players dig under the rainbow rock, they will find a treasure chest. Inside are gold coins, jewels, and a horn covered with intricately carved animals of all kinds.  It is a magical Horn of Animal Summoning.  When blown, some animal will come to the aid of the player.  Some animals are more helpful than others. Aquarius the whale will come if the players blow the horn at this point. He can tow their boat along with the chest all the way to Princess Soldina’s Castle in time for the birthday party.</p>

<p><strong>How it went</strong></p>

<p>R started by creating a new Princess character and enjoyed coloring her map of land throughout her adventure. R was initially very cautious exploring the caves–I had to goad her into moving down the tunnels–but by the end she was feeling quite comfortable underground. She was also wary of the frog boots and certainly didn’t want to tangle with the giant spider. The whole adventure took about half an hour and my favorite moment was at the very end, when she said “Can we play another story now?”</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nonviolent Dungeons and Dragons for Kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/21/non-violent-dungeons-and-dragons-for-kids/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/21/non-violent-dungeons-and-dragons-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-d-and-d-fun.jpg"></p>

<p>My daughter R spends half of her life in a fantasy world pretending she is either a pony, a cat, a princess, a fairy, or some combination of these. She also loves reading about fantastical adventures like <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Wonderful-Wizard-Oz-Anniversary-Wonder/dp/0060293233">The Wizard of Oz</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Comet-Moominland-Tove-Jansson/dp/0312608888">Comet in Moominland</a>, or <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Bravest-Knight-Mercer-Mayer/dp/0803732066">The Bravest Knight</a>. So when a friend sent me <a href="http://gygaxmagazine.com/2013/08/09/dming-for-your-toddler/">Cory Doctorow’s account</a> of how he plays <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_and_dragons">Dungeons and Dragons</a> (D&amp;D) with his four year old daughter, I got very excited. A game that has players pretending they are characters exploring mythical lands and fighting fabulous monsters seemed like an almost perfect match. Cory simplified the rules to fit into a little kid attention span, but there was still a problem: We run a nonviolent household and a game that revolves around bloodshed is a nonstarter.</p>

<p>In middle school, I played a lot of D&amp;D. Sometimes I’d play with friends who were all about the monsters, the combat, and the treasure.  Sometimes I played with friends who set up a vivid land, an intricate plot, and complex characters. These games revolved around solving mysteries, working together, and the occasional backstabbing. We stepped into another world when we played and while combat happened, it was just a small piece of the puzzle. This was the experience I wanted to share with R.</p>

<p>After some experimentation, I think we’ve come up with a decent set of rules and R is still talking about our last adventure (“The Haunted Castle”). I’ve written up our rules and a description of that adventure here so we don’t forget them and also for anyone else who might want to take the plunge. The biggest innovation is the replacement of the combat system with an “interaction” system.  Instead of fighting monsters, we try to befriend them or avoid them. And while the monsters might try to scare players or even imprison them, no one can actually hurt anyone.</p>

<h2 id="creating-characters">Creating Characters</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/nvdndfk/character-sheet.png"></p>

<p>Cory Doctorow wanted get his daughter adventuring as quickly as possible, and so had her make up a bare bones character up front, fleshing her out as needed during the game. We found that creating a character was one of the most riveting parts of the game. I pre-printed some character sheets (<a href="/images/nvdndfk/character-sheet.docx">.docx</a>, <a href="/images/nvdndfk/character-sheet.pdf">.pdf</a>) and R enjoyed rolling dice, writing down numbers, and drawing her character’s picture. We started by choosing the character’s name, race, and job.  Races include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>human,</li>
  <li>fairy (can fly),</li>
  <li>elf (good at hiding and finding), </li>
  <li>dwarf (can sniff out gems), and </li>
  <li>hobbit (can squeeze into small spaces). </li>
</ul>

<p>Possible jobs are: </p>

<ul>
  <li>princess (good at horseback riding), </li>
  <li>knight (also good on horses), and </li>
  <li>wizard (casting spells). </li>
</ul>

<p>There are no functional differences between knights and princesses just in case we end up playing with boys some time in the future. I didn’t think thieves or clerics were kid-appropriate.</p>

<p>Each character has three attributes: </p>

<ul>
  <li>strength, </li>
  <li>intelligence, and</li>
  <li>dexterity.</li>
</ul>

<p>These affect the characters’ chances of doing things like finding traps, climbing obstacles, jumping over things, or pushing/lifting things.  I had R roll three six-sided dice (aka 3d6) three times and each time decide which attribute she wanted that roll to be. I also let her roll again if she got a really low number.</p>

<p>I’m sure we’ll be adding new races, jobs and attributes as we play more. </p>

<h2 id="magic">Magic</h2>

<p>Wizards start off with one spell, but anyone can find and use scrolls with spells.  Possible spells currently include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Rainbow (can impress or distract monsters)</li>
  <li>Sleep (can put monsters to sleep for 10 minutes)</li>
  <li>Universal language (allows character to speak to any animate creature)</li>
  <li>Smoke cloud (good for creating diversions)</li>
  <li>Invisibility (lasts one hour)</li>
  <li>Flight (lasts one hour)</li>
  <li>Super strength (lasts one hour)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="magic-items">Magic Items</h2>

<p>The sky is the limit on magical items that can be found in the course of the adventure.  R already has a Wand of Stone (that turns living creatures to stone) and a Bracelet of Teleportation (that works once per day).</p>

<h2 id="basic-game-play">Basic Game Play</h2>

<p>Every adventure has a big goal.  The player(s) have to do something like rescue someone, find something, or stop someone. In our first adventure, the party had to rescue a princess that had been kidnapped by a giant frog army and brought to a volcano.  Our second involved helping the frog army (now our friends) get back to their home pond through a magic tunnel. The players always start somewhere specific and get a short description of what’s going on.  Then I say “What do you do now?”</p>

<p>Cory’s fairly improvisational method can work well if you have a great imagination and a library of “situations” you can bring to bear.  I’ve found I do better with a little bit of preparation– not nearly as much as you would need to run a game with older kids or adults, but more than none. Our third adventure (“The Haunted Castle”) is described below. Be inspired by books (yours and his/hers) and movies. These are great sources for monsters, characters, situations, and plots.</p>

<p>Some sort of board or map is very useful in anchoring the action.  We used a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Large-Neat-Oh-Dinosaur-Dinosauria-Figures/dp/B0080IUTN2">dinosaur landscape</a> first and then just a hand-drawn map of a castle. If you have a big pad of paper (like <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Melissa-Doug-Easel-Paper-Pad/dp/B00365OLU6">Melissa and Doug’s Easel Pad</a>), you can quickly draw anything you want.</p>

<p>As the action unfolds, we do a lot of ad hoc dice rolling. This definitely adds an element of excitement. If you don’t have dice, I highly recommend the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Chessex-001LBCHX-Pound-O-Dice/dp/B008C0KXYS">Chessex Pound of Dice</a>.</p>

<p>We’ve been keeping track of who we befriend during each adventure and counting them up.  This might eventually be a decent analog of experience points (traditionally acquiring by killing monsters) but we haven’t used these numbers for anything yet.</p>

<h2 id="the-interaction-system">The Interaction System</h2>

<p>When a player comes into contact with a creature, they can do anything except attack.  Possible actions include (but are not limited to):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Greet the creature</li>
  <li>Give a present</li>
  <li>Smile</li>
  <li>Tell a joke</li>
  <li>Sing a friendship song</li>
  <li>Run away</li>
  <li>Use a spell</li>
</ul>

<p>If the player decides to tell a joke or sing, they must actually do so. The joke or song must also be relevant to the situation at hand. If the player’s action is friendly, they roll a die. The size depends on the quality of the action–e.g., a good joke gets a greater die. The creature also rolls a die equal to his/her “friendship resistance points.” More ornery creatures roll bigger dice. The highest number wins.  If the monster wins, s/he stays ornery and doesn’t cooperate.  If the player wins, the monster becomes a friend.  No one ever gets hurt.  If friends are helping, they can roll dice too.</p>

<h2 id="the-haunted-castle">The Haunted Castle</h2>

<p>All descriptions and scenarios in this adventure benefit from extemperaneous elaboration–think of everything below as a jumping off point. The main goals are exploration and escape, and the only way out of the castle is to find and use the Bracelet of Teleportation.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/nvdndfk/the-haunted-castle-map.png"></p>

<p><strong>Props:</strong></p>

<p>You don’t actually need any props, but in general, with little kids, the more props the better.  This set worked well for us:</p>

<ul>
  <li>a big hand-drawn copy of <a href="/images/the-haunted-castle-map.pdf">the castle map</a> (you can also use a real doll house)</li>
  <li>a way to dim the lights</li>
  <li>spooky music and sound effects (the <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/dj-halloween/id337499264">DJ Halloween iPhone app</a> is awesome)</li>
  <li>a fancy box (doubles as jewelry box and treasure chest)</li>
  <li>a bracelet</li>
  <li>a key</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Introduction:</strong></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One day you were out exploring the Tangled Forest and there arose a terrible storm in the late afternoon. In the heavy rain, you couldn’t see much, but then there was a flash of lightning and it illuminated a castle to your left on a hill. It looks dark and foreboding but you need shelter. </p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>What do you do?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As the player moves closer to the castle they see flickering lights in the windows. The castle is made of heavy gray stone and is surrounded by a moat. Strange dangerous creatures seem to be swimming in the moat. On the right side of the castle rises a tall tower. A drawbridge slowly lowers.</p>

<p><strong>The five rooms of the castle (<a href="/images/nvdndfk/the-haunted-castle-map.pdf">.pdf map</a>):</strong></p>

<p><strong>3. The Great Room</strong></p>

<p>Once inside the castle, the drawbridge slams closed and three skeletons (FR points = 1d6 each) appear and laugh.  They tell the player she is trapped. The room is dark but has torches on the left and right walls.  On each side of the room are two doors. R made friends with these skeletons right away, but they aren’t very helpful.</p>

<p><strong>1. The Kitchen</strong></p>

<p>Three witches are huddled in a corner around a big bubbling cauldron with their backs to the door.  They are completely engrossed in cackling and stirring, and won’t notice a player until the player talks to them. Until they are befriended (FR points = 1d6 each), they will threaten to turn the player into a rat even though they won’t actually do it. They also won’t chase the player out of the room.</p>

<p>Once befriended, they can’t answer any questions, but they will refer the player to the rats in the dining room and offer up a universal language scroll so the player can talk to them.</p>

<p><strong>2. The Dining Room</strong> </p>

<p>The room is dominated by a huge table covered with rotting food on beautiful plates and big bowls of boiling stews. It smells terrible and there are rats sneaking around in the corners. As the rats get comfortable, they will hop on the table to steal food and drinks.</p>

<p>The rats here know a lot, and they can answer direct questions, but they usually run away after they answer them. Of course, you need the universal language spell to talk to them.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Q: How can I escape? A: You need the magic bracelet–it can transport you anywhere in an instant.</li>
  <li>Q: Where is the bracelet? A: In the dungeon–but don’t open the wrong chest!</li>
  <li>Q: Where is the key to the chest? A: In the tower–but don’t wake up the vampire!</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>4. The Dungeon</strong></p>

<p>The dungeon is dark–the player must bring a torch from upstairs or she won’t be able to see a thing.  The stairs are long and the dungeon is deep underground. The ceilings are low. The dungeon itself is filled with rubble, broken furniture, and loads of cob webs.  It’s more like a messy basement than a true dungeon, but it’s still scary.</p>

<p>In the far corner lie two large ornate chests. They look much fancier after the dust has been blown or brushed off.  One is unlocked and inside is a mummy (FR=1d12). He moves slowly and just says “Leave me alone! Leave my dungeon” over and over.</p>

<p>The second chest is locked and can only be opened with the key from the tower.  It contains gold coins, gems, and the Bracelet of Teleportation which will take the player home.</p>

<p><strong>5. The Tower</strong></p>

<p>The stairs to the top of the tower are long and they lead to a heavy unlocked wooden door. The player must roll 3d6 lower than their strength to push it open. Entering the room, the player sees an old decrepit bedroom. The bed is wrought iron with chipped paint and dirty white silk canopy. Sleeping on his back with his arms crossed over his chest is a vampire. He has pale white skin and two sharp canines protruding from his mouth.</p>

<p>As the player walks around the room, she makes noise stepping on broken glass and knocking things off dressers. These noises wake up the vampire if she rolls a 6 on a d6.  Otherwise the vampire simply moves and groans. In a jewelry box on a table next to the bed is the key that opens the locked dungeon chest.</p>

<p>If the vampire wakes up, he is very angry and has 1d20 friendship resistance points. At this point, the player should notice the jewelry box. If she still doesn’t grab it, the vampire should throw it at her, miss, and have it smash on the stairs revealing the key. The vampire will chase them down the stairs, but not into the dungeon. </p>

<p>Happy adventuring!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Stars Align]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/09/05/the-stars-align/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/09/05/the-stars-align</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-bike-and-shoes.jpg" title="[title “R’s bike and my shoes”]" ></p>

<p>Several years ago my wife and I spent a week in Costa Rica during the rainy season. As expected, it rained most of our trip but was warm and fun nonetheless. And those brief windows when the sun came out were magical. I think raising kids is a little like this–mostly great, but some periods when all the stars align that are truly amazing. </p>

<p>When R was born, my exercise regime changed.  I stopped going to the gym or training for particular events, but I still managed to get out a couple times a week for a run and stay in reasonable shape. When B was born, planned exercise (i.e., beyond chasing kids and racing to work) disappeared as two kids is a bit more work than one and something had to give.</p>

<p>Some people are good at combining exercise with parenting.  They backpack with their kids and push them around with jogging strollers.  My kids don’t like activities where they aren’t active–they like pushing strollers more than sitting in them.  Also, sleep is like gold in our house and our kids sleep best in beds. I would never risk waking a sleeping child miles from home because I hit a pot hole.  I’ve also seen other parents go bike riding with their kids.  These parents sometimes look like they are having fun, but they certainly aren’t getting more exercise than if they were out for a leisurely stroll.</p>

<p>Last week, I entered a fantastic window in my parenting career where I can finally join the ranks of the co-exercising parents.  R is getting pretty comfortable on her bike and I’ve been putting on my running shoes to run next to her on her rides. Yesterday she said she loved the feel of the wind in her face as she rode down a long hill. She calls the bike trail near our house “the country” even though it runs behind the local strip malls on one side, and the highway and an office park on the other.  To her credit, we also saw a ground hog cross the trail and watched ducks congregate in a little pond.</p>

<p>I’m terribly out of shape and she currently tires easily, but we’re both getting better as she learns the fine arts of balance and pacing. It also helps that R and I have had a fair amount of one-on-one time as B’s school started full-time last week but R’s won’t be full-time until next week. Unfortunately, I think this window is destined to be brief.  R will eventually want to ride faster and longer than I want to run.  I don’t know when that time will come, but it won’t surprise me if it’s soon given the current trend.  Every day she’s substantially more comfortable on the bike and she loves speed.</p>

<p>Going on these bike rides has been incredibly fun and I’m just trying to focus on the moment and appreciate them.  I’m also already hoping to do it all again in a couple years with B.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Too Soon?]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/06/09/too-soon/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/06/09/too-soon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I loved the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Oz_books">Wizard of Oz</a> when I was a kid. Not the movie and not just the book, but the whole series of books and the whole world of Oz and the whole host of amazing characters. L. Frank Baum wrote 14 books and by the end of second grade I had read them all. The Scarecrow, the Patchwork Girl, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Gump#The_Gump">the Gump</a>, the Cowardly Lion, and the Hungry Tiger (just to name a few) were some of my best friends. Given that my daughter R has a wild imagination and a voracious appetite for books, you can’t blame me for introducing  these stories as soon as possible. Actually, it was too soon.</p>

<p>We started reading a seriously condensed picture book version when she was about two years old. She thought it was terrific and for months all she wanted to do was to act out the story. She was Dorothy for Halloween last year, and right around R’s 4th birthday, we read a chapter of the unabridged <em>Wizard of Oz</em> every night. She loved it and even though it revved her up a little right before she was supposed to go to sleep, we finished it and dove right into the <em>Land of Oz</em>. Jack Pumpkinhead and the Sawhorse were as fun as the original characters and we zipped through <em>Ozma of Oz</em> where we got to meet our first Oz princess.</p>

<p>We hit a wall with <em>Dorothy and the Wizard of Oz</em>. The invisible bears were just too scary. That night it took a little longer than usual to get to sleep and the next night, R wanted to read something else. </p>

<p>Last weekend we had a similar experience.  As soon as it got warm enough, R has been zooming around on her pink Dora bike with training wheels. We would go as fast as we caould around the block and I would run down the hills to keep up with her. She was looking a little cramped and since the seat wouldn’t go up any higher, I thought it was time for a new bike. Our awesome local shop (<a href="http://www.thedevilsgear.com">The Devil’s Gear</a>) had a used 16” bike that was perfect and we picked it up. It didn’t have training wheels and R said that was fine with her.</p>

<p>I also thought since B just turned two, she was ready for her first bike. We decided to pick up a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/MyKick-Balance-Bike-Cotton-Candy/dp/B009T2SITU">Burley MyKick</a>. It’s got two wheels and no pedals so you learn to balance right away. My friend Google tells me it’s easier to transition to a “real bike” from one of these than from a bike with training wheels.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, we did not have the fun-filled weekend of bike-riding that I was hoping for.  As soon as we got home, we learned  that both kids were too little for their new bikes. Seats only go so low. The only short term benefit was that R enjoyed racing the MyKick up and down the driveway.</p>

<p>This weekend things got a lot better. R decided she was ready to ride her new bike and this evening we did 4 laps around the block!  It didn’t take long for her to master the straight-aways up hill and down hill. But the seat is still too high and she needs support to start or stop. She’s going to be a menace to herself and our neighbors for a while yet.</p>

<p>Books and bikes are pretty low stakes things, and I don’t feel so bad starting them on the early side. We’ll return to Oz at some point. Our new bikes will be be there when the girls are totally ready. But some decisions are a lot harder to recover from if you make a mistake. Parents of kids who were born late in the year know where I’m going with this: When is the right time to start school?</p>

<p>I’m a December birthday and I started first grade when I was 5. My mom had to convince the principal to bend the rules since technically I was supposed to be 6 by September 1. Throughout elementary, middle school, and high school I was the youngest kid in the class. I was pretty emotionally immature. I had regular “accidents” until third grade. I always had trouble with girls and I think at least part of that was being younger than they were. And yet I feel strongly that it was the right decision for me. I was curious and intellectually ambitious and competitive. I would have been bored silly if I had been held back and even as it was, I wish I’d been challenged more. </p>

<p>I’ve also met lots of people with late in the year birthdays that were pushed into school early, and they’re bitter about it to this day. They really believe they would have had a more comfortable and successful school experience had their parents waited. And maybe their parents should have waited.</p>

<p>The trendy thing to do now is to wait. I swear it all started when Malcolm Gladwell’s book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Outliers-Story-Success-Malcolm-Gladwell/dp/0316017922">Outliers</a> came out in 2008.  In the first chapter, he tells a story about how elite Canadian hockey players were all born in January or February. When these guys started playing, they were the biggest, most skilled kids on their age-graded teams and so were plucked out and given additional training/coaching. Maybe being the oldest kid in kindergarten or first grade helps with academics too. Maybe.</p>

<p>I strongly believe the “right” answer about when to start school depends on the kid (and the school). R was born in late November and will be starting kindergarten next year (before she turns 5). We will be watching her closely. The academic part of school will be no problem. She’s already got great reading and math skills and she loves to learn. On the social/emotional side, she acts her age. That might be hard when most of her friends are older. We are definitely open to having her repeat kindergarten at a new school. We’re also open to her moving on to first grade. We’re not open to doing something just because everyone else is doing it. We’ll make the decision based on her.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Feeling Negative]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/25/feeling-negative/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/25/feeling-negative</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spend a lot of time on this blog raving about <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/11/kid-book-review-library-trip-report-3/">great kid books</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/02/22/not-dead-yet/">great music</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/01/17/mincer-1958/">great writing for grown ups</a>, and even <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/08/an-homage-to-chris-welty/">great teaching</a>, but don’t get the idea that I think everything is all sunshine and roses. There are plenty of things I don’t appreciate. Here are just three:</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-grateful-dead.jpg" title="[title “Maybe the Ugliest Shirt of All-Time”]" ></p>

<h2 id="the-grateful-dead">1. The Grateful Dead</h2>

<p>When I think of the Dead, the first things that come to mind are dirty feet, ugly tie-dyed shirts, drugs, and silly annoying songs that just go on and on and on.  If you’re into that sort of thing, then I’m really sorry you can’t follow them around anymore.  At least you’ve got Phish.</p>

<h2 id="ezra-jack-keats">2. Ezra Jack Keats</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/hv-willie.jpg" title="[title “Whistle for Willie”]" ></p>

<p>This is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ezra_Jack_Keats">Ezra Jack Keats</a> week at my girls’ preschool and besides <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/05/10/carle-vs-lioni/">Eric Carle</a>, there isn’t a more over-rated children’s book author/illustator.  I’m not an expert on Jack Keats, but I have read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Snowy-Day-Board-Book/dp/0670867330">The Snowy Day</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Whistle-Willie-Board-Book-Keats/dp/0670880469">Whistle for Willie</a> and thus feel perfectly justified generalizing to his whole body of work. I like that he his stories take place in cities. I like that he’s got African-American characters. And I’m not arguing he wasn’t an important trail blazer–he was. I’m just arguing that the books themselves are uninspired and boring.  In the last forty years lots of authors have taken the torch and done a better job with it. My favorites are <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Rain-Stomper-Addie-Boswell/dp/0761453938">The Rain Stomper</a> (by Boswell Addie, illustrated by Eric Velasquez), <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Corduroy-Don-Freeman/dp/0140501738">Corduroy</a> (by Don Freeman), and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bear-Bike-Stella-Blackstone/dp/1905236980">Bear on a Bike</a> (by Stella Blackstone, illustrated by Debbie Harter)</p>

<h2 id="new-orleans">3. New Orleans</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-voodoo.jpg" title="[title “VOODOO”]" ></p>

<p>For some people, New Orleans is a great city. It’s got world class sea food and its own brand of jazz. It’s got a casino downtown and a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bourbon_Street">whole street</a> full of daiquiris and debauchery. But for a vegetarian who doesn’t drink, doesn’t gamble, and whose musical tastes are a little less hip, New Orleans doesn’t have much to offer. I used to think the best thing about the city was voodoo and while that sounds all cool and mysterious, when you take a closer look, it’s not. Chicken blood, bits of hair, and stabbing little dolls to hurt real people is just creepy. Of course, there is <a href="http://www.auduboninstitute.org/visit/insectarium">the Insectarium</a> which is also a little creepy, but was a lot of fun with the girls when we visited a couple weeks ago. </p>

<p>OK, I’ll admit it: I’m not usually such a Debby Downer, but  accumulated sleep debt from a busy winter and spring has taken a toll on my normally sunny disposition. Hopefully the end of the semester will take care of this I’ll soon be back to being a Cheerful Charlie!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
