<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[kids | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/kids/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-09T23:17:43-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Robot Edition]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/21/kbr-robots/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/21/kbr-robots</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>B is really into robots lately, and I thought it would be fun to share her favorite books that feature robots or have exciting robot-related scenes.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-robot-and-bluebird.jpg"></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Robot-Bluebird-David-Lucas/dp/0374363307">The Robot and the Bluebird</a> (written and illustrated by David Lucas) This is a sweet story that takes on some heavy topics: love, sacrifice and even death. Spoiler alert: The bird comes out ok at the end, the robot not so much. The quirky drawings are wonderful, and honestly I think David Lucas is physically incapable of creating a book that’s not great.</li>
</ul>

<!--more-->

<p><img class="left" src="/images/hv-boy-+-bot.jpg"></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Boy-Bot-Ame-Dyckman/dp/0375867562">Boy + Bot</a> (written by Ame Dyckman, illustrated by Dan Yaccarino) We picked this up at the library a couple weeks ago and it’s still B’s dinner time favorite. The boy and the robot meet in the forest and start a friendship that’s briefly interrupted by a couple cute misunderstandings. Now whenever I ask B if she likes this book she smiles and says in a slow monotone: “Affirmative.”</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/hv-lbg-mean-robot.jpg"></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Ladybug-Girl-Bumblebee-Jacky-Davis/dp/0803733399">Ladybug Girl and Bumblebee Boy</a> (written by Jacky Davis, illustrated by David Soman) This is our go-to bedtime book and it’s got Ladybug Girl playing Bug Squad at the playground with her new friend Sam. B loves when they pretend the tire swing is a mean robot and Lulu jumps on its head. And the other day at the playground we almost convinced a real boy to play Ladybug Bug girl with us! He wanted to be Mosquito Boy until his friend pulled him back to playing Ninjas.</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/hv-critter-giant-robot.jpg"></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="">Just Go to Bed</a> (written and illustrated by Mercer Mayer) The Critter books are like cheese sandwiches–they aren’t the most creative stories, but they are consistently good. I might appreciate this one more than the girls because we live it almost every night. Critter keeps coming up with excuses for not going to bed while his parents play along but get more and more exasperated. At  one point Critter is a space cadet and Dad (the giant robot) captures him. If only that were the end of the story.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Black metal for kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/04/black-metal-for-kids/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/04/black-metal-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Black metal is nasty stuff. Most of it revolves around Satanic imagery, shreiking vocals and guitars, incredibly fast “blast beat” drums, and spooky low fi production. Most bands hail from Scandinavia, and in the mid 90’s the nastiness reached a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lords-Chaos-Satanic-Underground-Edition/dp/0922915946">particularly nasty level</a> as bands competed with each other to see who was the most evil by burning churches and murdering each other. And yet, I really appreciate the dark moodiness and musicality.</p>

<p>You can imagine my surprise when I found an honest-to-goodness Norwegian black metal band that is perfect for kids and adults. Now, whenever we get in the car, my two year old requests their music and proceeds to laugh and sing along! How did this happen? A confluence of two amazing things.</p>

<p>As I’ve already reported, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/21/fun-and-games-at-the-library/">my girls love the Rainbow Magic books</a>. While the heros are Kirsty, Rachel, and the fairies, the villains are Jack Frost and the goblins. Their home is an icy castle north of Fairy Land and they are frankly hilarious. The goblins call each other names, trip over each other, and are some of the least scary “monsters” you’ll ever meet. I remember in one book Rachel and Kirsty got their way by tickling the goblins.</p>

<p>The band <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Immortal_(band)">Immortal</a> has been recording black metal since before their first full-length release: <em>Diabolical Fullmoon Mysticism</em> in 1992. Their music is classic black metal, but many of their songs simply describe frigid mountains and the grumpy king who reigns over them. B’s favorite song is “Mountains of Might.” It starts with organ which B says is “carousel music” and contains vocals which she calls “a goblin talking:”</p>

<pre><code>The storm is getting colder
In a place of the frozen sun
Alone on the mountainside
Breathing the clearest winds
The winds are everblowing
Blowing off the glaciers
Snow descend of the valley
Into the high impassable drifts
So rightly I am watching
These mountains that I know
Forever standing here
These mountains northern face
Mountains of might
Mountains of might
Mountains of might
Icicled peeks as far as the eye can see
I will reign this place alone
Cold winds blew into the valley wall
Snow was deeper there
The storm is getting colder
In a place of the frozen sun
Alone on the mountainside
Breathing the clearest winds
Mountains of might
Mountains of might
Mountains of might
</code></pre>

<p>The acoustic break in the middle is when “the goblins are dancing.” The whole album (<em>Blizzard Beasts</em>) is recorded with the vocals mixed extra loud so they don’t get lost. My favorite part is how Abbath (the lead singer) pronounces glaciers as “glaysseers”. The <a href="http://www.metrolyrics.com/antarctica-lyrics-immortal.html">lyrics of “Antarctica”</a> (from <em>Sons of Northern Darkness</em>) are similarly child-friendly and the music is similarly goblin-friendly.</p>

<p>The only downside to Immortal for kids is common to all heavy metal: the terribly inappropriate music videos. Immortal follows black metal tradition and performs in corpse paint while making lots of scary faces. They also seem to love weird spiked bondage gear. They look ridiculous and I try to avoid <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-VBdAY8eA9w">their videos</a> too. It doesn’t have to be this way. Consider the video below to be my small contribution to making the world a better place:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/tGXN58iZH5k" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>If you are excited to try and get your kids into other metal subgenres, make sure and check out <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/24/heavy-metal-for-kids/">my earlier post on this subject</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fun and Games at the Library]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/21/fun-and-games-at-the-library/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/21/fun-and-games-at-the-library</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-alphabet-rug.jpg"></p>

<p>Consumption, analysis, and <a href="http://randsinrepose.com/archives/the-builders-high/">creation</a>. A lot of my time can be assigned to one of these three categories, and while all three have their place, I find it very easy to slouch into consumption and shirk creation. I feel better about myself when I’m in balance, so I’m always looking for opportunities to make things. That’s one reason the girls and I have been making up so <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/12/pretty-pretty-princess/">many</a> <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/21/non-violent-dungeons-and-dragons-for-kids/">new</a> <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/17/sequence-for-kids/">games</a> lately. </p>

<p>Our trips to the library have always been more than simply dropping off and picking up bags of books. We like to take our time and hang out too. These are our three favorite games to play while we’re there:</p>

<p><strong>1. The Rug Game:</strong> The main branch of the New Haven Free Public Library has a huge children’s room and in the middle is a big circular rug with the alphabet and associated pictures printed around the edge. Since R was little we’ve played a game where I tell her to find something and she has to run to an appropriate letter. We started with the basics:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Run to the octopus!</li>
  <li>Where is the dog?</li>
  <li>Find the birthday cake!</li>
</ul>

<p>We moved on to more tricky questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What keeps you dry in the rain? (Umbrella)</li>
  <li>Who has 8 arms? (Octopus)</li>
  <li>Find a red fruit! (Apple)</li>
</ul>

<p>When other kids join in, the questions have to have at least two correct answers so everyone can find their own letter:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Who swims in the water? (Fish, octopus, turtle)</li>
  <li>Find a fun toy! (yoyo, kite)</li>
  <li>What has a shell? (Turtle, egg)</li>
</ul>

<p>As the kids get older, the questions get downright tricky:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What rhymes with cry? (Pie)</li>
  <li>Who has a princess for a daughter? (Queen)</li>
  <li>Who is black and white? (Zebra)</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>2. Rainbow Magic:</strong> R is currently obsessed with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rainbow_Magic">this series</a> of beginning chapter books. They are formulaic in the same way <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dora_the_Explorer">Dora and Boots</a> are formulaic beginning readers and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hardy_Boys">The Hardy Boys</a> are formulaic tween boy schlock. The books come in sets of seven (e.g. <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0545175178/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0545175178&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=highvari-20">The Pet Fairies</a>) and each book involves two girls (Rachel and Kirsty) helping a particular fairy retrieve some magic item before Jack Frost and/or his goblins can get it. The books are quite harmless, and the thing is kids <em>like</em> formula–figuring it out is like solving a puzzle. B is not so into the stories yet, but she’s been swept up in R’s enthusiasm, and at the library she loves to gather up a big pile of the books, pore over the covers, and flip for pictures of goblins. We recently made up a game where she files her books by the first letter of the fairy’s name on the alphabet rug. Fun and even a little educational!</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-picture-book-scavenger-hunt.jpg"></p>

<p><strong>3. Picture Book Scavenger Hunt:</strong> This is a game I’ve been trying to get the girls excited about for years, and during our last library outing it finally took hold. I made a list of animals, characters and objects, and the girls had to find a picture of each in a book. We settled in between two big shelves and started digging. It was surprisingly difficult–I would have told you that a third of all picture books contain princesses, fairies, pirates, and dogs. It turns out dogs are easy to find, but everything else took a little hunting. </p>

<p>I’ve written a lot recently about games we’ve made up and had a good time playing. I hope some of you are inspired to try a few out. I hope even more that you are inspired to create your own games. That’s the most fun of all.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pretty Pretty Princess!]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/12/pretty-pretty-princess/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/12/pretty-pretty-princess</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-pretty-pretty-princess.jpg"></p>

<p>I was talking to one of R’s former pre-school teachers the other day, and she mentioned a board game she used to play with her daughter and husband called <em>Pretty Pretty Princess</em>. It involved moving pieces around the board (ala Candy Land) and collecting real jewelry that you get to wear. You win when you put on the tiara and shout out “I’m a Pretty Pretty Princess!” My first thought was that both of my girls would love this game and I should look for it on Amazon as soon as possible.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> My second thought was that we already owned most of the parts and it would be even more fun to make the game ourselves.</p>

<p>We started by rolling out a big piece of paper and taping it to the dining room table. I drew a winding track and divided it into spaces. The girls went to town with their markers and drew bracelets, necklaces, rings, and earrings all over the board while I tracked down some dice (<a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/21/non-violent-dungeons-and-dragons-for-kids/">not hard</a>) and our tiaras. We selected our game pieces from our bag of <a href="http://www.schleich-s.com/en/US/toys/">Schleich animals</a> and My Little Ponies, grabbed our kids’ jewelry box, and started playing.</p>

<p>Rolling the dice and moving her piece the right number of spaces were challenges for B (not quite three years old), but picking jewelry out of the box made it all worthwhile. R enjoyed the game even though the pace was a little bit slow. We’ll play this version a few more times, but I’m already looking forward to making it more complicated by adding forks in the road, special squares, and some weird rules. </p>

<p><strong>Footnotes:</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I did eventually look up <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00000IWHP/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B00000IWHP&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=highvari-20">the game on Amazon</a> and it doesn’t look any more fun than our homemade version.  And holy mackerel, it’s $99!<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Our Favorite Board Game: Sequence for Kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/17/sequence-for-kids/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/17/sequence-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/hv-sequence-for-kids.jpg"></p>

<p>With the holidays upon us it seems like every geek blogger I read has been recommending family-friendly board games. <a href="http://macsparky.com/blog/2013boardgames">MacSparky</a> sent me to <a href="http://fannypackmafia.com/blog/2013/12/8/my-favorite-board-games-from-2013-part-one">Fanny Pack Mafia</a>, <a href="http://www.marco.org/2013/12/12/gift-guide-actually-used-for-a-year">Marco</a> says <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0007YDBLE/?tag=marcoorg-20">Power Grid</a> is really good, and <a href="http://kottke.org/13/11/how-to-quickly-get-good-at-chess">Kottke</a> is sending me to <a href="http://www.gautamnarula.com/how-to-get-good-at-chess-fast/">Gautam Narula</a> to improve my chess game. This is all well and good, but these games are a bit much for my 2.5 and 5 year old kids.  Maybe that’s why our favorite game hasn’t been on any of these lists.</p>

<p>The rules for <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00005UM9P/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B00005UM9P&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=highvari-20">Sequence for Kids</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=highvari-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B00005UM9P" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
are simple. The game starts with each player getting three cards and a pile of their own colored chips. The cards have animals on them as does the board which is a 6x7 square grid. A turn consists of playing a card and putting one of your chips on a square that has the same animal that was on the card. Players replenish their hand by picking another card from the deck at the end of their turn. The goal is to get four chips in a row. There are two “magical” animals: The Unicorn card lets a player put their chip on any square while the Dragon card lets a player remove any chip from the board.</p>

<p>Many games for little kids are designed simply to teach rule following and maybe some hand-eye coordination as the player spins a spinner or picks a card and moves their token along a track. Chutes and Ladders and Candyland are the canonical examples of a genre that rots adult brains. Sequence includes enough strategy that kids are challenged, and enough randomness that they have a chance to win against adults.</p>

<p>The set of skills kids can learn (or practice) while playing is surprisingly rich:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Forward thinking:</strong> Players need to make sequences of two before they can make three and then four to win. They need to recognize when their opponent is about to win, and then block them if possible. </li>
  <li><strong>Patience:</strong> Players should save their special cards for when they need them for defense or offense.</li>
  <li><strong>Reasoning about uncertainty:</strong> I wonder if my opponent has a Lion in their hand and could win next turn?  I wonder if I could pick a Lion from the deck for my next turn? Maybe two Lions have already been played and none are left!</li>
  <li><strong>Pattern recognition:</strong> Where are my winning opportunities? Four in a row wins whether it is across, down or diagonal.</li>
  <li><strong>Creativity:</strong> R thinks the magic animals are the best part of the game and we often make up our own rules to create more. Sometimes the Kangaroo card lets you put down a chip on a Kangaroo and another square next to it. Sometimes the Shark can eat another animal and let you put your own chip in its place. The possibilities are endless.</li>
  <li><strong>Reading:</strong> The game even promotes reading in a subtle way. The cards have pictures of the animals for non-readers, words for the animal  (e.g. “Penguin”) for learning readers, and even a fun name for the animal (e.g., “Percy”) for actual readers. </li>
</ul>

<p>Perhaps the best part of the game is that it’s easy to modify the game for players of any age. We often play with cards face up.  This makes reasoning about your opponent’s next move a little clearer and has two other big advantages: Little uncoordinated hands don’t have to try to hold three cards at once, and it’s a lot easier to teach strategy when you can see what cards your kid is holding.  I’ve also played a fairly rule-free version of the game with one and two year-olds where we just deal out cards and place chips on the board. These kids love the animals and the bright colors of the chips and even like matching the animals to the squares on the board. </p>

<p>Sequence for Kids really is fun for the whole family!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
