<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: kids | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/categories/kids/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-26T10:15:30-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Carle vs. Lionni: No Accounting for Taste]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/05/10/carle-vs-lioni/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/05/10/carle-vs-lioni</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most grown-ups, even those without kids, have heard of Eric Carle---He is
an extremely popular children's book author who illustrates using
collage.  In fact, his <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Brown-Bear-What-You-See/dp/0805047905">Brown Bear Brown Bear What Do See</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Very-Hungry-Caterpillar-Eric-Carle/dp/0399226907">The
Very Hungry Caterpillar</a> have now supplanted Margaret Wise Brown's
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Goodnight-Moon-Margaret-Wise-Brown/dp/0694003611">Goodnight Moon</a> as the standard gift for newborn kids.</p>

<p>Both my daughters celebrated Eric Carle week at school last month
and it got me thinking (again) just how over-rated he is.  He's
either today's <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman_Rockwell">Norman Rockwell</a> or the kids' version of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Kinkade">Thomas Kinkade</a>
("Painter of Light").<a href="My">^1</a>  With a few exceptions (like <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Secret-Birthday-Message-Board-Book/dp/0694011487">The Secret Birthday
Message</a>), his books couldn't be more repetitive and formulaic.</p>

<p>never miss a chance to bring up my favorite abusive alcoholic
religious nut-job artist, even if he did pass away recently.  And the
truth is, I think his work is pretty.  Just like Eric Carle's.</p>

<p>I'm not saying his books have no redeeming qualities---the pictures are
pretty and they do appeal to the 1-2 year old crowd. But thats not
exactly the most demanding audience and his collage style isn't even
unique. Leo Lionni started publishing picture books with collage back in
1959 and Lois Ehlert won a Caldecott in 1989 for <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Color-Board-Book-Lois-Ehlert/dp/0694010677">Color Zoo</a>.</p>

<p>Leo Lionni in particular deserves far more attention than he gets. The
only good thing about many of his books being out of print is that it
made it slightly easier to pick four Lionni books to send to my sister's
family for Christmas.</p>

<p>Lionni was a late bloomer as a children's book author as he had a full
career as a "real" artist before writing
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Little-Blue-Yellow-Leo-Lionni/dp/0688132855">Little Blue and Little Yellow</a>. His stories are quirky and many push
the envelope on what's possible in a kids' book.  And every one has a
positive message.  For example in his first book, the characters are
splotches of color who get mixed up and turn green.  Their parents don't
recognize them until they cry themselves apart, but then the parents recognize
their mistake and learn not to be so judgmental.</p>

<p>In <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Flea-Story-Leo-Lionni/dp/0905478266">A Flea Story</a>, you never even see the main characters. Instead you
only hear a dialog that's reminiscent of Herman Hesse's odd couple
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Narcissus-Goldmund-Hermann-Hesse/dp/B003NQOS4M">Narcissus and Goldmund</a>. One flea just wants to stay home on their
dog's butt while the other longs for adventure. They travel together for
a while and then split to follow their own paths. Stories that appeal to
both adults and children are rare and those that do usually have two
sets of jokes (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rocky_and_Bullwinkle_Show">Rocky and Bullwinkle</a> is the classic example). Lionni
manages to make the same things funny to all ages.</p>

<p>One of R's favorite Lioni stories is <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Matthews-Dream-Leo-Lionni/dp/067987318X">Matthew's Dream</a>. Matthew is a poor
mouse who visits a museum with his school and is inspired to be an
artist. He dreams fantastic versions of his mundane world and paints
them into reality.  Often when R paints her own pictures she says "I'm
Matthew!"</p>

<p>In <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Alexander-Wind-Up-Mouse-Leo-Lionni/dp/0394829115">Alexander and the Wind-Up Mouse</a>, Alexander yearns to be a windup
mouse who is loved by the family instead of hated and chased with a
broom. He finds a magical lizard who will grant him his wish in exchange
for a purple pebble.  By the time he acquires one, the world has changed
and he learns to be careful what he wishes for.  R still looks for
purple pebbles to give to the lizard.</p>

<p>My one year old does like flipping through Eric Carle board books, but
as soon as she will sit still and let us read to her, she's graduating to
Leo Lionni. The pictures are even more beautiful, the stories are
awesome, and the whole family can enjoy the ride.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[E-books and Kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/02/13/ebooks-and-kids/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/02/13/ebooks-and-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my house we read a lot of books to our kids.  We read after school,
on weekends, while traveling, during meals and (of course) right before
bed.  I was a voracious reader as a kid and I hope to impart this habit
and pure love of reading to my kids.  There's something about reading a
book and visualizing the scenes and action in your mind that expands
your imagination much more than watching a movie ever could.  Reading
with your kids is also a just high quality parent-child time.  You never
have to press pause to stop and talk about issues raised in the story.</p>

<p>We also run a fairly gadget-friendly household.  My wife and I often
work at our computers, we both have iPhones, and our iPad is pretty much
our living room computer.  My three-year old has almost as many apps as
I do.  You would think we would be actively transitioning all our
reading to e-books, but we're not.</p>

<h3><strong>The Good</strong></h3>

<p>E-books have a lot of advantages over physical books.  I love that you
can load up an iPad with a few hundred and it weighs no more than a
couple paperbacks.  While picture books look like junk (if they are
available at all) on the Kindle, they look fine on the iPad.  Some
e-books have a "read aloud" option and will repeat words and sentences
with a touch.  We don't use these features much as a parent is usually the one
reading, but it's nice to have the option.</p>

<p>Pricing of e-books is generally higher than the used physical book
price, but I think (hope?) it's only a matter of time before that changes.
I especially hope that the publishers realize that parents would love to
buy "boxed sets" for a reasonable price.  If I could buy all 26 of the Curious
George books in the iBooks store for $52 (that's $2 each) I'd jump on
it.  Instead, they charge between $3.99 and $8.99 each and I end up
spending a total of $3.99 on George.  We all lose out.</p>

<p>Availability is a similar story--it's lousy now but I have high hopes it
will get better.  The great thing will be that once a book is in digital
format, there's no reason it should ever go out of print.  So when I
want a mint condition copy of Amy Tan's
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Sagwa-Chinese-Siamese-Cat-Amy/dp/0689846177">Sagwa, The Chinese Siamese Cat</a>
I don't have to wait a single minute.  And if libraries can get in on
the action, their catalogs will be amazing.</p>

<h3><strong>The Bad</strong></h3>

<p>As I've already mentioned, the current pricing and availability
situation is atrocious for kids' books.  But these aren't the only
problems.</p>

<p>My iPad has a 9.7 inch display.  The vast majority of the kids' books in
our house are a lot bigger.  That means you either see a small version
of the page or you're constantly panning and zooming.  Graeme Bass'
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Legend-Golden-Snail-Graeme-Base/dp/0810989654">Legend of the Golden Snail</a>
is 12 inches by 22 inches open.  That's 25 inches diagonal
(according to Pythagoras) and it's going to be a long time before tablet
displays get that big.  The resolution on a printed page is a lot better
than my iPad today, but that could presumably <a href="http://www.macrumors.com/2012/02/12/ipad-3-to-pave-way-for-1080p-itunes-content-and-a-new-apple-tv/">change in the next month
or so</a>.
And you can completely forget about duplicating the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0394873742">Richard Scarry's
Biggest Word Book Ever!</a>
experience--it opens to 32 inches by 24 inches.</p>

<p>Even if I'm willing to give in on all this stuff for my three-year-old,
there's no way an e-book works for a one-year-old.  We have close to 100
board books, touch and feel books, and cloth books that can withstand
constant mouthing and provide good tactile feedback.</p>

<h3><strong>The Worrying</strong></h3>

<p>I'm mostly optimistic about the future of e-books for kids, but there
is a trend that worries me.  The kids' e-books that get the most praise
from critics and the highest ratings in the iOS app store tend to be the
flashiest and most movie-like.  Sesame Street's
<a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/monster-at-end-this-book...starring/id409467802">The Monster at the End of This Book</a>
is a perfect example.  It lasted about 5 minutes on my iPad before I saw
my daughter's eyes glaze over and I deleted it.  The Critter books
(e.g.,
<a href="http://itunes.apple.com/app/just-me-and-my-dad-for-ipad/id364723303">Just Me and My Dad</a>)
aren't much better.  They at least let you read the story while you
click around the page trying to make animals do funny things.</p>

<p>It's not that I think interactive features are a bad thing in e-books,
but I think they are a lot more appropriate in books for adults like
<a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/the-elements-a-visual-exploration/id364147847">The Elements: A Visual Exploration</a>
and Al Gore's <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/id432753658">Our Choice</a>.
Even textbooks has a lot to gain from embedded movie clips, social
network integration, and dynamic graphs.  And I'm excited about the new
<a href="http://www.apple.com/ibooks-author/">iBooks Author</a> software enabling a
whole new wave of these kinds of books.</p>

<p>But God help us if children's book publishers suddenly think they have tart up old
content to get us to buy it electronically.  Let my daughters and I
imagine <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Curious-George-Rides-Bike-Rey/dp/0395174449">George riding his bike</a> in the circus without turning it into
mini-game.  Let us laugh about <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Franklin-Messy-Paulette-Bourgeois/dp/0590486861">Franklin's messy closet</a> without having to
interactively explore it.  And let us imagine the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Goodnight-Moon-Book-Margaret-Brown/dp/0061119776">old lady whispering
"hush"</a> without having to hear it out loud.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bad Behavior in Kids' Books]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2011/12/30/bad-behavior/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2011/12/30/bad-behavior</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We do a lot of reading in my house and I don't pay much attention to
age/reading levels.  R (who just turned three) likes books geared to her
own age as well as lots that are for older kids.  Most of the time, this
works out well.  She misses some nuance (e.g., the rich description of
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Wizard-Oz-Puffin-Classics/dp/0141321024">The Wizard of Oz</a>)
and sometimes the main point (e.g., the literalness of
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Amelia-Bedelia-Collection-Read-Book/dp/0060542381">Amelia Bedelia</a>),
but she's almost always entertained.  And I think she gets a lot out of
pushing the envelope.  The best examples of this are science and nature
books.  We've been reading the Pooh Encyclopedias
(<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Very-First-Encylopedia-Winnie-Friends/dp/0786834064">Nature</a>
and
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Very-First-Encylopedia-Winnie-Friends/dp/0786834080">Animals</a>)
and
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Chickens-Arent-Only-World-Nature/dp/0698117786">Chickens Aren't the Only Ones</a>
for months and she's learned a ton.</p>

<p>The place where we get in trouble is when we read books for older kids with bad
behavior.  I don't mean where the main characters are having fun and
they do bad stuff like jumping on the bed (like those damn
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Five-Little-Monkeys-Jumping-Along/dp/0618732764">monkeys</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Skippyjon-Jones-Judy-Schachner/dp/0142404039">Skippyjon Jones</a>)
even though these are also inspiring in the wrong way.  I mean those
books that try to teach kids to behave by showing them how not to
behave.  The prototypical example is
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Berenstain-Bears-Too-Much-Teasing/dp/0679877061">Berenstein Bears and Too Much Teasing</a>
which we read over Thanksgiving.  What we learned is that saying "Nah
nah na nah nah" and calling your father "Flub-a-dub" are hilarious.  The
novelty wore off fast (for me, not her).  When we read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Best-Friends-Frances-Read-Book/dp/0060838035">Best Friends for Frances</a> we learned
that doing things with No Boys Allowed is fun.  When we read
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Dinosaurs-Play-Their-Friends/dp/B001VF5I1Y">How do Dinosaurs Play with Their Friends?</a> we learned to hog up toys
and say "Mine!" and when we read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Do-Dinosaurs-Say-Goodnight/dp/0590316818">How do Dinosaurs Say Goodnight?</a> we
learned to demand even more stories than usual before bed.  R learned
that fighting (and making up) with your friends is fun from the otherwise truly wonderful <a href="http://www.amazon.com/What-Busy-Day-Gyo-Fujikawa/dp/1402768192">Oh What a Busy Day</a>.</p>

<p>In fact, the only case I can think of where the authors actually pull
off this trick is
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Be-Friend-Friends-Families/dp/0316111538">How to Be a Friend</a>
which is a remarkably great manual from which most adults would learn a
thing or two.  R has yet to copy the bad stuff and is on the edge of her seat
throughout.  It even gets a lot of requests (i.e., "Excuse me, will you
read this?")</p>

<p>The lesson we've learned in our house is to recognize and quarantine
these books as fast as possible and hope we remember to bring them out
again when the girls are ready.  Of course, we'll probably be reading
them to R as her younger sister A listens in and then goes and jumps on her bed!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
