<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[kids | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/categories/kids/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-16T21:34:21-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Halloween Edition]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/11/16/kid-book-review-halloween/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/11/16/kid-book-review-halloween</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About a week before Halloween, R and I raided the library’s selection of
Halloween-appropriate picture books.  I’ve felt
<a href="http://highvariance.net/post/21370720836/kid-book-review-library-trip-report-2">guilty before</a>
about skimming the cream but hopefully sharing what we learned
will balance out the karma.  Before I start, I know what you’re
thinking: “It’s the middle of November!  Who cares about Halloween?  How about sharing something useful
like the top 10 Thanksgiving picture books?”  Don’t worry, that’ll be
here before Christmas.  In the meantime, bookmark this page and put a
note on your calendar to check back on October 15, 2013 and then head to
your local library.  On with the show!</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Franklins-Halloween-Paulette-Bourgeois/dp/0590693301">Franklin’s Halloween</a>
(by Paulette Bourgeois, illustrated by Brenda Clark) Franklin is one
of my favorite recurring lovable-yet-flawed characters.  He’s just a
regular kid (turtle) who usually gets in some sort of minor trouble
and learns from his mistakes.  He’s kind of
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Franklin-Messy-Paulette-Bourgeois/dp/0590486861">messy</a>,
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Franklin-Plays-Game-Paulette-Bourgeois/dp/0590226312">not very athletic</a>,
and has even been known to <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Franklin-Fibs-Paulette-Bourgeois/dp/0590446479">tell a fib or two</a>.  In this book, he just
has fun making his own Halloween costume and going to a party.
There’s a great spooky twist at the end and he’s even generous to a
sick friend.  Hurray for Franklin!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Brooms-Are-Flying-Michael-Rex/dp/0312380151">Brooms Are for Flying</a> (by Michael Rex) and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Humbug-Witch-Lorna-Balian/dp/159572009X">Humbug Witch</a> (by
Lorna Bailin) Spoiler Alert!  These two books are simple and cute.
One is about a witch who turns out to be a girl at the end and the
other is about a girl who turns out to be a witch at the end!  </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/WITCH-WHO-LIVES-DOWN-HALL/dp/B000J4MU7I">The Witch Who Lives Down the Hall</a> (by Donna Guthrie, illustrated
by Amy Schwartz) The mostly black and white illustrations (with
touches of orange) are a great complement to a story about a boy who
lives down the hall from a “strange” lady and her black cat.  He’s
convinced she’s a witch.  Clever and funny to both kids and adults.
Reminded me a lot of <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/18359444436/kid-book-review-monster-edition">Mrs. Muffly’s Monster</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Terrible-Halloween-Night-James-Stevenson/dp/0688099327">That Terrible Halloween Night</a>
  (by James Stevenson) This is about as scary as you can get and still
  be appropriate for a three year-old. I loved it and R is still talking
  about it.  Last night she told me our basement floor was covered with
  frogs!  I liked the pen and pastel comic book layout too.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Cake-Girl-David-Lucas/dp/B003NHR9OM">Cake Girl</a> (by David Lucas) <a href="http://www.amazon.com/David-Lucas/e/B001HMTVBY">David Lucas</a> is so good–all his books
have such sweet characters, surreal stories, and pretty
illustrations.  This one is about a witch who learns about friendship.</p>
  </li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mythical Creatures]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/10/13/mythical-creatures/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/10/13/mythical-creatures</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Basilisk/Cockatrice</strong></p>

<pre><code>Head and body of a cock,
Its breath cracks rock.

Leather wings--Whish!
Serpent tail--Swish!
A Basilisk--Hisss!
No doodle-head this!

(A Basilisk!--HISSS!
    Is also called--HISSS!
    A Cockatrice.)
 
HISSSSSS!
 
                  by Laura Whipple
</code></pre>

<p>As you may remember from <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/22767550387/carle-vs-lionni-no-accounting-for-taste">my last post</a>, my older daughter loves Greek
mythology, but the stories are hopelessly age-inappropriate. We’ve been
reading them anyway and I try to tone them down on the fly with limited
success.  What I’ve really wanted was something that could extract the
magic and wonder of the creatures and leave the ultra-violence and the
mixed moral messages behind.  It turns out I owe Eric Carle an apology
because he’s published exactly the book I was looking for.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Eric-Carles-Dragons-Carle/dp/014240103X">Dragons, Dragons</a> combines Eric Carle’s admittedly pretty
collage pictures with poems about 30 mythical creatures from around the
world.  Many are from Greek myths (e.g., Cerberus, Pegasus, the
Minotaur!) but they also hail from Japan (kappa), Africa (Okolo), the
Americas (Quetzalcoatl), Australia (bunyip), the Middle East
(manticore and roc), and other places.  In some cases the artistic representations don’t
match the images in my head (in addition to his lion’s head, the
chimaera has a goat’s head sprouting out of his back!) but considering
we don’t have any actual specimens to determine who is “correct,” I
don’t mind.</p>

<p>My favorite part of the book is the poetry.  Why should mythical
creatures be constrained to prose?  To accompany his illustrations,
Mr. Carle has chosen work ranging from classic (William Blake and
Elizabeth Barrett Browning) to poets I’ve never heard of but are a lot
of fun (see Laura Whipple’s contribution above).  R learns vocabulary
when we read them and she definitely appreciates the vivid word pictures
and rhymes.  She’s already memorized a few of the poems and there’s even
one (the Phoenix) that is written specifically for two voices.</p>

<p><a href="http://highvariance.net/post/22767550387/carle-vs-lionni-no-accounting-for-taste">I’m still not a fan</a> of all of Eric Carle’s work, but this book is almost perfect.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Violence in Kids' Books]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/10/06/violence-in-kids-books/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/10/06/violence-in-kids-books</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My 3.5 year old daughter wants to be a minotaur for Halloween. She loves
the idea of a person with a bull’s head. She knows that minotaurs live
in labyrinths and eat humans.  For her costume, she wants to carry an
axe.  And whenever we play minotaur, she wants me to be Theseus and she
often wants to “fight to death!”  Someday she’ll know what death is and
understand the consequences of a real fight, but for now these are just
fun words to say.</p>

<p>It all started more than a year ago when she was in a phase where she
wanted me to tell her new stories all the time.  And I mean about 25
times per day.  I quickly ran out of kid stories and moved on to stories
about my old pets and stories about my childhood.  Then I remembered the
Greeks had some good stories and started telling her about Daedalus and
Icarus, Pandora’s Box, and the 12 Labors of Heracles.  She thought they
were great and I ordered a copy of
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Greek-Myths-Young-Children-Heather/dp/0794530494">Greek Myths for Young Children</a> which was age inappropriate
(despite the title) but at least jogged my memory for a few more
stories.</p>

<p>About a month ago I brought out the book again and she loved it so much
she asked for a new Greek myth as her bed-time story every night.  She
especially loved the vivid characters and creatures, and she can now
tell you that Prince Bellerophon rode Pegasus, Cerberus has three heads,
and a Chimaera has the body of a goat, head of a lion and a snake for a
tail.  The stories were violent, but the language was relatively tame.</p>

<p>I was ambivalent about the situation, but then we crossed a line when I
picked up a few more “kids” mythology books at the library.  Suddenly
instead of just eating humans, the minotaur “had a taste for human
flesh.”  Centaurs were getting drunk and chasing bridesmaids and the
sphinx was tearing apart unfortunate travelers and devouring them.  I
skipped a lot of this, but then the babysitter started reading the
stories verbatim.  It was bad.</p>

<p>Now some people might wonder what the big deal is.  Weren’t old fairy
tales really violent too?  Didn’t Little Red Riding Hood’s grandmother
get eaten by a wolf?  Didn’t Hansel and Gretel get cooked in an oven?
Indeed, they did.  And those fairy tales werre written at a time when
violence was a normal part of everyday life.  Public life in the middle
class United Stated is far far less violent today and we run a pretty
pacifist household.  Violent fairy tales are not “keeping it real” for
us. I feel no need to expose my girls to realistic stories of violence
until they’ve got the tools to understand and process it.  I don’t want
to violence to be normal.  I don’t want them scared that if they go in
the woods they will get eaten by a witch or a wolf.  I don’t want them
playing fighting games at school even if they seem fun or even funny.</p>

<p>The time will come when all the violence that exists in pop culture on
tv, in the theater, at the movies, and in grown-up books will push
through our walls and into their lives.  And hopefully by that time they
will be old enough to know that it’s serious business.</p>

<p>Does this mean we’re banning Greek myths from house?  Not exactly.
We’re trying a compromise solution.  For now, I edit as I read. Theseus
and the Minotaur fight, but not always to the death.  Heracles has a
simpler young adulthood where he does not “fly into a rage and kill all
his children.”  And Theseus’ father doesn’t leap off a cliff to his
death because his son forgot to fly the white sail.  When the girls are
older they can read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bulfinchs-Mythology-Volumes-Chivalry-Charlemagne/dp/1440426309">Bullfinch’s</a> on their own and get maximum
mayhem. Until then Theseus and the Minotaur can be friends who
occasionally walk Cerberus around the block.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Carle vs. Lionni: No Accounting for Taste]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/05/10/carle-vs-lioni/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/05/10/carle-vs-lioni</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most grown-ups, even those without kids, have heard of Eric Carle—He is
an extremely popular children’s book author who illustrates using
collage.  In fact, his <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Brown-Bear-What-You-See/dp/0805047905">Brown Bear Brown Bear What Do See</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Very-Hungry-Caterpillar-Eric-Carle/dp/0399226907">The Very Hungry Caterpillar</a> have now supplanted Margaret Wise Brown’s
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Goodnight-Moon-Margaret-Wise-Brown/dp/0694003611">Goodnight Moon</a> as the standard gift for newborn kids.</p>

<p>Both my daughters celebrated Eric Carle week at school last month
and it got me thinking (again) just how over-rated he is.  He’s
either today’s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman_Rockwell">Norman Rockwell</a> or the kids’ version of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Kinkade">Thomas Kinkade</a>
(“Painter of Light”).<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>  With a few exceptions (like <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Secret-Birthday-Message-Board-Book/dp/0694011487">The Secret Birthday Message</a>), his books couldn’t be more repetitive and formulaic.</p>

<p>I’m not saying his books have no redeeming qualities—the pictures are
pretty and they do appeal to the 1-2 year old crowd. But thats not
exactly the most demanding audience and his collage style isn’t even
unique. Leo Lionni started publishing picture books with collage back in
1959 and Lois Ehlert won a Caldecott in 1989 for <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Color-Board-Book-Lois-Ehlert/dp/0694010677">Color Zoo</a>.</p>

<p>Leo Lionni in particular deserves far more attention than he gets. The
only good thing about many of his books being out of print is that it
made it slightly easier to pick four Lionni books to send to my sister’s
family for Christmas.</p>

<p>Lionni was a late bloomer as a children’s book author as he had a full
career as a “real” artist before writing
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Little-Blue-Yellow-Leo-Lionni/dp/0688132855">Little Blue and Little Yellow</a>. His stories are quirky and many push
the envelope on what’s possible in a kids’ book.  And every one has a
positive message.  For example in his first book, the characters are
splotches of color who get mixed up and turn green.  Their parents don’t
recognize them until they cry themselves apart, but then the parents recognize
their mistake and learn not to be so judgmental.</p>

<p>In <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Flea-Story-Leo-Lionni/dp/0905478266">A Flea Story</a>, you never even see the main characters. Instead you
only hear a dialog that’s reminiscent of Herman Hesse’s odd couple
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Narcissus-Goldmund-Hermann-Hesse/dp/B003NQOS4M">Narcissus and Goldmund</a>. One flea just wants to stay home on their
dog’s butt while the other longs for adventure. They travel together for
a while and then split to follow their own paths. Stories that appeal to
both adults and children are rare and those that do usually have two
sets of jokes (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rocky_and_Bullwinkle_Show">Rocky and Bullwinkle</a> is the classic example). Lionni
manages to make the same things funny to all ages.</p>

<p>One of R’s favorite Lioni stories is <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Matthews-Dream-Leo-Lionni/dp/067987318X">Matthew’s Dream</a>. Matthew is a poor
mouse who visits a museum with his school and is inspired to be an
artist. He dreams fantastic versions of his mundane world and paints
them into reality.  Often when R paints her own pictures she says “I’m
Matthew!”</p>

<p>In <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Alexander-Wind-Up-Mouse-Leo-Lionni/dp/0394829115">Alexander and the Wind-Up Mouse</a>, Alexander yearns to be a windup
mouse who is loved by the family instead of hated and chased with a
broom. He finds a magical lizard who will grant him his wish in exchange
for a purple pebble.  By the time he acquires one, the world has changed
and he learns to be careful what he wishes for.  R still looks for
purple pebbles to give to the lizard.</p>

<p>My one year old does like flipping through Eric Carle board books, but
as soon as she will sit still and let us read to her, she’s graduating to
Leo Lionni. The pictures are even more beautiful, the stories are
awesome, and the whole family can enjoy the ride.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>My wife thinks it’s a cheap shot comparing Carle to Kinkade, but I
never miss a chance to bring up my favorite abusive alcoholic
religious nut-job artist, even if he did pass away recently.  And the
truth is, I think his work is pretty.  Just like Eric Carle’s.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Library Trip Report 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/04/28/kid-book-review-library-trip-report-2/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/04/28/kid-book-review-library-trip-report-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The main goal of our biweekly trip to the New Haven Free Public Library is to
pick 20 or so great picture books.  I’m looking for books with beautiful
art, lovable (or at least memorable) characters, an original story, and
a positive message.  These books are rare and they’re difficult to
identify by a book spine, a book cover, or even a quick perusal.  And I
don’t have time for much more than that.</p>

<p>So the failure rate is high, but in this case failing isn’t all that bad
an outcome.  In fact, most books that come home succeed on at least one
dimension.  Sometimes the books are so spectacularly awful or
inappropriate that they stretch your brain.  And often R’s favorite
books are not my favorites.  The bottom line is that we both get a fair
amount out of reading the mediocre bulk of our haul, even when most get
returned never to be read again.</p>

<p>Our latest keepers:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Umbrella-Queen-Shirin-Bridges/dp/0060750405">The Umbrella Queen</a> (by Shirin Yim Bridges, illustrated by Taeeun
  Yoo) I have a special place in my heart for atypical stories
  that take place in other countries.  And even better, I
  like stories about kids who are true to themselves.  This book takes
  place in Thailand and follows a girl whose inner artist cannot
  be squashed.  It reminds me a lot of
  <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Empty-Pot-Demi/dp/0805082271">The Empty Pot</a>(by
  Demi) and I Ioved
  that too.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Library-Lion-Michelle-Knudsen/dp/076363784X">Library Lion</a> (by Michelle Knudsen, illustrated by Kevin Hawkes) The
  lesson here is fantastic: Rules are good, but there are always
  extenuating circumstances when they should be broken.  The premise is
  absurd (a friendly helpful lion hangs out at the library) but not
  totally drug-addled (see
  <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Hogula-Dread-Night-Jean-Gralley/dp/0805071644/">Hogula: the Dread Pig of the Night</a> (by
  Jean Gralley) for an
  example of the latter).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Night-Worker-Kate-Banks/dp/0374400008">The Night Worker</a> (by Kate Banks, illustrated by Georg Hallensleben)
A respectful portrayal of a Latino engineer who takes a son to the job
site one night.  Lots of construction equipment and beautiful almost
Gauguin-style paintings.  What’s not to love?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Maxs-Dragon-Kate-Banks/dp/B003IWYJIG">Max’s Dragon</a>by Kate Banks, illustrated by Boris Kulikov) This
story is about two (older?) brothers playing croquet and their quirky
(younger?) brother who has a big imagination and loves rhymes.
Super-cute and super-original and the art is good though not my
favorite style.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Polar-Bear-Easy---Read-Puffin/dp/0140386920">A Polar Bear Can Swim</a> (by Harriet Ziefert, illustrated by Emily
Bolam) This book is designed for kids who are learning to read on
their own and who are curious about animals and science.  That’s a
perfect match for R.  It’s filled with fun facts (“A cow can drink 75
gallons of water in a day!”) and simple artwork.  I’m excited to check out
other members of the Viking Science Easy-to-Read series.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Balloons-Dee-Lillegard/dp/0525459405">Balloons Balloons Balloons</a> (by Dee Lillegard, illustrated by
Bernadette Pons) I admit I find this book a little brain-numbing, but
R is going to love any book that has a rabbit in a hot air balloon
dumping huge numbers of multicolored balloons on a whole town.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Secret-River-Marjorie-Kinnan-Rawlings/dp/1416911790">The Secret River</a> (by Marjorie Kinnan Rawlings, illustrated by Leo
and Diane Dillon) This book is special.  It was written in 1947 by the
author of
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Yearling-Aladdin-Classics-Marjorie-Rawlings/dp/0689846231">The Yearling</a>
and it follows a poor black girl who lives in the rural South in the
early part of the 20th century.  I don’t have a lot of experience with
this environment, but it sure seems real to me.  The art is great and
the story is magical in a way that works for adults and children.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Honorable mentions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Ginger-Bear-Mini-Grey/dp/0375842535">Ginger Bear</a> (by Mini Grey) R and I both like the part where Horace
smears cookie dough all over the toilet seat, but it goes downhill
from there.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Really-Rabbits-Virginia-L-Kroll/dp/157091897X">Really Rabbits</a> (by Virginia Kroll, illustrated by Philomena
O’Neill) Cute story about two pet rabbits who do household chores in
the middle of the night.  We could use these guys in our house.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Wonder-Woman-Classic-Read-Book/dp/0061885177">Wonder Woman: I am Wonder Woman</a> (by Eric K. Stein, illustrated by
Rick Farley) An adaptation of a comic book?  Really? Yes!  Wonder Woman is a
positive role model for girls and R loves her tiara and bracelets.
And it doesn’t hurt that Dad had a thing for
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynda_Carter#Wonder_Woman">Linda Carter</a>
when he was in high school.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Punk-Farm-Tour-Jarrett-Krosoczka/dp/0375833439">Punk Farm On Tour</a> (by Jarrett J. Krosoczka) It’s really quite good,
but if you already have <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Punk-Farm-Jarrett-J-Krosoczka/dp/0440417937">Punk Farm</a> you’re not getting a whole lot
more here.  If you don’t have <em>Punk Farm</em> yet, you need to run out and
get it right away!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Tricycle-Elisa-Amado/dp/0888996144">Tricycle</a> (by Elisa Amado, illustrated by Alfonso Ruano) A girl from
a wealthy family in Guatemala is friends with three poor kids next
door.  She sees them steal her tricycle but doesn’t say anything to
her parents because she knows she shouldn’t have left it in the bushes
and she already has a lot more stuff than they have.  I love the complex
emotions and the interplay of personal relationships and the gulf
between rich and poor that exists pretty much everywhere but is
especially stark in Latin America.  All of this is lost on R, but
she’s 3.  I’m not so sure she’ll get it at 5 either, but I commend the
authors for trying!</p>
  </li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
