<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[mundane | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/mundane/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-19T10:59:42-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Three Great Product Features]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/04/three-great-product-features/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/04/three-great-product-features</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Great products get reviewed and talked about, but great features of good products often fly under the radar. They can seem obvious in hindsight or just have a niche group that really appreciates them. Here are three of my favorites that deserve more notice.</p>

<p>{% img right /images/hv-control-center.png %}</p>

<p><strong>1. Control Center</strong></p>

<p>Hands down my favorite new feature of iOS 7, the Control Center removes lots of little dead moments from my life. Every night I lock my phone into portrait mode when I get in bed. I use the flashlight at least twice a day. I select an Airplay destination or use the music controls about twice a day. And in the morning I free up the phone’s orientation again. Since I don’t even have to unlock the phone to do any of this, it saves me at least five seconds each time. That adds up to a minimum of 30 seconds a day and three whole hours a year.</p>

<p>{% img left /images/hv-whispersync.jpg %}</p>

<p><strong>2. Whispersync</strong></p>

<p>After the kids go to sleep and I’m cleaning the kitchen or putting toys away, I like to listen to audiobooks. When it’s particularly gripping, I continue to read the book on my phone in bed using the Kindle app. Whispersync means I automatically pick up right where I left off on the audio. The next night when I start listening again, the Audible app jumps to where I was in the e-book. I can’t imagine too many people take advantage of this, but I love it. </p>

<p>{% img right /images/hv-sneeze-shield.jpg %}</p>

<p><strong>3. Sneeze Shield</strong></p>

<p>Maybe our bedroom is dusty. Maybe I have allergies. Maybe I get a lot of low-grade colds. I don’t know why I sneeze a few times almost every morning when I wake up, but I do. And with two little kids, we all get our share of normal-grade colds. This means we go through a lot of tissues. Sneeze Shield means the tissue doesn’t fall apart when a grown up blows into it. I don’t miss handfuls of wet snot at all.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bathroom Fan Love Letters]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/10/30/bathroom-fan-love-letters/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/10/30/bathroom-fan-love-letters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two of my favorite bloggers (<a href="http://www.marco.org">Marco Arment</a> and <a href="http://brooksreview.net">Ben Brooks</a>) recently
published passionate <a href="http://www.marco.org/2012/05/06/bathroom-fan-timer-switches">love</a> <a href="http://brooksreview.net/2012/03/amazon-item/">letters</a> to the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B003TJAGPS">Panasonic WhisperCeiling</a> bathroom
fan, and in Marco’s case, a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00313JXB0">Leviton electronic timer switch</a>.  Since
our downstairs bathroom has had no fan at all for more than a year, and
our upstairs bathroom fan sounded like a jet engine (and took 20 minutes
to de-fog a mirror), I took this as a sign that it was time to upgrade.
It was harder than expected to find an electrician to install them, but
today was the big day.  It’s worked out pretty well for our upstairs
bathroom, but not so much for the downstairs bathroom.  In fact, I was
surprised by three issues that were unmentioned in the “reviews” I read:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>The Panasonic WhisperLite fan/light combo unit is approximately
square and it doesn’t fit in our downstairs bathroom because we have a
cast-iron drain pipe running 8.5” away from the stud where the fan has
to be mounted.  Drat.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The bulbs in the WhisperLite are compact-fluorescent and they send
out a very white light.  I like it, but my wife calls it “institutional”
and she says it reminds her of a public restroom.  This isn’t exactly
where anyone wants to be taking a shower, and if she doesn’t acclimate, I’m
hoping we can just change the bulbs to something a little softer.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Leviton switch requires three wires (including a neutral) and our
downstairs bathroom only has two.  If I want a timer switch we either
spend $200 to run a new line (I’m not <em>that</em> crazy) or we get one of
those <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Intermatic-FD15MWC-15-Minute-Spring-Loaded/dp/B000EVS4WG">spring-loaded knobs</a> that screams hotel sauna.  For now, we’re
sticking with the old manual switch.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>To be fair, the new fan is very quiet and is working like a champ–our
upstairs bathroom isn’t small and during a leisurely shower the mirror
never fogged up.  And the Leviton timer is far more reliable than I was
about remembering to turn off the fan when it’s done its job.  But I
think there is a bigger lesson here: Some products that are perfect for
some people (or bathrooms) are not perfect for others, and we shouldn’t
let ourselves be blinded by the opinions of fan-bois.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ode to My Messenger Bag]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/02/02/ode-to-my-messenger-bag/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/02/02/ode-to-my-messenger-bag</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Messenger bags have been getting a lot of flack on
<a href="http://brooksreview.net/2011/12/backpacks-my-bff/">Ben Brooks’ blog</a>
lately as he has made the complete switch to a
<a href="http://www.tombihn.com/page/001/PROD/100/TB0103">Tom Bihn Smart Alec backpack</a>.
He raves about the ergonomics and pockets and even makes a case that it
looks kinda cool.  Maybe this set up works for him, but I’m very happy
with my decidedly non-hipster plain vanilla blue and black
<a href="http://www.timbuk2.com/tb2/products/classic-messenger/1809057">Timbuk2 Classic Messenger</a>.</p>

<p>It’s almost all one cavernous compartment which gives me maximum
flexibility.  It’s is perfect for any combination of books, folders,
iPads, or my MacBook Air in it’s Zero Shock sleeve.  I leave the sleeve
unzipped so it’s easy to take the MBA in and out and if I don’t need it,
the whole sleeve/MBA combo stays home.  I love the simplicity of never
having to remember what’s in what pocket.  I’ve even used it to
transport pretty big boxes– they can stick out if need be and the flap
can partially cover them but be secured by the strap.</p>

<p>It’s super-fast to open and close since I don’t have to take it off my
back or loosen any straps.  I can keep my bike lock there when I’m out
and about and it’s trivial to pull it out and put it back in as needed.</p>

<p>It’s perfect for cycling–the weight is on your hips instead of your
back/shoulders and that makes for much better stability.  Just make sure
you use the strap that attaches to a belt loop so it doesn’t swing
around unexpectedly.</p>

<p>The ballistic nylon show almost no wear.  My bag is six years old and
I’ve put it through the laundry maybe three times.  And it’s not like I’ve
babied it–it’s with me outdoors every day rain, shine, or even the
arctic conditions of last winter in Connecticut.</p>

<p>The bottom line: Six years from now I’ll probably be using exactly the
same bag.  And it’ll still look great.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Radiators, Thermostats, and Heat Momentum]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/01/14/radiators-thermostats-and-heat-momentum/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/01/14/radiators-thermostats-and-heat-momentum</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We’re deep into our first winter in the new house and are just now
figuring out how to properly control the indoor temperature.  On the
plus side, we’ve got the ingredients of a fabulous heating system.  The
brand-new
<a href="http://www.buderus.us/products/gasheating/gasconventionalboilers/loganog234x.html">gas-fired boiler</a>
is <em>so</em> much cheaper and cleaner than the oil-fueled relic that was here
when we moved in.  The house was built in the 1920’s and has one
or two huge radiators in every room.  We even have a
programmable thermostat (a Lux TX500B which is nearly identical to the
current <a href="http://www.luxproducts.com/thermostats/tx500e.php">Lux TX500E</a>)
so we can lower the temperature during the day when we’re at work and at
night when we’re in bed.</p>

<p>For the last couple months, the thermostat would turn on the boiler at
6:00 am and keep it on until the house reached 68 F.  The problem was
that even though the boiler turned off, the radiators were still full of
hot water and they would continue heating the house driving the
temperature up to 71 or 72 and driving me kind of crazy.  The same thing
would happen in the afternoon when we got home from work.</p>

<p>My first thought was that there must be a setting on the thermostat to
account for what I’m calling “radiator heat momentum”.  There isn’t.
The closest you can get is to lower the minimum amount of time the
boiler is on and that doesn’t actually help in most situations.  My
second thought was that this was a great excuse to get a
<a href="http://www.nest.com">Nest</a>–it’s the only thermostat anyone has ever
described as sexy, but as far as I can tell, its AI smarts are all about
saving you 10 minutes of programming.  This is especially true if you
have a pretty rigid schedule.  And it has no special knowledge of
radiators.  Oh well.</p>

<p>The solution we’ve settled on is imperfect, but  good and easy to
implement with some semi-creative thermostat programming.</p>

<p>WEEKDAYS: In the morning, we simply set the thermostat to go to 66 and
the temperature drifts up to where we want it after the boiler turns
off.  During the day, the house goes down to 62 and at 4:30 pm, the
thermostat goes back to 67.  The temperature drifts up a little higher
than we’d like, but we don’t want it to drop below 67 before we go to
bed and we can only have 4 different temperature settings per day. (Yes,
I think this restriction is ridiculous.)</p>

<p>WEEKENDS: At 6:00 am, the thermostat jumps to 66 and drifts up to about
68 within the hour.  At 7:00 am, the thermostat goes to 68 and that
keeps the house from getting too cold during the day when we are around.  We also set the
Swing on the thermostat to 0.25 degrees; this means the boiler turns on
fairly often for short periods of time but these little firings during the
day don’t generate much momentum–it’s really just the big push in the
morning and in the afternoon during the week that cause a problem.  It’s
possible we could raise the Swing and be a little more efficient and
still not generate much heat momentum.</p>

<p>I’m don’t know why other folks aren’t complaining about this (since
radiator heat isn’t <em>that</em> rare) and why the thermostats don’t handle it
more transparently.  My best guess is that less than mammoth radiators
don’t hold their heat as well and so it’s just not an issue in houses
with average radiators.  Either that or the solution I’ve come up with
is so obvious that no one feels the need to talk about it.  My ego tells
me it’s the former so I’m going with that.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Humidifers]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/01/11/humidifiers/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/01/11/humidifiers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Having someone I respect validate a choice I’ve made always gives me a
warm feeling inside.  In
<a href="http://www.marco.org/2012/01/10/humidifiers">a recent post</a>,
<a href="http://www.marco.org">Marco Arment</a> discusses and recommends
humidifiers. The upshot is that evaporative humidifiers work best, but I
wanted throw my four cents in.</p>

<p>First, steam humidifers are pretty dangerous around small children.  The
last thing I want is an inviting vat of hot water falling off the dresser and
boiling my girls.  Of course I can only find perfectly safe (though
not very effective)
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Crane-Gallon-Humidifier-Hello-Kitty/dp/B000MR4IX6">ultrasonic Hello Kitty humidifers</a>
on the web, so it’s not a huge crisis.</p>

<p>Second, we have a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Honeywell-QuietCare-Cool-Moisture-Humidifier-3-Gallon/dp/B0002UXDRA">Honeywell HCM-630</a> 3 gallon cool moisture humidifier in
our bedroom.  It’s now $60 on Amazon, but it was $30 when we bought it 4
years ago.  We end up refilling it almost every day and it does a pretty
good job on a relatively small room with the door open.  But the air
coming out is cold enough that we have to be careful that it doesn’t
blow too close to the baby’s sleep area.</p>

<p>Third, we don’t use the
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B0002TSA8S/?tag=marcoorg-20">liquid additive</a>
that Marco recommends, but we do use
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/ProTec-PC-1-Humidifier-Cleaning-Cartridge/dp/B000FKJRDG/ref=pd_sim_k_5">these cleaning cartridges</a>.
They definitely work, but I bet Marco’s solution ends up being cheaper.</p>

<p>Finally, it’s really important to run the thing every day or the filter
dries out and gets very gross very fast.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
