<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[blog | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-03T22:27:15-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Teach Better: My New Teaching Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/11/teach-better/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/11/teach-better</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://teachbetter.co"><img src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-teach-better.png" /></a></p>

<p>I am very happy to announce the birth of this blog’s first child!</p>

<p><a href="http://teachbetter.co">Teach Better</a> is the new home for everything I have to say about teaching and education in general. <a href="http://highvariance.net">High Variance</a> will remain high variance, and you can continue to come here for regular <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/18/crucial-years-in-metal-1983/">rants about 80’s music</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/09/05/the-stars-align/">heartwarming kid stories</a> and <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/02/26/kid-book-review-monster-edition/">book reviews</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/27/conan-the-snowman/">original Christmas carols</a>, and the occasional <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/02/27/mlp-revelations/">ridiculous theory</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Second Blogoversary]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/02/13/my-second-blogoversary/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/02/13/my-second-blogoversary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the past few weeks this blog has achieved two big milestones: December 21 marked the second anniversary of <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2011/12/21/first-post/">my first post</a>, and on December 30, I published my 100th article. To mark the occasion, I thought it would be fun to reflect on the past two years quantitatively.</p>

<p>In <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/22/happy-blogoversary/">2012</a>, I published 54 articles with 29,699 words, and in 2013, I posted 44 articles with 27,938 words–a decline, but not a major one. The average length of an article went up (550 words vs. 635 words) as did the standard deviation of the word count per article (296 words vs. 394 words). The increasing variance on this dimension can be seen visually in these two overlaid histograms:</p>

<p><img src="/images/analyze-2014-02-09/wchist.png"></p>

<p>So is this blog high variance in article length? That’s hard to say without scraping a bunch of other blogs and analyzing the data. <a href="http://mattgemmell.com/how-i-write/">Matt Gemmell</a> says the distribution of his article lengths is bimodal:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When I’m not writing to a count, I have two natural lengths of piece:</p>

  <ul>
    <li>700 to 1,000 words for a compact exposition on a topic. This is also an ideal bite-sized chunk of text for the reader, and fits well on a single page. It’s no coincidence that the majority of commissioned magazine pieces fall into this band.</li>
    <li>2,000 to 3,500 words for a more detailed exploration or discussion.</li>
  </ul>

  <p>The zone between the two is a death march.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I seem to have one natural length, but its range is a bit broader than Matt’s shorter pieces, as only half my articles fall within 369 and 724 words. If you include Matt’s longer pieces, he clearly wears the higher variance crown.</p>

<p>The yearly numbers mask an interesting monthly pattern. While I wrote a little less in 2013, I was more consistent in my output during the year. In both years I started strong, gradually slowed down, and then picked up the pace again in the fall:</p>

<p><img src="/images/analyze-2014-02-09/ac.png">
<img src="/images/analyze-2014-02-09/wc.png"></p>

<p>Most article content seems to have settled into a small set of categories (<a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/categories/tech/">tech</a>, <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/categories/kids/">kids</a>, <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/categories/education/">education</a>, and <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/categories/music/">music</a>. You could even make an argument that you’re reading a mixture of four distinct extremely low-traffic blogs with the occasional off-the-wall post thrown in. The below picture shows article counts by tag for each year for each tag that had more than one article. Many articles are tagged more than one way and every article I’ve published had at least one of the tags shown below. I wrote a bit more about education and Conan in 2013 and a bit less about music, but I’m not sure those trends will continue in 2014.</p>

<p><img src="/images/analyze-2014-02-09/tags.png"></p>

<p>On the demand side, High Variance had 8,504 unique visitors in 2013 (up from 2,017) and 13,809 page views (up from 4,000). Chris Blattmann <a href="http://chrisblattman.com/2013/04/18/links-i-liked-220/">pointed his firehose my way</a> in mid-April, but even if I ignore that week (961 unique visitors and 1,578 page views), readership is still way up for the year.</p>

<p><img src="/images/analyze-2014-02-09/traffic-2013.png"></p>

<p>To celebrate, I’ve made a few minor tweeks to the site. First, I’ve added an <a href="http://ifttt.com">IFTTT</a> rule that tweets every time I post something new. You can follow me at <a href="https://twitter.com/intent/follow?screen_name=HighVarianceNet">HighVarianceNet</a>. Second, I’ve made it easier to share content on the site by adding links for tweeting articles and sharing them on Facebook. Third, I’ve signed up as an <a href="https://affiliate-program.amazon.com/gp/associates/join/landing/main.html">Amazon associate</a>. That means if you follow a link from this site to Amazon and then buy the product, you’ll pay the same price but I’ll get a few cents. Maybe by the end of next year I’ll be able to celebrate with a free cup of coffee.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scratching my nerd itch with Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/29/scratching-my-nerd-itch/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/29/scratching-my-nerd-itch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I started this blog, I chose a platform that would give me a site that looked fine out of the box so I could concentrate on the writing.  <a href="http://www.tumblr.com">Tumblr</a> fit this requirement and even provided several nice features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Built-in search</li>
  <li>Organization with tags so visitors could easily find articles by category</li>
  <li>Easy integration with Disqus comments</li>
  <li>Built-in <a href="http://www.usa.gov/Topics/Reference-Shelf/Libraries/RSS-Library/What-Is-RSS.shtml">RSS feed</a> for those who want to subscribe</li>
  <li>Automatic announcement of new articles to Facebook</li>
  <li>Easy integration with <a href="http://www.google.com/analytics/">Google Analytics</a> (for traffic statistics)</li>
</ul>

<p>Now, a year later, I have more of a vision for what I want to do with the site and I’m ready to tinker a bit. Unfortunately, while there’s some flexibility in how a Tumblr site looks, but they don’t give you any real control. Ever since high school I’ve spent regular chunks of time writing code and bending computers to my will. I’ve done this as a professional software developer, as a research economist, and often just messing around. The last year has been less geeky than usual as I’ve concentrated on teaching and less technical research projects.  It’s time to scratch my nerd itch.</p>

<p>I’ve chosen to switch to a particularly nerdy blog platform (<a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a>) that requires using command-line tools, but it has the huge benefit of total control. Octopress is built on top of <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll#readme">Jekyll</a> which is written in <a href="http://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</a> and I can tweek it as much as I’d like. I’ve always wanted to learn Ruby and reading and modifying other other people’s code is a great way to learn a language.</p>

<p>In addition to Octopress/Jekyll/Ruby, this project gets me up to speed on several other modern nerdy technologies:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://mxcl.github.com/homebrew/">Homebrew</a> is a package manager for MacOS that lets you install all sorts of open source software including the latest version of Ruby.</li>
  <li><a href="http://git-scm.com">git</a> is what version control will look like for years to come–it’s fast, collaborative, distributed, and flexible.</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com">Github</a> is where all the coolest open source projects live these days.  Any new software I write that I want to share will go here.    </li>
  <li><a href="http://sass-lang.com">Sass</a> (Syntactically Awesome Style Sheets) is a powerful layer on top of CSS (Cascading Style Sheets) that allows for powerful adaptive layout of HTML pages.</li>
</ul>

<p>While Octopress is in part an excuse to fiddle with new tech, it also feels very comfortable as articles are written in <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown</a>–a very lightweight text-based markup language that I lately find myself using for almost everything.</p>

<h2 id="whats-new">What’s New?</h2>

<p>On the surface, the site shouldn’t look all that different, but beyond the engine being replaced, there are several subtle changes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A real <a href="http://highvariance.net/about.html">About</a> page</li>
  <li>Links up top for the main categories I tend to write about</li>
  <li>A search bar near the top of every page</li>
  <li>Quick links to my recent posts and my favorite posts.</li>
  <li>Much better layout for mobile devices</li>
  <li>Super-fast rendering since Octopress generates the whole site as static HTML which just sits on the server</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="was-it-easy-to-migrate-from-tumblr">Was it Easy to Migrate from Tumblr?</h2>

<p>Two things helped a lot: The Octopress documentation is excellent and I already had all the articles on my local machine in Markdown. The only thing that was tricky was backwards compatibility as I wanted all my old URL’s to work and all my discussions to transfer over.  I used the <a href="https://github.com/tsmango/jekyll_alias_generator">alias-generator</a> plugin and a little elbow grease to make all my Tumblr URL’s redirect to my new URL’s.   </p>

<p>Disqus (the service that keeps track of comments) says they will crawl your new site and use any redirects it provides to update their database.  Unfortunately, while <em>browsers</em> can understand the redirects that the alias-generator creates<sup id="fnref:fn_ag"><a href="#fn:fn_ag" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> just fine, the <em>disqus crawler</em> does not.  So I had to create a csv file that mapped all the old URL’s to the new ones and upload that.</p>

<p>Announcements of new articles on Facebook are now handled by <a href="http://ifttt.com">IFTTT</a>.  It will likely take a little fine-tuning to get these right.</p>

<h2 id="whats-on-the-horizon">What’s on the Horizon?</h2>

<p>The primary emphasis of this site remains the text, but I do want to integrate a little more media–even just a few pictures here and there would be nice. I want the category pages to have their own looks. Beyond that, all I know is that I’ve now got the power to do anything.  Should be fun!</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn_ag">
      <p>Since the site is static, it can’t actually send HTTP
301 permanent redirects. Instead, the alias-generator creates HTML stub files for all the old URL’s with http-equiv meta tags containing the new locations of the URLs.<a href="#fnref:fn_ag" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Blogoversary!]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/22/happy-blogoversary/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/22/happy-blogoversary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first time I saw the World Wide Web, I was hunched over an 8 lb laptop using a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynx_(web_browser)">text based browser</a> and a 56k modem. There wasn’t much to see and it didn’t seem like a big deal. Then about three month’s later <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NCSA_Mosaic">NCSA Mosaic</a> (the first graphical browser) was released and I “got it.” Within a week <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NaviSoft">we</a> redefined our product line and turned a generic set of “network publishing” tools into a web server and a web authoring tool.  Within a year we were purchased by America Online to show that they “got” the web too. My point is that I’ve been deeply embedded in the web for a long time.  </p>

<p>And yet, not including my professional <a href="http://www.econ.yale.edu/~dm529">web-based resume/cv</a>, I didn’t have my own website until exactly a year ago when High Variance was <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/14573237390/first-post">born</a>. I’m not sure why it took me so long to get here, but after a year of any project, I think it’s important to step back and take stock to see if the original goals are being met. I had three:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Create more:</strong>  As expected, the topics have been eclectic ranging from economic policy to kid book reviews to eighties pop music.  The rate of production has been similarly irregular with a burst of activity last January (17 posts) and a summer hiatus.  But the aggregate rate has been about one post per week.  I’m happy with this.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Learn to write better and more comfortably:</strong> Perhaps my biggest surprise is how enjoyable the whole process has been. I don’t get anxious when I write here and my anxiety level when writing professionally has definitely decreased.  When my mind is spinning about a topic, writing about it actually gets me to calm down and figure out what I actually think about it.  As for the quality of the writing, I think I’m getting better, but it’s hard to tell.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Provide entertaining, useful, and/or inspiring content:</strong> My audience will need to be the judge of this, but I know I’ve given at least a few chuckles, a few bits of helpful advice, and even tugged on a few heartstrings.  And in looking back on what I’ve written, much of the content seems to have aged well.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>I suppose I should also say something about my readership. According to Google Analytics, over the past year I’ve have 2,070 unique visitors (5.7 per day) and 4,000 page views (11 per day). Not much, but if you squint at the chart, it does look like traffic is trending slightly up.  There are even a few posts that get regular search engine traffic–<a href="http://highvariance.net/post/18591130112/why-are-zebras-so-mean-and-horses-so-nice">zebras</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/23166850855/pdf-annotation-on-the-ipad-in-2012">pdf annotation on the iPad</a>, and <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/16047390011/mincer-1958">Mincer 1958</a> are the top three.</p>

<p>As I was about to blow out the candles on my birthday cake a few weeks ago I realized something very special: I didn’t have anything new to wish for.  I have a wonderful wife and two lovely children.  We’re all healthy and happy with our jobs and our house.  I just want what I already have.  That’s kind of true of this blog too.  So here’s to another fun and fulfilling year!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Update: Comments on Blogs]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/01/06/update-comments-on-blogs/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/01/06/update-comments-on-blogs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Wouldn’t you know it, the very day after I post <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/15325386814/comments-on-blogs">my piece on comments on
blogs</a>, <a href="http://www.marco.org">Marco Arment</a> and
<a href="http://twitter.com/mattalexand">Matt Alexander</a> actually have a
<a href="http://www.loopinsight.com/2012/01/04/the-e-reader-as-we-know-it-is-doomed/">post</a>,
<a href="http://www.marco.org/2012/01/04/the-ereader-as-we-know-it-is-doomed">back</a>,
and <a href="http://www.one37.net/blog/2012/1/5/doomed.html">forth</a> and
<a href="http://www.marco.org">back</a>.  Just the kind of blog-to-blog
conversation I said never happens.  I guess
<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_Z5-P9v3F8w">Justin Bieber</a> was right.</p>

<p>Incidentally, <a href="http://www.loopinsight.com/">The Loop</a>, where Matt
Alexander posted his original article does allow comments.
His take-away on Twitter seems to be that the conversation
wasn’t all that fruitful:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“It’s blogging interactions like I had
yesterday that prove @mattgemmell right.”  </p>
</blockquote>

<p>So we’ve come full circle.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
