<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[blog | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/categories/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-27T00:20:31-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Blogoversary!]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/12/22/happy-blogoversary/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/12/22/happy-blogoversary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first time I saw the World Wide Web, I was hunched over an 8 lb laptop using a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynx_(web_browser)">text based browser</a> and a 56k modem. There wasn’t much to see and it didn’t seem like a big deal. Then about three month’s later <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NCSA_Mosaic">NCSA Mosaic</a> (the first graphical browser) was released and I “got it.” Within a week <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NaviSoft">we</a> redefined our product line and turned a generic set of “network publishing” tools into a web server and a web authoring tool.  Within a year we were purchased by America Online to show that they “got” the web too. My point is that I’ve been deeply embedded in the web for a long time.  </p>

<p>And yet, not including my professional <a href="http://www.econ.yale.edu/~dm529">web-based resume/cv</a>, I didn’t have my own website until exactly a year ago when High Variance was <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/14573237390/first-post">born</a>. I’m not sure why it took me so long to get here, but after a year of any project, I think it’s important to step back and take stock to see if the original goals are being met. I had three:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Create more:</strong>  As expected, the topics have been eclectic ranging from economic policy to kid book reviews to eighties pop music.  The rate of production has been similarly irregular with a burst of activity last January (17 posts) and a summer hiatus.  But the aggregate rate has been about one post per week.  I’m happy with this.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Learn to write better and more comfortably:</strong> Perhaps my biggest surprise is how enjoyable the whole process has been. I don’t get anxious when I write here and my anxiety level when writing professionally has definitely decreased.  When my mind is spinning about a topic, writing about it actually gets me to calm down and figure out what I actually think about it.  As for the quality of the writing, I think I’m getting better, but it’s hard to tell.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Provide entertaining, useful, and/or inspiring content:</strong> My audience will need to be the judge of this, but I know I’ve given at least a few chuckles, a few bits of helpful advice, and even tugged on a few heartstrings.  And in looking back on what I’ve written, much of the content seems to have aged well.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>I suppose I should also say something about my readership. According to Google Analytics, over the past year I’ve have 2,070 unique visitors (5.7 per day) and 4,000 page views (11 per day). Not much, but if you squint at the chart, it does look like traffic is trending slightly up.  There are even a few posts that get regular search engine traffic–<a href="http://highvariance.net/post/18591130112/why-are-zebras-so-mean-and-horses-so-nice">zebras</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/23166850855/pdf-annotation-on-the-ipad-in-2012">pdf annotation on the iPad</a>, and <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/16047390011/mincer-1958">Mincer 1958</a> are the top three.</p>

<p>As I was about to blow out the candles on my birthday cake a few weeks ago I realized something very special: I didn’t have anything new to wish for.  I have a wonderful wife and two lovely children.  We’re all healthy and happy with our jobs and our house.  I just want what I already have.  That’s kind of true of this blog too.  So here’s to another fun and fulfilling year!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Update: Comments on Blogs]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/01/06/update-comments-on-blogs/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/01/06/update-comments-on-blogs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Wouldn’t you know it, the very day after I post <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/15325386814/comments-on-blogs">my piece on comments on
blogs</a>, <a href="http://www.marco.org">Marco Arment</a> and
<a href="http://twitter.com/mattalexand">Matt Alexander</a> actually have a
<a href="http://www.loopinsight.com/2012/01/04/the-e-reader-as-we-know-it-is-doomed/">post</a>,
<a href="http://www.marco.org/2012/01/04/the-ereader-as-we-know-it-is-doomed">back</a>,
and <a href="http://www.one37.net/blog/2012/1/5/doomed.html">forth</a> and
<a href="http://www.marco.org">back</a>.  Just the kind of blog-to-blog
conversation I said never happens.  I guess
<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_Z5-P9v3F8w">Justin Bieber</a> was right.</p>

<p>Incidentally, <a href="http://www.loopinsight.com/">The Loop</a>, where Matt
Alexander posted his original article does allow comments.
His take-away on Twitter seems to be that the conversation
wasn’t all that fruitful:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“It’s blogging interactions like I had
yesterday that prove @mattgemmell right.”  </p>
</blockquote>

<p>So we’ve come full circle.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comments on Blogs]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/01/04/comments-on-blogs/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/01/04/comments-on-blogs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s become very trendy on tech blogs to not allow comments on articles.
And at least a couple of folks
(<a href="http://mattgemmell.com/2011/11/29/comments-off/">Matt Gemmell</a> and
<a href="http://brooksreview.net/2011/11/gemmell-comments/">Ben Brooks</a> have been
actively trying to convince other bloggers to turn off their comments too.  I
agree that if you’ve got a popular blog (and maybe a thin skin), turning
off comments can make your life easier.  I would even agree that on
popular blogs (and websites more generally) many (most?)  comments don’t
really further the discussion.  In fact, I read most of my blogs
(including Matt’s and Ben’s) inside
<a href="http://reederapp.com/">an RSS reader</a> and so I don’t even see any of
the comments that might or might not be there unless I click through to
the site itself.</p>

<p>But I have three objections to their position on comments.  First, when
you don’t get much traffic (I’m looking at you High Variance) and you
know most of the people reading your blog, it’s really nice to get as
much feedback as possible and I think comments are the best way to do
that.  If someone reading my article has something interesting to say
about it, the comment gives them an audience.  They can always email if
they want to say something privately,</p>

<p>Second, I often like to read what other people have to say about an
article (whether I’ve written it or not), even when I have to wade
through some less than insightful stuff.  Again, the signal-to-noise
ratio is particularly high in the early days of a blog when it’s mostly
friends reading, but even on a big messy site like
<a href="http://www.espn.com">espn.com</a> I think it’s fun to see the popular
reaction to a story.  And yes, I get it that the sample is not even
representative of the readership let alone the general population.  I
think <a href="http://slashdot.org">Slashdot</a> is a terrific example of how
constructive (and entertaining) discussion of an issue can happen on the
web through comments.</p>

<p>Third, there’s this high horse attitude that if people have something to
say about an article, they should just write it up as an article on
their own blog.  And if the original author reads it and wants to
comment back, they will write another article on their blog.  I’m sorry,
but this just doesn’t happen.  I mean, I’ve seen blogs comment on other
blogs, but in almost every case the debate stops there.  And it’s
impossible for someone visiting the original site to see the
conversation at all.  And, believe it or not, there are people with
intelligent things to say that don’t have a blog.</p>

<p>Maybe I’ll change my tune in the future when I’m drowning in haters and
forum-spam, but I have a feeling that’s going to be a while.  Until
then, comments will stay turned on.</p>

<p><a href="http://highvariance.net/post/15402930759/update-comments-on-blogs">UPDATE HERE</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2011/12/21/first-post/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2011/12/21/first-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m sure there are hundreds (if not thousands) of articles on the web
about why one should (or shouldn’t) blog, but I think this is a very
personal question.  For me, the first (but not the only) reason is that
I want to consume less and create more.  Of course, blogging is
something I’ve thought about for a long time and
<a href="http://www.quora.com/Chris-Wake/Hidden-habits-of-ineffective-people">this article</a> was the straw that filled the camel’s stomach.</p>

<p>I also feel the only way to write better and more comfortably is to
write, and blogging is a natural and fun form of writing.  I think it
lends itself to the 15-30 minute chunks that I’m planning to invest.  I
tried Twitter a few months ago as way to scratch my blogging itch and
the experience confirmed for me that tweeting isn’t writing. Even my
tiny attention span is too long for Twitter.</p>

<p>But these two goals could have been accomplished with a personal
journal.  That didn’t feel right either, because I also aspire to
providing entertaining, useful, and inspiring content, though achieving
just one or two of these at a time is probably a more achievable goal.
Having an audience also has perks: It’s a great incentive to not put out
junk.  You don’t even need an audience to get this benefit–just a
potential audience.  I’m also looking forward to hearing occasional
feedback on stuff I write.</p>

<p>So what’s on the horizon?  To be honest, this might be one of those
projects I start that fizzles almost immediately.  I almost named this
Ghost Blog in honor of that possibility.  But instead, I went with a
more optimistically descriptive title because I have eclectic plans for
this space.  And while this is most definitely not a purely professional
blog, I don’t plan to write anything that will prevent me from holding
elected office.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
