<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[kbr | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/kbr/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-19T09:55:20-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Second Time Around]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/16/kid-book-review-second-time-around/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/16/kid-book-review-second-time-around</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the best things about having a second child is getting to do all your favorite little kid things again.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Near the top of that list for me is re-reading our best picture books, and L, at 2.5 years old is just now appreciating the stories as well as the pictures. These five books have been particularly popular over the last few weeks:</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-uncle-elephant.jpg" title="[title “Uncle Elephant”]" ></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Uncle-Elephant-Can-Read-Book/dp/0064441040">Uncle Elephant</a> (written and illustrated by Arnold Lobel) Like all of Arnold Lobel’s books, the illustrations are classic, the stories are clever, and the messages are deep. A boy loses his parents at the beginning and he bonds with his Uncle who takes care of him until his parents come back. Among other things, they walk in the garden, sing songs, and grant wishes to spiders. Uncle Elephant is the grandfather everyone wanted when they were growing up. We’ve also been enjoying Lobel’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s?url=search-alias=aps&amp;field-keywords=lobel%20frog%20and%20toad">Frog and Toad stories</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="">Pup and Hound Catch a Thief</a> (written by Susan Hood, illustrated by Linda Hendry) This criminally under-rated series of books is published by Kids Can Press where it gets lost in a slew of mediocre tales of poorly behaved cats (<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mittens-My-First-Can-Read-ebook/dp/B006JQTQNG">Mittens</a>) and dogs (<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Pizza-Sam-Kids-Can-Read/dp/1553373316">Sam</a>). The rhymes and artwork are cute, and the stories have twists at the end that both L and I can appreciate.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/hv-lyle-walks-the-dogs.jpg" title="[title “Lyle Walks the Dogs”]" ></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lyle-Crocodile-Walks-Dogs/dp/B006Z31NI4">Lyle Walks the Dogs</a> (written by Bernard Waber, illustrated by Paulis Waber) Not to be confused with <a href="">Zack’s Alligator</a> Bridget, Lyle the Crocodile is as sweet as Bridget is sassy. In this counting book Lyle builds a business through competent hard work and positive word of mouth.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Curious-George-Rides-Bike-Rey/dp/B0099R035M">Curious George Rides a Bike</a> (written and illustrated by H.A. Rey) My personal favorite George book when I was a kid, I’m happy to report that L loves it too, even if she does admonish George for not wearing a helmet.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-there-are-cats-in-this-book.jpg" title="[title “There are cats in this book”]" ></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/There-Are-Cats-This-Book/dp/0763639230">There Are Cats in This Book</a> (written and illustrated by Viviane Schwarz) I’m cheating here since we just discovered this book a month ago at the library, but it’s just so good and so perfect for the two year old age group that I had to include it. It follows in the interactive mode of Herve Tullet’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Press-Here-Herve-Tullet/dp/0811879542">Press Here</a> asking the reader to do things (like toss a ball of yarn or look inside a box) and reacting to them. The only potential downside is that the pop-up features are not totally robust, but isn’t that what Scotch tape is for? I just realized there’s a well-reviewed sequel (<a href="http://www.amazon.com/There-Are-Cats-this-Book/dp/0763649546">There are no cats in this book</a>) and can’t wait to check that out too!</li>
</ul>

<hr />
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>One of the worst things about a second child is having to do all your least favorite things again, but I’m a glass-half-full guy. <a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Library Trip Report 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/11/kid-book-review-library-trip-report-3/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/11/kid-book-review-library-trip-report-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We haven’t read much new in the last six months, and while I’d like to take the blame and say it’s because we’ve been busy with work and other commitments, I’m instead going to throw my almost two year old daughter under the bus. While R (who is 4.5 now) is an extreme reader, L has not been very excited about reading. Or about anyone else reading. So instead of all of us enjoying a long cuddle on the couch working through a stack of books, this would quickly devolve into yelling and then R going off to read on her own, L going off to cook in her kitchen, and just me and Curious George sitting there wondering what to do next.  I’m happy to say we have recently turned a corner and L now actually seeks out the social reading experience and we’re back to moving big stacks of books back and forth from the library.</p>

<p>Our last two trips have yielded some keepers, some honorable mentions, and even a couple dishonorable mentions.</p>

<h2 id="keepers">Keepers:</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-cowboy-and-octopus.jpg" title="[title “Cowboy and Octopus”]" ></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Cowboy-Octopus-Jon-Scieszka/dp/0670910589">Cowboy and Octopus</a> (by Jon Scieszka, illustrated by Lane Smith) This collection of 7 very short stories about two good friends has something for everyone. L loves the characters and how the cowboy says “Yee Haw!”. Roxana loves the knock-knock joke and when Octopus gets hammered by Cowboy. I love the adult layer of humor and the style that is a combination of collage and old-school comic book illustration. Win win win.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mrs-Crumps-Cat-Linda-Smith/dp/0060283025">Mrs. Crump’s Cat</a> (by Linda Smith, illustrated by David Roberts) A hungry stray cat shows up at an annoyed Mrs. Crump’s door. But as soon as she describes him as “exquisite” and “golden” you know how the story is going to end. So cute.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Cook---Doodle-Doo-Janet-Stevens/dp/0152056580">Cook-a-Doodle-Doo!</a> (by Janet Stevens and Susan Stevens Crummel, illustrated by Janet Stevens) Rooster is tired of the same old food and decides to bake a cake. Turtle, Iguana, and Pot-bellied Pig “help” and along the way we learn a whole bunch about baking. It’s a great combination of funny, sweet, and truly educational.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Frog-Inside-My-Hat-First/dp/0816731306">A Frog Inside My Hat: A First Book of Poems</a> (compiled by Fay Robinson, illustrated by Cyd Moore) Both girls love the simple fun poems collected in this book and L especially loves flipping through it on her own and looking at the pictures–she calls it “the froggie book”. At these ages reading poetry is completely normal and I hope we can keep it that way.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/At-Supermarket-Anne-Rockwell/dp/080507662X">At the Supermarket</a> (by Anne Rockwell) L’s favorite of the bunch is about a boy who goes to the supermarket with his mom. The big twist is that they buy the ingredients for his birthday cake and make it the next day for the party. The author wrote and illustrated a similar book called <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-SUPERMARKET-Anne-Rockwell/dp/0027775801">Supermarket</a> in 1979 and this “updated” version was published in 2010. My favorite part is that it still seems like a 1980’s period piece: There are no laser scanners. No one uses reusable shopping bags. Everyone’s driving station wagons. I can’t wait until Amazon sends me a copy of the original so I can see what actually got updated.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Yard-Full-Birds-Anne-Rockwell/dp/002777273X">Our Yard is Full of Birds</a> (by Anne Rockwell, illustrated by Lizzy Rockwell) Both girls love looking at birds in our yard and this helps them identify who is who.  Only downside is it makes them want a bird bath even more than they already did. And when your kids are little, bird bath = extra dirty outdoor kid bath.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="honorable-mentions">Honorable mentions:</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-jims-lion.jpg" title="[title “Jim’s Lion”]" ></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Jims-Lion-Russell-Hoban/dp/0763611751">Jim’s Lion</a> (by Russell Hoban, illustrated by Ian Andrew) On the first page, Jim says from his hospital bed that “People who have what I have, mostly they die, don’t they?” It gave me the chills and I immediately realized that neither of my girls are old enough for this story. But what a vivid and hopeful story it is. Wow.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Dawn-Uri-Shulevitz/dp/0374416893">Dawn</a> (by Uri Shulevitz) The art is beautiful and the story is subtle–The sky and the silence are the stars and the grandfather and his son are just supporting characters.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Hero-Cat-Eileen-Spinelli/dp/0761458379">Hero Cat</a> (by Eileen Spinelli, illustrated by Jo Ellen McAllister Stammen) I am a sucker for true stories about animals helping other animals. This one has a mom cat rescuing her babies from a burning building. If you read it with feeling, it’s pretty dramatic.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Sarahs-Little-Ghosts-Thierry-Robberecht/dp/B003NHR7D0">Sarah’s Little Ghosts</a> (by Thierry Robberecht, illustrated by Philippe Goossens) This story is very creative and has a great message. Sarah sneaks into her mom’s jewelry box, breaks her favorite necklace, and then hides the evidence. She feels terribly guilty and everytime she lies about it, another ghost flies out of her mouth. Finally, she can’t take it anymore, comes clean, and feels a lot better. R and I read this one very carefully, and I think she even understood what was going on.  Score one for the good guys!</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="dishonorable-mentions">Dishonorable mentions:</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-big-elephant.jpg" title="[title “The Big Elephant in the Room”]" ></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Big-Elephant-Room-Lane-Smith/dp/1423116674">The Big Elephant in the Room</a> (by Lane Smith) This story revolves around two donkeys.  One says they need to talk about the “big elephant in the room” and the other is sure he is asking about the myriad of terrible things he’s been doing and confesses to all of them. These include eating all the ice cream, breaking the computer, stealing a video game, and even telling a mutual friend about a pee accident. My girls do not need <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2011/12/30/bad-behavior/">books giving them more ideas for bad behavior</a>–they’ve got that covered already.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Ladybug-Girl-Beach-Jacky-Davis/dp/0803734166">Ladybug Girl at the Beach</a> (by David Soman and Jacky Davis) I like Ladybug Girl, R loves Ladybug Girl, and we own several Ladybug Girl books. She’s curious, creative, and adventurous. Our best guess is that she and R are both about the same age (between 4 and 5) Her parents are mostly absent, and that’s OK when the story takes place in the backyard or at the playground. At the beach, however, very bad things can happen when parents aren’t around. Like kids drowning bad. In this book Lulu wanders all around the beach by herself and almost gets pulled out to sea without anyone even noticing. As far as I can tell, the message is that you shouldn’t be afraid of sneaking off by yourself to play in the waves when you’re four years old. My four year old already thinks she can swim–I’d rather not encourage that delusion.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Halloween Edition]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/11/16/kid-book-review-halloween/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/11/16/kid-book-review-halloween</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About a week before Halloween, R and I raided the library’s selection of
Halloween-appropriate picture books.  I’ve felt
<a href="http://highvariance.net/post/21370720836/kid-book-review-library-trip-report-2">guilty before</a>
about skimming the cream but hopefully sharing what we learned
will balance out the karma.  Before I start, I know what you’re
thinking: “It’s the middle of November!  Who cares about Halloween?  How about sharing something useful
like the top 10 Thanksgiving picture books?”  Don’t worry, that’ll be
here before Christmas.  In the meantime, bookmark this page and put a
note on your calendar to check back on October 15, 2013 and then head to
your local library.  On with the show!</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Franklins-Halloween-Paulette-Bourgeois/dp/0590693301">Franklin’s Halloween</a>
(by Paulette Bourgeois, illustrated by Brenda Clark) Franklin is one
of my favorite recurring lovable-yet-flawed characters.  He’s just a
regular kid (turtle) who usually gets in some sort of minor trouble
and learns from his mistakes.  He’s kind of
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Franklin-Messy-Paulette-Bourgeois/dp/0590486861">messy</a>,
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Franklin-Plays-Game-Paulette-Bourgeois/dp/0590226312">not very athletic</a>,
and has even been known to <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Franklin-Fibs-Paulette-Bourgeois/dp/0590446479">tell a fib or two</a>.  In this book, he just
has fun making his own Halloween costume and going to a party.
There’s a great spooky twist at the end and he’s even generous to a
sick friend.  Hurray for Franklin!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Brooms-Are-Flying-Michael-Rex/dp/0312380151">Brooms Are for Flying</a> (by Michael Rex) and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Humbug-Witch-Lorna-Balian/dp/159572009X">Humbug Witch</a> (by
Lorna Bailin) Spoiler Alert!  These two books are simple and cute.
One is about a witch who turns out to be a girl at the end and the
other is about a girl who turns out to be a witch at the end!  </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/WITCH-WHO-LIVES-DOWN-HALL/dp/B000J4MU7I">The Witch Who Lives Down the Hall</a> (by Donna Guthrie, illustrated
by Amy Schwartz) The mostly black and white illustrations (with
touches of orange) are a great complement to a story about a boy who
lives down the hall from a “strange” lady and her black cat.  He’s
convinced she’s a witch.  Clever and funny to both kids and adults.
Reminded me a lot of <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/18359444436/kid-book-review-monster-edition">Mrs. Muffly’s Monster</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Terrible-Halloween-Night-James-Stevenson/dp/0688099327">That Terrible Halloween Night</a>
  (by James Stevenson) This is about as scary as you can get and still
  be appropriate for a three year-old. I loved it and R is still talking
  about it.  Last night she told me our basement floor was covered with
  frogs!  I liked the pen and pastel comic book layout too.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Cake-Girl-David-Lucas/dp/B003NHR9OM">Cake Girl</a> (by David Lucas) <a href="http://www.amazon.com/David-Lucas/e/B001HMTVBY">David Lucas</a> is so good–all his books
have such sweet characters, surreal stories, and pretty
illustrations.  This one is about a witch who learns about friendship.</p>
  </li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Library Trip Report 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/04/28/kid-book-review-library-trip-report-2/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/04/28/kid-book-review-library-trip-report-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The main goal of our biweekly trip to the New Haven Free Public Library is to
pick 20 or so great picture books.  I’m looking for books with beautiful
art, lovable (or at least memorable) characters, an original story, and
a positive message.  These books are rare and they’re difficult to
identify by a book spine, a book cover, or even a quick perusal.  And I
don’t have time for much more than that.</p>

<p>So the failure rate is high, but in this case failing isn’t all that bad
an outcome.  In fact, most books that come home succeed on at least one
dimension.  Sometimes the books are so spectacularly awful or
inappropriate that they stretch your brain.  And often R’s favorite
books are not my favorites.  The bottom line is that we both get a fair
amount out of reading the mediocre bulk of our haul, even when most get
returned never to be read again.</p>

<p>Our latest keepers:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Umbrella-Queen-Shirin-Bridges/dp/0060750405">The Umbrella Queen</a> (by Shirin Yim Bridges, illustrated by Taeeun
  Yoo) I have a special place in my heart for atypical stories
  that take place in other countries.  And even better, I
  like stories about kids who are true to themselves.  This book takes
  place in Thailand and follows a girl whose inner artist cannot
  be squashed.  It reminds me a lot of
  <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Empty-Pot-Demi/dp/0805082271">The Empty Pot</a>(by
  Demi) and I Ioved
  that too.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Library-Lion-Michelle-Knudsen/dp/076363784X">Library Lion</a> (by Michelle Knudsen, illustrated by Kevin Hawkes) The
  lesson here is fantastic: Rules are good, but there are always
  extenuating circumstances when they should be broken.  The premise is
  absurd (a friendly helpful lion hangs out at the library) but not
  totally drug-addled (see
  <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Hogula-Dread-Night-Jean-Gralley/dp/0805071644/">Hogula: the Dread Pig of the Night</a> (by
  Jean Gralley) for an
  example of the latter).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Night-Worker-Kate-Banks/dp/0374400008">The Night Worker</a> (by Kate Banks, illustrated by Georg Hallensleben)
A respectful portrayal of a Latino engineer who takes a son to the job
site one night.  Lots of construction equipment and beautiful almost
Gauguin-style paintings.  What’s not to love?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Maxs-Dragon-Kate-Banks/dp/B003IWYJIG">Max’s Dragon</a>by Kate Banks, illustrated by Boris Kulikov) This
story is about two (older?) brothers playing croquet and their quirky
(younger?) brother who has a big imagination and loves rhymes.
Super-cute and super-original and the art is good though not my
favorite style.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Polar-Bear-Easy---Read-Puffin/dp/0140386920">A Polar Bear Can Swim</a> (by Harriet Ziefert, illustrated by Emily
Bolam) This book is designed for kids who are learning to read on
their own and who are curious about animals and science.  That’s a
perfect match for R.  It’s filled with fun facts (“A cow can drink 75
gallons of water in a day!”) and simple artwork.  I’m excited to check out
other members of the Viking Science Easy-to-Read series.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Balloons-Dee-Lillegard/dp/0525459405">Balloons Balloons Balloons</a> (by Dee Lillegard, illustrated by
Bernadette Pons) I admit I find this book a little brain-numbing, but
R is going to love any book that has a rabbit in a hot air balloon
dumping huge numbers of multicolored balloons on a whole town.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Secret-River-Marjorie-Kinnan-Rawlings/dp/1416911790">The Secret River</a> (by Marjorie Kinnan Rawlings, illustrated by Leo
and Diane Dillon) This book is special.  It was written in 1947 by the
author of
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Yearling-Aladdin-Classics-Marjorie-Rawlings/dp/0689846231">The Yearling</a>
and it follows a poor black girl who lives in the rural South in the
early part of the 20th century.  I don’t have a lot of experience with
this environment, but it sure seems real to me.  The art is great and
the story is magical in a way that works for adults and children.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Honorable mentions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Ginger-Bear-Mini-Grey/dp/0375842535">Ginger Bear</a> (by Mini Grey) R and I both like the part where Horace
smears cookie dough all over the toilet seat, but it goes downhill
from there.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Really-Rabbits-Virginia-L-Kroll/dp/157091897X">Really Rabbits</a> (by Virginia Kroll, illustrated by Philomena
O’Neill) Cute story about two pet rabbits who do household chores in
the middle of the night.  We could use these guys in our house.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Wonder-Woman-Classic-Read-Book/dp/0061885177">Wonder Woman: I am Wonder Woman</a> (by Eric K. Stein, illustrated by
Rick Farley) An adaptation of a comic book?  Really? Yes!  Wonder Woman is a
positive role model for girls and R loves her tiara and bracelets.
And it doesn’t hurt that Dad had a thing for
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynda_Carter#Wonder_Woman">Linda Carter</a>
when he was in high school.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Punk-Farm-Tour-Jarrett-Krosoczka/dp/0375833439">Punk Farm On Tour</a> (by Jarrett J. Krosoczka) It’s really quite good,
but if you already have <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Punk-Farm-Jarrett-J-Krosoczka/dp/0440417937">Punk Farm</a> you’re not getting a whole lot
more here.  If you don’t have <em>Punk Farm</em> yet, you need to run out and
get it right away!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Tricycle-Elisa-Amado/dp/0888996144">Tricycle</a> (by Elisa Amado, illustrated by Alfonso Ruano) A girl from
a wealthy family in Guatemala is friends with three poor kids next
door.  She sees them steal her tricycle but doesn’t say anything to
her parents because she knows she shouldn’t have left it in the bushes
and she already has a lot more stuff than they have.  I love the complex
emotions and the interplay of personal relationships and the gulf
between rich and poor that exists pretty much everywhere but is
especially stark in Latin America.  All of this is lost on R, but
she’s 3.  I’m not so sure she’ll get it at 5 either, but I commend the
authors for trying!</p>
  </li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Library Trip Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/13/kid-book-review-library-trip-report/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/13/kid-book-review-library-trip-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every couple weeks we go to the library after school.  Mostly we run
around and raise a ruckus because that’s what three-year-olds and
almost-one-year-olds do.  But we also gather up 15-20 new books to
peruse at home.  I’ve tried a lot of strategies for selecting them:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Get all the books by a few authors we like.  This sometimes nets us
some surprises (Janell Cannon’s
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Trupp-Fuzzhead-Tale-Janell-Cannon/dp/0152001301">Trupp</a>
is about a large earless cat who hangs out with the homeless) and some
stinkers (Don Freeman’s
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mop-Top-Don-Freeman/dp/1595190600">Moptop</a> is
about a kid who “needs” a haircut) but the main problem is we don’t
know enough good authors.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Quickly make a random selection from a new part of the picture book
stacks.  More misses than hits but not so bad.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Take most of the books the librarians have pulled out for display on
the tops of the shelves.  This works surprisingly well as the
librarians have better than random taste.  But I feel slightly
guilty—it’s like taking the clothes off the mannequins in a shop
window.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>After reading these books at home (some several times) there are
always a few keepers that we have to order on Amazon.  Here are the
keepers from our most recent trip:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Dahlia-Boston-Globe-Horn-Honors-Awards/dp/0374316783">Dahlia</a>
(by Barbara McClintock): I absolutely love everything about this book–Old
fashioned beautifully detailed line drawings and a story about a
tom-boy who gets a lacy doll as a gift from an aunt.  Great fun and
great message.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Cats-Night-Paula-Wiseman-Books/dp/1416940057">Cat’s Night Out</a>
(by Caroline Stutson, illustrated by J. Klassen): A counting (by twos) book with tons of cute
dancing cats–the wife and kid love it though I prefer a bit more story.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Tinka-Rainy-Dohaney/dp/0689852614">Tinka</a> (by
  Rainy Dohaney): This story about a cupcake-sized sheep is only OK
  and the washed out art is nothing special.  But it’s still 4.5/5
  stars because it’s so quirky and R thinks it’s hilarious when the
  crow gets a worm wrapped around his head.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Birthday-Presents-Rabbit-Hedgehog/dp/1842700359">The Birthday Presents</a>
(by Paul Stewart and Chris Ridell): Super-cute story about a rabbit and a
hedgehog with classic-looking pictures.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>There were also a few books that weren’t keepers but merit mentions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Root-Beer-Banana-Sarah-Sullivan/dp/0763617482">Root Beer and Banana</a>
(by Sarah Sullivan, illustrated by Greg Shed) is about a middle-class country girl and a
poor country girl who become friends over ice pops.  The art is
old-fashioned and I love how the poor girl is treated like a regular
person and not a sad museum exhibit.  But the stereotypes are a little
heavy handed–she’s kind of dirty with ratty clothes, she has no
nearby family, and she only has money she found in the street.  And
she can’t read so good.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Priscilla-Pink-Planet-Nathaniel-Hobbie/dp/0316113492">Priscilla and the Pink Planet</a>
  (by Nathaniel Hobbie, illustrated by Jocelyn Hobbie)  has rhymes that are as close to
  Seuss as I’ve every read.  And the art is cute and so is the story.
  I’m not sure why I don’t like this book more.  Maybe it’s because
  the main character reminds me too much of Betty Boop.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Bracelet-Yoshiko-Uchida/dp/069811390X">The Bracelet</a>
(by Yoshiko Uchida): A picture book about the Japanese-American internment
during WW II.  Definitely not appropriate for a three year old.  A
little too much barbed wire.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Fly-Free-Roseanne-Thong/dp/1590785509">Fly Free!</a>
(by Roseanne Thong): I want to like this book.  It’s about Buddhist temples
in Vietnam and is all about doing nice things for other people.  The art is pretty.
But I really didn’t like that the temples were caging sparrows so that
people could pay them money to release them (and get good karma).  Can
we just not cage the birds to begin with please?</p>
  </li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
