<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[education | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/education/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-06T01:40:06-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lectures 2.0: Using online materials to improve off-line courses]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/29/lectures-2.0/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/29/lectures-2.0</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The big lecture is an institution in institutions of higher learning. The professor stands at the front of a hall full of students and talks. Sometimes he or she uses slides and sometimes he or she writes on a board.  And sometimes, he or she is informative and engaging, but it’s almost always a pretty one way affair with occasional questions posed to the class.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>  The experience for students is a lot like watching a good documentary.  And that’s the best case scenario. The vast majority of the time, students sit back and absorb the flow or just check out. They don’t get <em>their</em> questions answered or engage constructively with the material. The average professor talks at their students for an hour and a half twice a week and it’s more like a late night infomercial than a documentary. </p>

<p>Now let’s think about seminars. Students read articles and book chapters ahead of time and then gather in a small classroom to discuss the material with the professor and each other. Often there are in-class exercises or even smaller group activities. In general, students report they get more out of these classes. </p>

<p>So why aren’t all classes structured as seminars? First of all, some material (especially introductory material) is more easily presented visually than textually–that’s one reason why <a href="http://www.khanacademy.org">Kahn Academy</a> is so successful. Seeing someone work through a problem is, for many students, a lot clearer than reading about it in a book. Lecturing allows for this kind of presentation and I believe it complements book learning. The second reason is purely economic: Seminars are expensive. If you have 33-34 students per seminar and you want to teach 100 students, you need three professors.  That’s triple what you’d need to teach a 100 person lecture.</p>

<p>Wouldn’t it be great if we could take the best qualities of the lecture and the seminar and combine them in an economically feasible way?  We can. </p>

<p>I was asked recently why I am excited to teach an online class this summer. Expanding the reach of my teaching was one reason, but it also gives me the opportunity to put together high quality online materials. This won’t simply be recordings of my hour and half lectures. Instead, it will be 3-5m chunks of <a href="https://www.udacity.com">Udacity</a>-style video interspersed with questions to make sure students are following along. The video will mostly be me drawing on slides, working through problems, and presenting new concepts.</p>

<p>Here’s my vision: The 100 person class is divided into three separate groups of students. Each week, all students work their way through about 2 hours worth of online interactive video. At the end of the week, I meet with each group for an hour. I answer questions that they still have. I tie the “timeless” online material to current events. I have them work on problems in smaller groups and float between groups helping them as needed. </p>

<p>I think the experience will be clearly better for students, but what about faculty and the administration? This won’t happen unless it’s a Pareto improvement.  That is, none of the parties involved can be worse off. </p>

<p>Once the materials are in place, they can be re-used by different professors–this radically reduces the amount of prep time. The class itself should be a lot more fun to teach since the professor  can actually have conversations with students and get direct feedback on how well the class is going. If the online materials are high quality (and they should be), the professor doesn’t have to be fantastic to teach an excellent class. Most faculty are not naturally great lecturers, but the small classes give them an opportunity to share their raw intelligence and experience with the material–it’s a much better skill match.</p>

<p>The administration is happy because the same 100 students are getting higher quality education for the same cost.  In fact, far more students get to benefit from close contact with big name professors–that makes the institution look good.</p>

<p>What I’m describing is not a totally new idea–It’s a straight-forward application of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flip_teaching">flipping the classroom</a>. And it’s an idea that gets better and better every day as the education world learns  more about what works online and more high quality materials are made publicly available.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Some professors will use <a href="http://www.engaging-technologies.com/teaching-with-clickers.html">clickers</a> to get real-time multiple choice feedback from his or her audience.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Who should own course materials?]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/13/course-materials/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/13/course-materials</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every spring university departments match their faculty to the courses that will be taught the next year.  Often, professors are assigned to courses they’ve never taught before.  This is almost always the case for new assistant professors who haven’t really taught anything before.  In the best case scenario, whoever taught the class the last time around has lunch with the new instructor, passes on a few pearls of wisdom, and hands over a subset of their course materials.  I’ve personally benefited immensely from this generosity since it’s much easier to prepare a course when starting with a stack of slides, problem sets, and old exams. It’s also quite common to have to start from scratch.  But there is a better way.</p>

<p>First of all, a course is a lot more than slides, exams, and problem sets. Instructors say a lot of stuff that’s not on the slides–they do board work, ask students questions, and use their slides as a springboard for what they actually teach.  What the instructor says sometimes lives only in the instructor’s brain but often there exists a rough set of hand-written or quickly typed set of notes for each lecture. Some instructors will write up another set of notes about what worked and what didn’t after each class–I call these my post-mortem notes.  And then some instructors include various other fancy things in their classes like videos, online surveys and in-class exercises.</p>

<p>When I was in college, all fraternities kept files of class exams.  Every time a brother took a test, it went into a folder which could be used as a resource for future brothers. Surely departments can get at least this organized.  I propose that they do even better and serve as a clearing house for the materials for  at least their core courses and maybe all of their courses. My dream scenario is that <strong>when a professor has to teach a new course they get access to a department-managed folder that has all the materials from previous years.</strong></p>

<p>There are several potential issues here, but I believe they are all small relative to the potentially huge improvements in course quality and reductions in required teaching prep.</p>

<p><em>How can this be fair to the first professor who prepares a course?</em> Yes, the first person does more work. The department should give them more credit–perhaps a course and a half is fair. Frankly, these professors should get extra credit no matter who owns the course materials.</p>

<p><em>Shouldn’t courses be tailored to individual professors?</em> Yes, this is true too. That’s why the department shouldn’t just keep the previous year’s materials. Ideally, when someone takes over a course, they could peruse several years and find the best starting point for them.  And when they customize those materials, they are providing another potential starting point for the next instructor.</p>

<p><em>Prepping a course is a lot of work–the instructor should own that!</em> I agree here too and all I’m arguing is that the department should share ownership. Instructors should certainly be able to take with them whatever they’ve used to teach the course when/if they leave the university</p>

<p>Professors don’t generally make their materials public even to their departments because they don’t reap much (if any) personal benefit.  The sharing I’m talking about costs a small amount but yields big <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Positive_externality#Positive">positive external</a> benefits. Since the market isn’t solving this problem by itself, I think it only makes sense that economics departments should solve it by explicitly internalizing the externality.  That’s exactly what enforcing departmental ownership would do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Homage to Chris Welty]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/08/an-homage-to-chris-welty/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/08/an-homage-to-chris-welty</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>According to the Internet, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Welty">Chris Welty</a> is now a research scientist at IBM’s TJ Watson Research Center in upstate New York.  He works on knowledge representation and the semantic web and was one of the developers behind <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Watson_(computer)">Watson</a>, the computer program that kicked ass on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeopardy!">Jeopardy!</a>  He also taught Intro to Artificial Intelligence at <a href="http://www.rpi.edu">Rensselaer</a> in the late 1980’s. As far as I know, he is alive and well. But life comes and goes and I really like the idea of writing this  while he is still around to read it. You don’t always get <a href="http://www.marco.org/2013/01/05/dr-bob-cupper">that chance</a>. </p>

<p>I showed up at Rensselaer in 1986 extremely excited to learn how to turn computers into people.  I grew up on science fiction like Asimov’s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I,_Robot">I Robot</a> and was certain we were on the threshold of true software-based intelligent beings.  I knew the average person wasn’t that smart–how hard could it possibly be to write code that could simulate their basic skills?<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> </p>

<p>In the spring of my sophomore year I took Professor Welty’s Intro to AI class and it was everything I could have hoped for. Professor Welty was not quite as young as I was, but he was certainly as excited as any of us about the box full toys we got to play with.  Mini-max algorithms, backward-chaining, forward chaining, Lisp, semantic networks–I could go on and on. I put serious work into that class, but it was also a serious amount of fun.  This was the only class in college that actually inspired me to work all night on projects.</p>

<p>You might think that with subject matter this good, anyone could have taught a great class, but you’d be wrong.  Now that I spend big chunks of my own time standing in the front of the classroom, I realize all the work he put in and the skills he had.  The problem sets were engaging. The in-class explanations of concepts were clear and polished and yet the classes were very conversational.  In Professor Welty’s class everyone felt comfortable raising their hand.</p>

<p>I don’t do AI anymore, but I use what I learned in that class every day: Hold yourself to a high standard.  Be present. Share. Do what you love. Have fun.  Thanks Professor Welty!</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>It turns out to be very hard, but it also took me many more years to figure that out.  <a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Few Thoughts on MOOC's]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/08/thoughts-on-moocs/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/08/thoughts-on-moocs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mooc">MOOC</a> is an acroynm for Massive Open Online Course.  It’s a trendy name
for packing up a course’s content (video lectures, problem sets, exams,
a mechanism for peer interactions, etc.) and making it available to a large
number of students over the internet without requiring significant live instructor input.
It’s that last part that allows the system to scale and separates the
idea from simple distance learning or a traditional online course.</p>

<p>The most exciting thing about MOOC’s is the expansion in availability of
university-level content.  At least three groups of top-tier
universities in the US (<a href="http://www.edx.org">edX</a>, <a href="http://www.coursera.org">Coursera</a>, and <a href="http://www.udacity.org">Udacity</a>) are
actively producing these kinds of online courses and making them
available for free to anyone.  It means that kids and
adults from rural China to urban Brazil can watch and learn from the
some of the best professors in the world and interact with each other
about the material.</p>

<p>A second exciting thing about MOOC’s is that they promise to be a major
disruptive innovation for existing institutions of higher education.
Think about what happens in an average traditional college course.  The
professor stands up and gives a lecture taking occasional questions from
the class. He/she assigns reading and homework and gives exams. They are
somewhat available to answer questions in office hours or by email. A
MOOC isn’t better on every dimension, but I believe they’ve recently crossed a
line and the overall experience is actually better than the average
college course.  </p>

<p>As students become aware of MOOC’s, I think a few will decide to forego
college and instead learn what they want to learn more cheaply and on
their own schedule.  Most students (and their future employers) however
will want a credential (degree) that “proves” they have mastered a set
of material.  It’s only a matter of time before the big three (or
someone new) comes along and is able to provide this.  Online degrees
exist today and I predict they will become more and more
mainstream.<sup id="fnref:fn_dating"><a href="#fn:fn_dating" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>  That said, the current college experience is more than
courses and I think the market for that won’t be going away soon.  </p>

<p>Students will also start demanding more of classes at existing
universities and attending colleges that raise their game and start
providing higher quality in-class experiences.  That means colleges will
have to leverage what they have that the MOOC’s will never have: live
instructors/experts that are able to spend time either one-on-one or in
small groups with students answering questions and having real time
conversations. This is possible online, but it doesn’t scale up to
massive numbers of students per instructor.  Some faculty will start
building on MOOC content–that is, they will replace their own lectures
with those of the MOOC’s and add their own interactivity.  And I’m happy
to say that the he big live lecture will go the way of the horse and
buggy–average professors just won’t be able to compete with the top
professors in the world and their video lectures.</p>

<p>I was going to title this post “The Revolution’s Coming” but the
revolution is already here.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn_dating">
      <p>This is exactly what happened with online dating over
thelast 10 years.<a href="#fnref:fn_dating" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Social Science "Labs"]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/04/06/social-science-labs/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/04/06/social-science-labs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When most people think of labs, they imagine scientists in white coats
staring into microscopes, carrying around beakers of bubbling chemicals, 
and holding test tubes over Bunsen burners.  In social science, the
reality is much more mundane.  It’s usually just a room full of
computers with software that may or may not be useful and may or may not
be up to date.  Even less compelling are the labs associated with
statistical methods classes.  The last couple years my own classes have
been the worst case scenario–I just get up and lecture about how my
students should use some particular piece of software to apply the
methods we’ve been learning in the “lecture” part of the class.  It
doesn’t have to be this way.</p>

<p>Over the next few months I will have the opportunity to teach two new
methods classes and completely re-invent how I incorporate labs.  I had
lunch with <a href="http://publichealth.yale.edu/cde/people/mayur_desai.profile">Mayur Desai</a> the other day and I think he does a great job
with labs in his classes and he’s inspired most (but not all) of the
ideas here.  This is what I’m thinking:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>No lectures.  None.  Students enter the lab and get their assignment
    and spend the rest of the class trying to complete it.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Each assignment starts with a data set (preferably real) and a
    blank screen–that is, I don’t give them any code.  Their job is to
    answer a substantive question by applying methods we’ve covered
    recently to the data.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Students work in pairs and take turns driving.  I think this keeps
    students focused and they can teach each other.  It also means only
    half the class has to have laptops if I want to implement a lab in a
    regular classroom.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I’m around to answer questions.  In this way, it’s very different
    from a problem set where getting stuck on something dumb for hours
    at a time is a common occurrence.  Struggling with problem is good
    for learning, but banging your head against a wall isn’t an
    efficient use of time.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The end product should be similar to results they might find
  in a published paper.  Sometimes I’ll provide an empty table they must
  fill in and other times they will produce their own tables of results
  from scratch.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>There should be opportunities for quicker/more advanced students to
  do more.  One size does not fit all.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>While it’s possible to use any statistical analysis tool in a lab
successfully, I do think some packages are better than others.  Most
students already know Microsoft Excel and doing basic analyses (even
regression) using it is easy, but you really hit a wall when you want to
do anything even a little sophisticated.  SAS is powerful, but there is
a steep learning curve.  My plan is to use Stata.  You can browse your
data in a spreadsheet style interface.  You can play with commands
through the menus and when you choose one, it shows you the command-line
equivalent.  You can work interactively at the command-line or build
programs (using those same commands) in an editor.  And the
documentation is excellent and available online.</p>

<p>I’ll let you know how it goes!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
