<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[education | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/education/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-04T23:19:33-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Economics and Data Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/09/economics-and-data-analysis/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/09/economics-and-data-analysis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We live in a world where more and more people and organizations make <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Super-Crunchers-Why-Thinking-By-Numbers-Smart/dp/0553384732">decisions based on data</a>. These include business decisions, policy-making decisions, and even many personal decisions. <a href="http://www.quora.com/Google/What-do-economists-do-at-Google-their-responsibilities-as-Googles-employees">Google employs hundreds of quantitative analysts</a> to analyze auctions, forecast revenue, predict customer needs, and surely lots of other things we don’t know about. A good friend of mine just spent the last month carefully analyzing student loan data for the <a href="http://www.federalreserve.gov">Federal Reserve</a>. I even just read about a guy who <a href="http://www.wired.com/wiredscience/2014/01/how-to-hack-okcupid/all/">scraped dating data from OK Cupid</a> to find himself a wife.</p>

<p>Business and the government often look to economists to do this kind of data analysis for two main reasons. First, economists have been using data to answer questions about optimal behavior for a long time and have developed a set of statistical methods tuned for these problems that we call <em>econometrics</em>. These tools are particularly applicable to the non-experimental (aka “observational”) data that is piling up all around us. The second reason is that economists are good at thinking mathematically about human behavior and markets–two concepts at the heart of many important questions. </p>

<p>I am constantly telling my undergraduate students to take as many classes on econometrics, statistics, and/or data analysis as they can.  Only one semester of statistics/econometrics is required to get a bachelor’s degree in economics at Yale, and this introductory course covers the basics of probability, statistical inference, and linear regression.  The payoff to taking the second class is huge–that’s where students actually gain proficiency with elementary methods and build up to important methods like instrumental variables and difference-in-differences that can separate causation from correlation.</p>

<p>I recently did an informal survey of ten top-tier economics departments and learned that seven of the ten now require two semesters (or quarters) of statistics and/or econometrics.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> I will be shocked if in five years it’s not at least nine out of ten. Even now, many advanced applied elective courses teach statistical methods so that students can understand (and contribute to) the research they read.</p>

<p>At the beginning of my last semester in college I had a conversation with a fellow senior that has really stuck with me. He went on and on about how excited he was to be taking Econ 101. At least part of his logic was that he didn’t want to graduate without knowing something about the economy. I had not taken any economics up to this point and had no idea what he was talking about. I didn’t get it at all. Now I do. Economics training gives people tools for understanding how the world works. That training needs to keep up with our increasingly data-driven world.</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes:</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Harvard, MIT, Berkeley, Brown, Penn, and Duke require their economics majors to take two semesters of econometrics and/or statistics. Stanford requires two quarters. Yale, Amherst, and Princeton require one semester. Yale also offers an Econ/Math degree that requires two semesters of econometrics.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't Throw Them to the Wolves]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/04/thrown-to-the-wolves/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/04/thrown-to-the-wolves</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-wolfpack.jpeg"></p>

<p>I recently heard <a href="http://bbs.yale.edu/people/michael_koelle-1.profile">Michael Koelle</a> (Associate Professor of Molecular Biophysics and Biochemistry at Yale) give a very interesting <a href="http://teaching.yale.edu/programs/faculty/award-winning-teachers-teaching-lunchtime-colloquia">presentation on teaching</a>. He led by saying he wasn’t going to talk about anything trendy like MOOC’s or flipping the classroom or project-based learning, but would instead focus on how how he teaches traditional big lecture courses. He proceeded to tell us about the most progressive lecture courses I’ve ever heard of. Among other things, he never lectures for more than 15 minutes at a time and peppers his classes with interactivity and small group exercises. While his whole talk was inspiring and full of concrete advice and ideas, I want to write today about something he brought up almost in passing.</p>

<p>Professor Koehlle’s department introduces junior faculty to teaching big lectures by having them co-teach with someone senior the first few times. The junior sees first-hand what goes into a good lecture, learns the nuts and bolts with a safety net, and has someone right there who can answer questions and critique individual classes. What a great model! </p>

<p>The far more common practice is to throw junior faculty to the wolves in a big course. If you happen to be a natural or are willing to invest far more than makes sense for someone hoping to get tenure, it might result in a decent class. More often than not, it’s a train wreck. It occurs to me that while many departments can’t afford to have two faculty teaching their big classes, there are other (cheaper) ways to mentor juniors:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Have experienced senior faculty pay attention to juniors while they are teaching a challenging class for the first time. That means observing lectures, having lunch meetings about how things are going, and encouraging juniors to ask questions about teaching.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When a junior takes over an existing class, give them as much of the previous instructor’s materials as possible. Lecture slides are a start, but notes, problem sets and old exams are also helpful. If the department has <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/13/course-materials/">ownership of the materials</a>, this is easy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Let juniors get their first teaching experience in a high-level class. It sounds weird to people outside academia, but the more advanced classes are much easier to teach. The students in these classes are more bought into the discipline’s norms, and the material is closer to what the instructor works on every day while doing their research. Introductory classes need to be far more polished and have a much more diverse group of students. I love diversity but it’s a lot harder to teach. Electives are easiest of all because every student in the class wants to be there.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Exploit university resources outside the department for helping teachers. At Yale, the <a href="http://teaching.yale.edu">Yale Teaching Center</a> will help instructors learn from their evaluations, review syllabi, and even do classroom observation. Letting faculty know about these services is a nice first step, but my experience is that only the above average teachers take advantage of them. It should be mandatory for all juniors (and probably seniors too).</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Junior faculty in top departments are evaluated for promotion based on their research productivity. Mentoring is a way to improve their teaching without having to take time away from their research. In fact, there are techniques many juniors don’t know that will <em>save</em> them time spent teaching. Starting with high-quality course materials means less time preparing class. Clearer lectures mean fewer confused students visiting during office hours. A better match between lecture content and exam content means fewer irate student emails.</p>

<p>If a department is serious about upgrading the quality of its undergraduate instruction, doing a better job of mentoring junior faculty is low hanging fruit. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Online tech in an in-person seminar: An experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/10/online-tech-in-an-in-person-seminar/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/10/online-tech-in-an-in-person-seminar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve written about <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/05/20/seminars/">how I like to run seminar classes</a> before and you may have noticed that my approach is decidedly low tech. My students read the week’s articles before class and fill out a “worksheet” for each one. Before this semester, the most important question on the worksheet was “What didn’t you understand?” I would look over their answers to identify weak spots that we would  cover in class.</p>

<p>This semester I tried something new: I took “What didn’t you understand?” off the worksheet and asked my students to post questions they had about the reading on a <a href="http://piazza.com">Piazza</a> online discussion forum. If two (or more) students have the same question, only the first has to post it–the others could just mark it as a “good question.” They could also answer each other’s questions and I could “approve” answers or provide my own. I had high hopes for the new system. I thought it would be easier for the students, and would make it easier for me to see what the hot button issues were and even provide some feedback before class. </p>

<p>It didn’t work very well. Even with a fair amount of cajoling during the semester, I would only get 4-5 students (of 24) participating in the forum each week. Based on feedback during the last class, it seems there were three primary reasons. First, it wasn’t clear to many of them that they could post their questions anonymously and they didn’t want to embarrass themselves in front of their fellow students by posting potentially “dumb” questions. Second, several students felt they were done with the assignment after they filled out their worksheets. They didn’t want to take the time to go to the Piazza web site for more work. Third, they didn’t like posting questions that weren’t going to get answered on the forum.</p>

<p>I’m not ready to give up on the idea, but I’m also not sure what to do differently next semester. I can try more cajoling on the first day of class and I can let everyone know that they can post anonymously. I can also commit to answering questions before class. The worksheets and questions are due on Monday night, so that gives me plenty of time before Wednesday’s class to provide at least basic answers. I’m still not sure this will be enough to get mass participation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Few More Thoughts on Grade Inflation]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/12/a-few-more-thoughts-on-grade-inflation/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/12/a-few-more-thoughts-on-grade-inflation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I gave three reasons why <a href="/blog/2013/11/07/a-few-thoughts-on-grade-inflation">Yale shouldn’t worry so much about grade inflation</a>:</p>

<ol>
  <li>There is still enough room at the top of the grade distribution to separate students into Excellent (A), Good (A-), and Good enough (B+).</li>
  <li>It doesn’t matter that you can’t reasonably compare today’s students to students from more than five years ago.</li>
  <li>It’s actually a good thing for Yale undergraduates because employers and graduate schools like high grades.</li>
</ol>

<p>This doesn’t mean we should wash our hands and walk away–There are still some issues with grades that should be addressed.  First, grade distributions are still rising and we could end up in a place where there isn’t enough room at the top to distinguish great students. That wouldn’t be fair to those students because they are the ones who should get into the best graduate schools and get the best jobs. It would be nice to put the brakes on grade inflation even if we don’t need to reverse it. The economics department has had some success holding grade distributions steady since we started suggesting grade guidelines to our faculty before the end of every semester. They aren’t requirements, but the faculty do seem to take them seriously.</p>

<p>The second issue is that grade distributions at Yale vary across departments. In general, grades are higher (and more compressed) in courses that judge students based on essays, papers, and class participation where it’s just hard to assign a numeric grade. It’s easier to do so in courses that have more exams and problem sets where it’s much clearer what’s right and wrong, and these classes tend to have more “traditional” grade distributions. This means students who care about grades shy away from classes and majors that are more likely to lower their GPA even if those classes might be more interesting or beneficial in the long-term. I’ve had students who want to go to law school but feel like they won’t get into a top program because they took too much science and math.</p>

<p>I don’t think it makes sense to force or even suggest that all classes follow the same grade distribution.  Even in my department, the guidelines are different for the more quantitative/analytical core classes than the more creative/applied advanced classes. I think the best way to head off potential future grade inflation is for departments to have their own suggested grading guidelines that may depend on the type of course.</p>

<p>Incentivizing students to take the more harshly graded classes and enroll in the “tougher” majors is a harder problem, and I don’t have an answer.  I do know that at my alma mater, students’ rank in their graduating class and in their major was on their transcript. I think doing this at Yale would be better than doing nothing. Some grad schools and employers would ignore this information, but the smarter ones would use it to identify the best students.  </p>

<p>NOTE: It should be glaringly obvious from a brief perusal of this site that I do not speak on behalf of Yale.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Few Thoughts on Grade Inflation]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/07/a-few-thoughts-on-grade-inflation/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/07/a-few-thoughts-on-grade-inflation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.yalealumnimagazine.com/articles/3735">Grade inflation at Yale</a> is a sensitive topic–The administration doesn’t even like to call the issue grade inflation but instead refers to the problem as grade <em>compression</em>. The feeling is not that grades are (necessarily) too high, but that with so many A’s and A-‘a being handed out, it’s very hard to distinguish the good students and the great students. Is this really true? And is grade inflation itself a real problem? And if there is a problem with grade distributions, how should we fix it? I don’t have answers, but I do have opinions.</p>

<p>First off, many people complaining about grade inflation seem to believe students today don’t “deserve” so many A’s. I think that’s dumb.  The main purpose of class grades is to help employers and graduate schools distinguish between students graduating at the same time from the same university. Even with Yale’s high mean grades right now, I believe there is still enough variation in the distribution to be able to do this. Grade inflation is a problem if <em>everyone</em> is getting A’s, but as long as you have three grade categories (e.g., A, A-, and B+) you can distinguish the excellent from the good and the good from the poor in a single graduating class.</p>

<p>As fun as it would be to be able to use grades to compare students from different generations, it’s not terribly useful.  By the time you are five years out of college, employers have far better direct information on workplace performance than your GPA. To put this in baseball terms, debating whether Miguel Cabrera is better than Joe Dimaggio is entertaining, but knowing the answer won’t help the Tigers compete for the World Series next year.  They need to assess performance of players available today.</p>

<p>Grades shouldn’t be used to compare individuals across universities either–institutional standards have been different for a long time.  <a href="http://www.rpi.edu">My alma mater</a> held grades to a B- average when I was in college and that was a lot lower than its peers.  It wasn’t a problem because employers knew this and took it into account when hiring new college graduates.  Plenty of my friends with seemingly low GPA’s had little trouble finding jobs.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, there is a fair bit of <a href="http://www.bostonglobe.com/ideas/2013/08/31/the-trouble-with-grade-inflation-works/tL6am7MEz56f3PA2MD7I3I/story.html">evidence</a> that employers and graduate schools <em>do</em> compare GPA’s across universities without taking proper account of the institutions’ different grade distributions. This argues that grade inflation at Yale is actually a <em>good</em> thing for its own undergraduates. Of course, if we want to live in a more meritocratic society (where the best students get the best jobs), it’s not fair that students at grade-inflated universities get the best jobs.</p>

<p>Implementing a solution is going to be difficult, because we’re stuck in a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prisoners_dilemma">prisoner’s dilemma</a>–all the elite universities have an incentive to ignore their own grade inflation because it benefits them individually.  There needs to be collective action (cooperation!) between schools on an issue that is prickly enough at the individual university level.</p>

<p>Alternatively, it might be easier for the <em>consumers</em> of grades to solve this problem by demanding class ranks and ignoring GPA’s all together when comparing candidates from different universities. That is, admissions committees and employers need to smarten up.  In a perfect market, economic theory predicts that the firms and schools that do this will get better candidates and drive the firms and schools that don’t out of business. This is the same theory that says discrimination on the basis of sex and race should naturally disappear from the market.  Now that I think about it, we might be living with the negative consequences of grade inflation for a while.</p>

<p>Update: <a href="/blog/2013/11/12/a-few-more-thoughts-on-grade-inflation">I’ve written up a couple more thoughts on grade inflation</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
