<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[education | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/education/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-23T00:38:51-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exams and Online Classes]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/08/23/exams-and-online-classes/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/08/23/exams-and-online-classes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With just a few exceptions, no one likes exams.  Students don’t like the stress of taking the exams, instructors have to write the exams, and someone usually has to grade them. In-class exams don’t give enough time for testing very much material, and if the test is too long, it punishes students who know their stuff but are just a little slow. Take-home exams can cover more content, but it can be very tempting for students to cheat by getting help from friends or the Internet. Unfortunately, we need objective assessments of how much each student has mastered the course material, and right now exams are the best tool we have.</p>

<p>In an online class, exams are even trickier.  In my econometrics class this summer, we held our midterm and final exams in the virtual classroom.  At exam time, I emailed them a PDF with all the questions and my students wrote their answers on paper while my teaching assistant and I watched them through their webcams. We used pencil and paper because answering the questions required doing a fair amount of math and I wanted to see their work.  I didn’t want them to use valuable time slowly typing in symbols and equations. After two hours, they scanned their written answers (mostly with their phone cameras) and emailed them to me.  When I confirmed receipt and readability, the students were free to go.  </p>

<p>The process was easy and convenient, but had one major flaw: it would have been pretty easy to cheat. I say this believing in my heart that none of my students cheated and having absolutely no evidence to even make me suspicious.  Even so, any one of them could have forwarded the exam PDF to a friend (or professional) and had them email back their answers.  The incentives for doing so are actually quite strong: Yale classes are not cheap and they get real Yale credit for my online class. Not to mention the fact that most elite college students care a lot about their GPA.</p>

<p>A second problem we ran into was that students’ Internet connections were not always reliable.  When these connections dropped, some students didn’t even notice for a while and others had trouble reconnecting.  It wouldn’t have been fair to just disqualify those students, but again, it was a pretty huge opportunity to cheat. </p>

<p>We considered three alternative testing procedures, but I think only one would be a clear improvement over what we did.  First, we thought about requiring students to have a separate webcam that would let us view their computer screen.  In this scenario, they couldn’t use their computer for evil, but I still think it would be relatively easy for them to cheat with an alternative device outside the frame of view.  Second, we investigated using an online service that locks down their computer for only exam taking purposes. <a href="https://webassessor.com">Webassessor</a> provides this service along with online proctors, but it would also require good webcam placement.  And both of these alternatives are still reliant on continuous connection to the Internet.</p>

<p>The solution I like best is to use an in-person testing service where students go to a controlled physical location to take their exam.  <a href="https://www.prometric.com">Prometric</a> has more than 10,000 test taking centers all over the world–that means a huge fraction of the world’s population is within two hours drive of a center so it’s not all that inconvenient to travel to one one or two times during a course.</p>

<p>Timing is an issue for all these solutions–that is, you’d like all your students to take the exam simultaneously so the early students can’t share information with those that take the exam later.  If your students are scattered around the globe, at least some of them will have to take their exam in the middle of the night and that doesn’t seem fair.  My students in the far east had to take their exams at either 10pm or 11pm.  One way around this problem would be to have two versions of the exam–one for each half of the planet.</p>

<p>Next time I teach an online class where the stakes are high, I’m going to try to use a service like Prometric.  I’ll let you know how it goes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Opposite of a MOOC]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/07/24/opposite-of-a-mooc/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/07/24/opposite-of-a-mooc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>MOOC’s are Massive Open Online Courses and they are what everyone in higher education is talking about. These classes  are usually free, have huge enrollments, and per student are pretty cheap to run relative to a typical college class. The quality can be decent and MOOC’s open up access to higher education to literally billions of people around the world. MOOC’s also have the potential to decrease the cost of education for the millions of people that would normally attend a traditional in person college.</p>

<p>Yale currently allows anyone on the Internet to watch record lectures from many of its best classes through <a href="http://oyc.yale.edu">Yale Open Courses</a>, but with zero interactivity, the user experience is quite different from taking a “real” course.  Yale has also recently entered a relationship with Coursera, the leading MOOC provider, and plans to dip its foot in the MOOC pool this year with a few classes.</p>

<p>At the same time, Yale has been breaking new ground through its Summer Session online classes which aim to let students experience as close to an in-person class as you can get without being on campus. These classes mix recorded video lectures with the usual outside-class reading and problem sets and a live interactive video session with the professor and rest of the class.</p>

<p>It’s these live sessions that are really innovative for online learning.  When a student logs in, they see everyone else in the class including the professor in a virtual classroom.  Imagine a Google Hangout with up to 25 participants.  It requires everyone to have a decent internet connection, but when it works, it’s kind of amazing. </p>

<p>It would be impossible to scale up this type of course to “massive” numbers of students, but the idea is to maximize quality, not minimize price.  I call it a Small Closed Online Course, and while Yale started offering these online classes two summers ago, I’m in the middle of teaching my first one now.  It’s “Econometrics and Data Analysis” and it’s been a real learning experience for everyone so far.</p>

<p>Students can take the class from almost anywhere.  I have students logging in three times a week from China, Singapore, Madrid, Kentucky, Alberta, California, and even a couple from downtown New Haven, CT. They can watch the video lectures when it is convenient for them and they have the power to pause and replay parts that are not clear the first time through.</p>

<p>The live experience is a work in progress. I use it to do three substantive things.  First, I answer questions about the recorded material and the reading.  It seems clear that my students are not taking notes and writing down questions they cannot ask in the moment (as they would in an in-person class) because most days they don’t have any questions. It’s hard to know how if they are really engaging with the recorded lectures or if they have them on while they’re doing something else. For the past couple classes I’ve been asking them basic questions about the material to get a sense for how much is sinking in. I am thinking about requiring them to email questions before the live session begins.</p>

<p>The main thing I do in the live sessions is have my students work through problems together.  The software we are using (<a href="http://watchitoo.com">Watchitoo</a>) allows me to divide the class into groups and send them to sub-classrooms.  I visit each of the groups in turn and push them along when they get stuck. It’s classic <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flipped_classroom">flipped classroom</a> stuff and it works well.</p>

<p>The third thing we do is discuss the material. I haven’t done much of this so far, but I have some future classes planned where we go over new applications of methods and talk in depth about specific points.  Most of Yale’s online classes thus far have been discussion-oriented (e.g., psychology or philosophy), but econometrics is much closer to a math class and thus not as good a match for discussions.</p>

<p>The technology has mostly worked well but has some real rough edges. Some students just don’t have strong enough internet connections and drop in and out during the live sessions. Moving between the sub-classrooms and the full classroom takes several more mouse clicks and time than I’d like. The whiteboard built into the live session software is too buggy to use, but we’ve had great success with a free HTML-based shared whiteboard (<a href="http://awwapp.com">awwapp.com</a>) I have the live session in one window on my laptop and my whiteboard in another window on my Wacom external monitor.  This lets me write with a real stylus and still see all my students.</p>

<p>One of the most successful parts of the class is my office hours.  I hold them in the same virtual classroom and use the same virtual whiteboard.  It’s almost identical to my in-person office hours.  Realtime access to an expert is the biggest difference between this class and a MOOC.</p>

<p>I’m getting a fair bit of feedback on how much they’re learning from their problem sets and the live sessions, but I miss being able to look into their eyes while I’m lecturing. We have our first exam this week, and I honestly don’t know how they are going to do.  My fingers are crossed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I've learned about teaching advanced undergraduate seminars]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/05/20/seminars/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/05/20/seminars</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At Yale, economics majors are required to take two “senior seminars” before they graduate.  These classes usually have 10-20 students and revolve around reading and discussing contemporary research in a specific area. After three years of mostly big lecture classes on theory and methods, seniors finally get a chance to apply what they’ve learned to a substantive topic.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> I just finished my fourth year of teaching two of these seminars, and while that might not seem like very long, I have learned a lot about what works and what doesn’t work.  </p>

<h2 id="big-goals">Big Goals</h2>

<p>Every seminar should have both a substantive theme and a methodological theme.  In the fall I teach the Economics of Aging. We read papers on retirement, saving, elder care, and inheritance–if it’s economics and it affects older people, the topic is fair game. Most of the papers we read use structural microeconometric methods. The theory and estimation methods are serious–I still remember the shocked look a senior faculty member gave me when I told him we were reading <a href="http://gemini.econ.umd.edu/jrust/crest_lectures/rust_phelan.pdf">Rust and Phelan’s 1997 paper on Social Security, Medicare, and Retirement</a><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. In the spring, I teach the Economics of Human Capital in Latin America. The papers are mostly about the determinants of health and schooling in the region and most use reduced form program evaluation techniques. I teach just enough about difference-in-differences, matching, regression discontinuity, and instrumental variables so that my students can understand why an author chose a particular method and can interpret the results. By the end of the semester, my students can read a big chunk of the research literature that was previously inaccessible.</p>

<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>

<p>I require my students to read two or three dense articles each week. I tell them they are hard and not to expect to understand everything immediately–these aren’t fluffy beach novels.  I encourage them to work at it and tell them I wouldn’t have assigned the articles if I didn’t they they were smart enough to figure them out.  To help them focus, students must fill out and submit a worksheet for each paper before we discuss it in class. Some articles (like surveys or policy reports) get special worksheets, but most worksheets contain these seven questions:</p>

<ol>
  <li>What is the research question? There may be more than one, but usually one is most important.</li>
  <li>What is the answer to the research question?</li>
  <li>Why is this paper important</li>
  <li>If there is an economic model, what is the behavior or process being modeled? What are the key characteristics of the model?</li>
  <li>What is the empirical approach?</li>
  <li>What data does the paper use?</li>
  <li>What didn’t you understand?</li>
</ol>

<p>The worksheets keep students thinking critically and constructively. The last question is most important to me as it tells me what I need to cover well during class time. The syllabus also suggests optional papers for most weeks in case students are particularly interested in a topic.</p>

<h2 id="student-presentations">Student Presentations</h2>

<p>Each week two or three students help me teach the class. They read the papers ahead of time and we meet to make sure they understand them well. These meetings are a pretty efficient way for me to review the week’s material and get to know my students. We usually plan short presentations on the papers that cover the basics quickly and some of the important technical parts that the rest of the class might have missed when they read the papers. Often the presentations contain new stuff from related or more recent papers to spur discussion. An easy way to put a class to sleep is to tell them things they already know.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> The students then draft slides which I review the night before class. Again, it’s a great way for me to prepare and it means there is never a bad presentation.</p>

<p>During class, I interrupt the speakers often to offer alternative explanations of difficult points and ask the rest of the students questions. I try to do it in a constructive/respectful way–the goal is for everyone to be engaged and at least following along.</p>

<h2 id="discussion">Discussion</h2>

<p>After the presentations, I usually divide the class into small groups of 4-5 students each and give each group a job. Sometimes they will design a conditional cash transfer program for a particular context. Sometimes they will prepare for a debate on alternatives to social security. Sometimes they will make a list of the three most important questions in an area that remain unanswered. The key is that the students never know exactly what’s going to happen when they walk into the classroom. After the groups work for 15-20 minutes, we all talk about what they’ve come with as a big group.</p>

<p>Sometimes we don’t have time for any discussion because I’ve given a mini lecture about an econometric method that they need to know in order to do the reading for the next week. I’ll have a few questions for the class prepared, but mostly we proceed organically with an eye on the clock. </p>

<h2 id="papersprojects">Papers/Projects</h2>

<p>Most seminars require some sort of paper, but it’s often not well-defined and the instructor sees it for the first time when it’s passed in at the end of the semester.  That is very different from how it works in my seminars.  Each student works throughout the semester on a research proposal and gets lots of feedback from their peers and me during the process.  </p>

<p>At about week 3, they pass in a one page summary of their research idea. Before this, I try and give an overview of the topics we’ll cover during the semester. I also describe three or four successful proposals from earlier semesters. Their one-pagers are ungraded but I do tell them if I think they’re on the right track, give them ideas on how to refine their ideas, and point them to relevant literature.</p>

<p>They draft the front-end of the proposal in the middle of the semester. This builds on the research question and contains a literature review, a hypothesis, and an economic model. They’ve seen several models in papers and other classes by this point, but constructing one of your own to explain how a process works is a difficult but rewarding experience. I don’t expect them to formally prove any theorems based on their models–they can do that if they go to grad school.</p>

<p>Before they pass in their mid-term proposal, I spend a little class time explaining what I expect in the literature review and walk through the process of constructing an example model. I also hold three or four “work groups” outside class where 5-6 students and I talk through each student’s project. It’s more time-efficient than having one-on-one meetings and incredibly useful for the students to hear about and contribute to each other’s work.</p>

<p>I spend a fair bit of time giving constructive feedback on the midterm proposal. I give comparatively much less feedback on the final papers as most students don’t read those comments and even fewer will act on those comments. I expect every student to incorporate my mid-term feedback into their final paper.</p>

<p>We have another round of work group meetings near the end of the semester to talk about the last pieces of the final proposal: the empirical approach and the data. Here’s where they have to decide how to actually answer the question they posed at the beginning of the semester. The whole process exercises the creative part of their brain that is vastly under-used in most classes. </p>

<p>The important thing is not that the paper is a research proposal, though that works well for me. The key is that students actually work on it throughout the semester and get feedback along the way. </p>

<h2 id="miscellaneous-advice">Miscellaneous Advice</h2>

<p>I believe one of the most valuable services I provide is just being available. Elite college professors are not typically great teachers. They are selected for their research skills and knowledge of the field. They should use this comparative advantage in their teaching by answering questions and talking about the state-of-the-art.  These classes are small–I am never overwhelmed answering questions after class or during office hours.  We aren’t talking about 300 person lectures where you could spend your life answering student email.  The bottom line is that most students really appreciate human contact.</p>

<p>I try to have a very open mind about improving the class and talk to other instructors about what works and doesn’t work for them.  I also take the last 15-20 minutes of the last class every semester getting direct feedback about what worked and what didn’t. Formal student evaluations are valuable, but they don’t allow for a conversation. I can throw out ideas and see what they think.  I can ask follow-up questions. Some students’ ideas spawn other students’ ideas. And every year, I learn new things that improve my class.</p>

<p>I refresh my classes at least a little bit every time I teach. I’ll dump the worst week. I’ll add papers I’ve come across over the last year that are interesting and relevant. I’ll try new exercises in class. And I’ll change what I expect from student presentations. It’s a lot easier to keep students excited when I’m excited.</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes:</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>Juniors can take these classes if they meet the pre-requisites (at least two of intermediate micro, intermediate macro, and econometrics), but seniors get priority and the most popular seminars are full by the time juniors can register. It’s a shame, really, since these seminars can be great training for writing a senior essay.<a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>His exact words were “You can’t teach that paper to undergraduates!” He was wrong–the motivation and descriptive sections of the paper are very well-written and approachable. The model of retirement presented is tough, but straight-forward. And the results are easy to understand once you understand the model. We skip the heavy duty derivation of estimation method.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>It’s also a great way to encourage them to skip the reading.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lectures 2.0: Using online materials to improve off-line courses]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/29/lectures-2.0/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/29/lectures-2.0</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The big lecture is an institution in institutions of higher learning. The professor stands at the front of a hall full of students and talks. Sometimes he or she uses slides and sometimes he or she writes on a board.  And sometimes, he or she is informative and engaging, but it’s almost always a pretty one way affair with occasional questions posed to the class.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>  The experience for students is a lot like watching a good documentary.  And that’s the best case scenario. The vast majority of the time, students sit back and absorb the flow or just check out. They don’t get <em>their</em> questions answered or engage constructively with the material. The average professor talks at their students for an hour and a half twice a week and it’s more like a late night infomercial than a documentary. </p>

<p>Now let’s think about seminars. Students read articles and book chapters ahead of time and then gather in a small classroom to discuss the material with the professor and each other. Often there are in-class exercises or even smaller group activities. In general, students report they get more out of these classes. </p>

<p>So why aren’t all classes structured as seminars? First of all, some material (especially introductory material) is more easily presented visually than textually–that’s one reason why <a href="http://www.khanacademy.org">Kahn Academy</a> is so successful. Seeing someone work through a problem is, for many students, a lot clearer than reading about it in a book. Lecturing allows for this kind of presentation and I believe it complements book learning. The second reason is purely economic: Seminars are expensive. If you have 33-34 students per seminar and you want to teach 100 students, you need three professors.  That’s triple what you’d need to teach a 100 person lecture.</p>

<p>Wouldn’t it be great if we could take the best qualities of the lecture and the seminar and combine them in an economically feasible way?  We can. </p>

<p>I was asked recently why I am excited to teach an online class this summer. Expanding the reach of my teaching was one reason, but it also gives me the opportunity to put together high quality online materials. This won’t simply be recordings of my hour and half lectures. Instead, it will be 3-5m chunks of <a href="https://www.udacity.com">Udacity</a>-style video interspersed with questions to make sure students are following along. The video will mostly be me drawing on slides, working through problems, and presenting new concepts.</p>

<p>Here’s my vision: The 100 person class is divided into three separate groups of students. Each week, all students work their way through about 2 hours worth of online interactive video. At the end of the week, I meet with each group for an hour. I answer questions that they still have. I tie the “timeless” online material to current events. I have them work on problems in smaller groups and float between groups helping them as needed. </p>

<p>I think the experience will be clearly better for students, but what about faculty and the administration? This won’t happen unless it’s a Pareto improvement.  That is, none of the parties involved can be worse off. </p>

<p>Once the materials are in place, they can be re-used by different professors–this radically reduces the amount of prep time. The class itself should be a lot more fun to teach since the professor  can actually have conversations with students and get direct feedback on how well the class is going. If the online materials are high quality (and they should be), the professor doesn’t have to be fantastic to teach an excellent class. Most faculty are not naturally great lecturers, but the small classes give them an opportunity to share their raw intelligence and experience with the material–it’s a much better skill match.</p>

<p>The administration is happy because the same 100 students are getting higher quality education for the same cost.  In fact, far more students get to benefit from close contact with big name professors–that makes the institution look good.</p>

<p>What I’m describing is not a totally new idea–It’s a straight-forward application of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flip_teaching">flipping the classroom</a>. And it’s an idea that gets better and better every day as the education world learns  more about what works online and more high quality materials are made publicly available.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Some professors will use <a href="http://www.engaging-technologies.com/teaching-with-clickers.html">clickers</a> to get real-time multiple choice feedback from his or her audience.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Who should own course materials?]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/13/course-materials/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/13/course-materials</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every spring university departments match their faculty to the courses that will be taught the next year.  Often, professors are assigned to courses they’ve never taught before.  This is almost always the case for new assistant professors who haven’t really taught anything before.  In the best case scenario, whoever taught the class the last time around has lunch with the new instructor, passes on a few pearls of wisdom, and hands over a subset of their course materials.  I’ve personally benefited immensely from this generosity since it’s much easier to prepare a course when starting with a stack of slides, problem sets, and old exams. It’s also quite common to have to start from scratch.  But there is a better way.</p>

<p>First of all, a course is a lot more than slides, exams, and problem sets. Instructors say a lot of stuff that’s not on the slides–they do board work, ask students questions, and use their slides as a springboard for what they actually teach.  What the instructor says sometimes lives only in the instructor’s brain but often there exists a rough set of hand-written or quickly typed set of notes for each lecture. Some instructors will write up another set of notes about what worked and what didn’t after each class–I call these my post-mortem notes.  And then some instructors include various other fancy things in their classes like videos, online surveys and in-class exercises.</p>

<p>When I was in college, all fraternities kept files of class exams.  Every time a brother took a test, it went into a folder which could be used as a resource for future brothers. Surely departments can get at least this organized.  I propose that they do even better and serve as a clearing house for the materials for  at least their core courses and maybe all of their courses. My dream scenario is that <strong>when a professor has to teach a new course they get access to a department-managed folder that has all the materials from previous years.</strong></p>

<p>There are several potential issues here, but I believe they are all small relative to the potentially huge improvements in course quality and reductions in required teaching prep.</p>

<p><em>How can this be fair to the first professor who prepares a course?</em> Yes, the first person does more work. The department should give them more credit–perhaps a course and a half is fair. Frankly, these professors should get extra credit no matter who owns the course materials.</p>

<p><em>Shouldn’t courses be tailored to individual professors?</em> Yes, this is true too. That’s why the department shouldn’t just keep the previous year’s materials. Ideally, when someone takes over a course, they could peruse several years and find the best starting point for them.  And when they customize those materials, they are providing another potential starting point for the next instructor.</p>

<p><em>Prepping a course is a lot of work–the instructor should own that!</em> I agree here too and all I’m arguing is that the department should share ownership. Instructors should certainly be able to take with them whatever they’ve used to teach the course when/if they leave the university</p>

<p>Professors don’t generally make their materials public even to their departments because they don’t reap much (if any) personal benefit.  The sharing I’m talking about costs a small amount but yields big <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Positive_externality#Positive">positive external</a> benefits. Since the market isn’t solving this problem by itself, I think it only makes sense that economics departments should solve it by explicitly internalizing the externality.  That’s exactly what enforcing departmental ownership would do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
