<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[education | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/education/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-26T21:53:00-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Improving Classes with Live Student Feedback]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/24/improving-classes-with-live-student-feedback/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/24/improving-classes-with-live-student-feedback</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the huge payoffs from having smart students that are engaged and thinking <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/17/creativity-in-the-classroom/">creatively</a> is that they have great ideas for how I can make <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/05/20/seminars/">my courses</a> better. Yesterday was the last meeting of the semester for my <a href="http://www.econ.yale.edu/~dm529/hcla-syllabus.pdf">Economics of Human Capital in Latin America</a> seminar, and I spent the last 15 minutes getting feedback on the course. I could have waited for their written course evaluations, but this way we can actually have a constructive dialog. Here’s what we came up with:</p>

<h2 id="substantive-content">Substantive Content</h2>

<ul>
  <li>They felt like they learned a lot about economics, policy, and empirical methods, but didn’t have a strong feel for the region itself. I should provide more background material (e.g., optional reading) on Latin America.</li>
  <li>After the introductory week, weeks two and three are focused on schooling. My students choose their research topics right before the fourth week. Not surprisingly, topics are heavily weighted toward education. I need to do a better job during the first week previewing the later course content, but I’m also seriously considering making their research topics due a week later so they are exposed to a wider range of material.</li>
  <li>Some students wanted to spend a week talking about how human capital influences (and is influenced by) poverty and inequality at a macro level. I used to have a class on this topic but dropped it. I might have to bring it back.</li>
  <li>Other students wanted to know more about rural areas of Latin America and in particular the role of human capital in agriculture. I think most of the interesting work on agriculture in development economics is happening in Africa and Asia, but I should look more closely to see if there are good papers in Latin America.</li>
  <li>For everything I add, something has to go, and I’m not sure what that would be. Maybe I should give them a menu of 15+ topics and have them vote for their favorite 13 at the beginning of the semester.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="empirical-methods">Empirical Methods</h2>

<ul>
  <li>The literature we read mostly relies on data analysis methods they have never seen before. These include difference-in-differences, instrumental variables, regression discontinuity, and propensity score matching. I try to give short mini-lectures about these methods in class before they read articles that use them. Sometimes we run out of time and I email them some notes and review the method on the same day we discuss the corresponding paper. This is sub-optimal and I need to try harder to do the mini-lectures before they read the papers. That said, my students did appreciate the class’s balance of substance and method.</li>
  <li>I should provide more references for the methods we talk about for those students that want to learn more.</li>
  <li>In years past I’ve had some students suggest that I hand out a methods problem set at the beginning of the semester to ensure that they take some time outside class to mull the math behind the methods. This year a student suggested a short in-class quiz early in the semester for the same reasons. It would certainly help them later in the semester if they were more solid on the methods, so next year I’m going to try one of these ideas.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="worksheets">Worksheets</h2>

<ul>
  <li>A staple of my seminars is the worksheet that every student fills out for every article they read during the semester. They always struggle at the beginning and then get the hang of it. To speed up this process, some students suggested that I walk through a few worksheets in class and hand out a few more examples of  worksheets that are filled out well.</li>
  <li>Almost every article we read has one key table or figure that summarizes the primary contribution of the paper. One of my students had the fantastic idea that I should ask them to identify this in the worksheets. Doing so would force them to spend quality time with the raw tables instead of trusting the authors’ textual interpretation of the results.</li>
  <li>At the end of every worksheet, I ask them what they didn’t understand in the paper. Some of the students were frustrated that they didn’t always get answers to those questions in class. <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/10/online-tech-in-an-in-person-seminar/">I tried to fix this</a> last semester and the cure was worse than the disease. A better system is out there, but I still don’t know what it is.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="presentations-and-in-class-exercises">Presentations and In-class Exercises</h2>

<ul>
  <li>They all got a lot out of preparing and doing a presentation in class, and one student suggested that everyone should do this twice. I don’t want to spend more class-time on presentations, but if the individual presentations are shorter, this could work well.</li>
  <li>They liked the presentations of things they hadn’t read such as background material or optional papers. We should do more of this.</li>
  <li>In class I often have them suggest potential solutions to complicated social problems in a very small amount of time. If I pre-announce these exercises, they can think about them before class and have a better and deeper discussion during class.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creativity in the Classroom]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/17/creativity-in-the-classroom/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/17/creativity-in-the-classroom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.missionartcenter.com"><img src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-kids-painting.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>While some disciplines encourage substantial creativity in their undergraduate students, the vast majority of college student academic effort goes into analysis or memorization. Certainly that’s true in economics. Most of the students in my seminars are seniors, and they are far more comfortable interpreting and using theory than creating or even tweeking it. </p>

<p>In the core classes, economics majors are taught a series of models of the world. These include simple models like: “Individuals make choices to maximize their utility<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.” If these individuals don’t know exactly what the consequences of their choice might be, we assume they maximize their <em>expectation</em> of utility. Another example: Prices are determined by equating demand and supply functions since at the end of the day, the amount bought and the amount put up for sale should be the same (i.e., they reach an <em>equilibrium</em>). If I write down one of these models on the board in a senior seminar, my students recognize it and can tell me what it means. If I describe a novel situation and ask them to write down a formal model that captures the choices made and the constraints faced, they have a much harder time.</p>

<p>Like almost any activity, you can become better at coming up with new and interesting ideas through practice. I follow three principles to inspire my students to work creatively in my classes. The first is that students must be actively engaged. Some faculty are very good at this. On the first day of the semester, <a href="http://www.yale.edu/strobel/">Scott Strobel</a> has all his students play <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mastermind_(board_game)">Mastermind</a>. Most of them have never seen this game before, and they need to figure out how it works. They actively grapple with the problem instead of passively receiving knowledge from the lecture. As the semester progresses, Professor Strobel spends some time transferring static knowledge from his brain to his students’, but he focuses his effort on teaching students how to think.</p>

<p>There are many ways to keep students engaged. Calling on them when they haven’t raised their hand, saying slightly outrageous things to start conversations, and basically making sure the class is more interesting than Facebook all help. This is harder in a big lecture, but not impossible. Mixing in quizzes, pair exercises, and even <a href="http://www.cmu.edu/teaching/clickers/">clickers</a> can make sure students come to class and think while they are there.</p>

<p>The second key to inculcating creativity is the most obvious: Have students create things during class. I often spend the first hour talking about something substantive and in the second hour my students break into small groups and propose something new. In one class we started by discussing several policies different countries have tried for reducing high school drop out rates. Then each small group proposed (and later defended) a new policy for reducing high school drop out in a particular context. In another class, I had them design their own conditional cash transfer programs. While most conditional cash transfer programs involve paying parents (usually mothers) to take their kids to the doctor or enroll them in school, I wanted my students to think outside the box. Some of the ideas they came up with were really interesting. In a third class, we talked about the relationship between health and retirement behavior and how health is a multi-dimensional concept. The small groups then proposed new ways to measure dimensions of health that are ignored by traditional measures. </p>

<p>My third principle is that ideas are precious. That is, the classroom has to be a safe place to share an imperfect idea. Most ideas my students come up with are bad. This isn’t surprising since most ideas anyone comes up with are bad. In fact, the more innovative and truly new an idea is, the more flaws it initially has. But the vast majority of <em>all</em> good ideas start as bad ideas. Bad ideas inspire other ideas which inspire other ideas which may  eventually be good ideas. That’s why it’s so important not to squash things right away. I model this by saying things like “Here’s a bad idea, but maybe it will help us think of something that would actually work.” Providing constructive feedback is critical to the process of moving ideas along.</p>

<p>The rewards to creativity in real economic research (and I think scientific research in general) are huge. All of the truly great papers involve big leaps. Strong analytical skills are important, but they are far from sufficient. In the workplace, there are big payoffs to creativity too. I’d even say that creativity is a traditional comparative advantage of the United States. </p>

<p>Yale President Peter Salovey’s <a href="http://president.yale.edu/creativity-transfer">recent Note from Woodbridge Hall</a> gives several examples of Yale graduates starting businesses, writing plays, and inventing products. He’s absolutely right that some Yale students are very creative. And yet, I believe we can and must do better at encouraging their innate creativity in the classroom.</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes:</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>You can think of utility as happiness, but the concept is a little bit different. Imagine that individuals rank, in order of preference, every possible combination of stuff that they value. If they maximize their utility, that means there is no other attainable combination of stuff that they prefer.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Another Way to Teach Seminars]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/06/another-way-to-teach-seminars/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/06/another-way-to-teach-seminars</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Peloponnesian-War-Donald-Kagan/dp/0142004375"><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-the-peloponnesian-war.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>Donald Kagan is a giant<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> in the study of ancient Greek history–I mean sheesh, you should see his <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald_Kagan">Wikipedia</a> page! He is also one of the most celebrated teachers at Yale and the other day I had the pleasure of <a href="http://teaching.yale.edu/programs/faculty/award-winning-teachers-teaching-lunchtime-colloquia">hearing him talk</a> about how he teaches seminars. </p>

<p>Each week during the semester Professor Kagan has two of his students write a 5-7 page response to specific questions related to the week’s topic. For example, in his class on Thucydides and the Peloponnesian War, he has students evaluate Sparta’s strategies and try to suggest better ones. The students circulate their papers a week before class so everyone has a chance to read and digest them. The class consists primarily of a group interrogation of the authors led by Professor Kagan. I believe the students find the process equal parts intimidating and inspiring. Each student is held to the fire twice during the semester.</p>

<p>Everyone is expected to be prepared for class. That becomes very clear very quickly because Professor Kagan considers every student fair game for probing questions. That would be enough to make me read. I should definitely do more of this in my seminars.</p>

<p>Ancient Spartans used to have lunch in groups of 15. Based on this (and his own personal experience) Professor Kagan says 15 is the optimal number of students in a seminar. I’d love to have a seminars this size, but I also hate turning students away. My compromise is to accept about 25 students. The class is still good for the first 15 and loads better for the 10 students who would otherwise miss out completely.</p>

<p>In addition to his oral feedback during class, Professor Kagan gives written feedback on the papers. He does not assign any grades to anything until the end of the semester. While I feel qualitative feedback is far more valuable as both a guide and a motivator, I also believe students deserve a clear quantitative signal about their work. If they want an A, they need to know if they need to invest more in the class. Final grades should not be surprises.</p>

<p>In many ways Professor Kagan’s method couldn’t be more different from <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/05/20/seminars/">mine</a>. Learning how to write a long technical research paper and working on it throughout the semester is the spine of my seminars. Professor Kagan explicitly eschews this as he wants his students to spend as much time as possible grappling with the week’s reading and the concepts in those <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_the_Peloponnesian_War">books</a> (or even <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stele">steles</a>). Even so, I’m still excited to try a few of his techniques.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Titan_(mythology)">Titan</a> is probably the more appropriate term. <a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Economics and Data Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/09/economics-and-data-analysis/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/09/economics-and-data-analysis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We live in a world where more and more people and organizations make <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Super-Crunchers-Why-Thinking-By-Numbers-Smart/dp/0553384732">decisions based on data</a>. These include business decisions, policy-making decisions, and even many personal decisions. <a href="http://www.quora.com/Google/What-do-economists-do-at-Google-their-responsibilities-as-Googles-employees">Google employs hundreds of quantitative analysts</a> to analyze auctions, forecast revenue, predict customer needs, and surely lots of other things we don’t know about. A good friend of mine just spent the last month carefully analyzing student loan data for the <a href="http://www.federalreserve.gov">Federal Reserve</a>. I even just read about a guy who <a href="http://www.wired.com/wiredscience/2014/01/how-to-hack-okcupid/all/">scraped dating data from OK Cupid</a> to find himself a wife.</p>

<p>Business and the government often look to economists to do this kind of data analysis for two main reasons. First, economists have been using data to answer questions about optimal behavior for a long time and have developed a set of statistical methods tuned for these problems that we call <em>econometrics</em>. These tools are particularly applicable to the non-experimental (aka “observational”) data that is piling up all around us. The second reason is that economists are good at thinking mathematically about human behavior and markets–two concepts at the heart of many important questions. </p>

<p>I am constantly telling my undergraduate students to take as many classes on econometrics, statistics, and/or data analysis as they can.  Only one semester of statistics/econometrics is required to get a bachelor’s degree in economics at Yale, and this introductory course covers the basics of probability, statistical inference, and linear regression.  The payoff to taking the second class is huge–that’s where students actually gain proficiency with elementary methods and build up to important methods like instrumental variables and difference-in-differences that can separate causation from correlation.</p>

<p>I recently did an informal survey of ten top-tier economics departments and learned that seven of the ten now require two semesters (or quarters) of statistics and/or econometrics.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> I will be shocked if in five years it’s not at least nine out of ten. Even now, many advanced applied elective courses teach statistical methods so that students can understand (and contribute to) the research they read.</p>

<p>At the beginning of my last semester in college I had a conversation with a fellow senior that has really stuck with me. He went on and on about how excited he was to be taking Econ 101. At least part of his logic was that he didn’t want to graduate without knowing something about the economy. I had not taken any economics up to this point and had no idea what he was talking about. I didn’t get it at all. Now I do. Economics training gives people tools for understanding how the world works. That training needs to keep up with our increasingly data-driven world.</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes:</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Harvard, MIT, Berkeley, Brown, Penn, and Duke require their economics majors to take two semesters of econometrics and/or statistics. Stanford requires two quarters. Yale, Amherst, and Princeton require one semester. Yale also offers an Econ/Math degree that requires two semesters of econometrics.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't Throw Them to the Wolves]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/04/thrown-to-the-wolves/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/04/thrown-to-the-wolves</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-wolfpack.jpeg"></p>

<p>I recently heard <a href="http://bbs.yale.edu/people/michael_koelle-1.profile">Michael Koelle</a> (Associate Professor of Molecular Biophysics and Biochemistry at Yale) give a very interesting <a href="http://teaching.yale.edu/programs/faculty/award-winning-teachers-teaching-lunchtime-colloquia">presentation on teaching</a>. He led by saying he wasn’t going to talk about anything trendy like MOOC’s or flipping the classroom or project-based learning, but would instead focus on how how he teaches traditional big lecture courses. He proceeded to tell us about the most progressive lecture courses I’ve ever heard of. Among other things, he never lectures for more than 15 minutes at a time and peppers his classes with interactivity and small group exercises. While his whole talk was inspiring and full of concrete advice and ideas, I want to write today about something he brought up almost in passing.</p>

<p>Professor Koehlle’s department introduces junior faculty to teaching big lectures by having them co-teach with someone senior the first few times. The junior sees first-hand what goes into a good lecture, learns the nuts and bolts with a safety net, and has someone right there who can answer questions and critique individual classes. What a great model! </p>

<p>The far more common practice is to throw junior faculty to the wolves in a big course. If you happen to be a natural or are willing to invest far more than makes sense for someone hoping to get tenure, it might result in a decent class. More often than not, it’s a train wreck. It occurs to me that while many departments can’t afford to have two faculty teaching their big classes, there are other (cheaper) ways to mentor juniors:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Have experienced senior faculty pay attention to juniors while they are teaching a challenging class for the first time. That means observing lectures, having lunch meetings about how things are going, and encouraging juniors to ask questions about teaching.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When a junior takes over an existing class, give them as much of the previous instructor’s materials as possible. Lecture slides are a start, but notes, problem sets and old exams are also helpful. If the department has <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/13/course-materials/">ownership of the materials</a>, this is easy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Let juniors get their first teaching experience in a high-level class. It sounds weird to people outside academia, but the more advanced classes are much easier to teach. The students in these classes are more bought into the discipline’s norms, and the material is closer to what the instructor works on every day while doing their research. Introductory classes need to be far more polished and have a much more diverse group of students. I love diversity but it’s a lot harder to teach. Electives are easiest of all because every student in the class wants to be there.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Exploit university resources outside the department for helping teachers. At Yale, the <a href="http://teaching.yale.edu">Yale Teaching Center</a> will help instructors learn from their evaluations, review syllabi, and even do classroom observation. Letting faculty know about these services is a nice first step, but my experience is that only the above average teachers take advantage of them. It should be mandatory for all juniors (and probably seniors too).</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Junior faculty in top departments are evaluated for promotion based on their research productivity. Mentoring is a way to improve their teaching without having to take time away from their research. In fact, there are techniques many juniors don’t know that will <em>save</em> them time spent teaching. Starting with high-quality course materials means less time preparing class. Clearer lectures mean fewer confused students visiting during office hours. A better match between lecture content and exam content means fewer irate student emails.</p>

<p>If a department is serious about upgrading the quality of its undergraduate instruction, doing a better job of mentoring junior faculty is low hanging fruit. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
