<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[music | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/music/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-10T10:07:33-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[So Embarrassing]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/09/18/so-embarrassing/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/09/18/so-embarrassing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve always valued a catchy beat over insightful lyrics and my favorite genres tend to reflect that. In other words, I listen to a lot of songs with dumb lyrics, so it means something that the other day I heard some <em>extra</em> dumb lyrics on the radio. </p>

<!--- Bonnie McKee, "American Girl"
--->
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/-Uh6VZF0R5U" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Lets take a closer look at Bonnie McKee’s “American Girl” line by line:</p>

<pre><code>I fell in love in a 7/11 parking lot
Sat on the curb drinking slurpees we mixed with alcohol
</code></pre>

<p>Either you’re underage and shouldn’t be mixing in alcohol or you’re of age and shouldn’t be drinking slurpees in the parking lot. I’m not sure which is worse. </p>

<pre><code>We talked about all our dreams and how we would show 'em all (whoa oh oh oh)
I told him I got a plan and I'm gonna dominate
And I don't need any man to be getting in my way
</code></pre>

<p>This is as good as it gets–girl power!</p>

<pre><code>But if you talk with your hands then we can negotiate (whoa oh oh oh)
</code></pre>

<p>I think she’s making a subtle sexual reference here. </p>

<pre><code>I just keep moving my body (yeah)
I'm always ready to party (yeah)
No I don't listen to mommy (yeah)
And I'll never say that I'm sorry
</code></pre>

<p>First off, not one of these four lines actually rhymes, and I don’t think she’s trying to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slant_rhyme">emulate Emily Dickinson</a>. Second, you’re to old to be calling your mother mommy. And third, I think even Gandhi had to occasionally apologize.</p>

<pre><code>Chorus
Oh I'm an American girl
</code></pre>

<p>If the rest of the world thinks this girl is representative of the whole population of American girls, we are in deep trouble.</p>

<pre><code>Hot blooded and I'm ready to go I'm loving taking over the world
Hot blooded, all american girl (Whoa) I was raised by a television
</code></pre>

<p>I spent a good chunk of my childhood in front of a TV too, but I watched relatively wholesome fare like The Brady Bunch, Happy Days, and Gilligan’s Island. She must have been raised by Bridezilla, real Housewives of Beverly Hills and The Jersey Shore. </p>

<pre><code>Every day is a competition Put the key in my ignition (Oh-way-oh)
</code></pre>

<p>Oh no; another subtle sexual reference. I think she needs to go to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Back_in_Black#Track_listing">AC DC school</a></p>

<pre><code>I wanna see all the stars and everything in between
</code></pre>

<p>Unless she has a thing for dark matter, I have a feeling she’s talking about celebrities more than astronomy.</p>

<pre><code>I wanna buy a new heart out of a vending machine
Cause It's a free country so baby we can do anything (Whoa)
</code></pre>

<p>We may be a free country, but we still have fairly strict laws banning the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Organ_trade">sale of organs</a>.</p>

<pre><code>Chorus

You know we're gonna shine so bright (Oh we're gonna shine so bright...) Oh baby gonna go all night (Oh we're gonna go all night) You know we're gonna shine so bright (Oh we're gonna shine so bright...) Oh baby gonna go all night

Chorus
</code></pre>

<p>Every American should be embarrassed that this song exists. I was doubly embarrassed when I saw the “artist” was my namesake. And I’m triply embarrassed by how much I actually enjoy the song. It’s not as good as “Party in the USA” or “Call Me Maybe,” but it just makes me want to get up and dance whenever I hear it.  Maybe I should just stop talking before I embarrass myself further. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Third Wave of Awesome]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/09/13/a-third-wave-of-awesome/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/09/13/a-third-wave-of-awesome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I went to college in the late 1980’s, and <a href="http://www.rpi.edu">my school</a> was just close enough to NYC for the radio stations to play a lot of what was “hot” in the “hot” clubs in the city. And that was a Latin-infused pop dance music called <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freestyle_music">freestyle</a>. It was awesome:</p>

<!--- Noel, "Silent Morning"
--->
<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/bzA6yO7BO10" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
<!--- Sweet Sensation, "Hooked on You"
--->
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/psQfWUbEDEc" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
<!--- Stevie B, "Spring Love"
--->
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/sFjoNhUrmU0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I even used my fake ID to see <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sweet_Sensation">Sweet Sensation</a> perform live in Albany. After graduation, I moved to DC where (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WHFS_(historic)">Indie Rock was king</a>) and only heard freestyle driving through NYC on my way to and from Boston. The genre died out in NYC just a few years later.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>Amazing dance music came into my life again in 2003 when <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KDLD">103.1 FM</a> in Los Angeles started calling itself KDL and playing “<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dance_Hits">Dance Hits</a>.”  Instead of building on a Latin groove, they injected what seemed to me to be pure European pop trance directly into unsuspecting American ears.  </p>

<!--- Four Strings, "Take Me Away"
--->
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/faHomJimjLc" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
<!--- Junior Senior, "Move Your Feet"
--->
<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/SPlQpGeTbIE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
<!--- Sophie Ellis Baxtor, "Murder on the Dancefloor"
--->
<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/BsISfQAXE60" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I was obsessed and then devastated when KDL went off the air after less than a year.  And I wasn’t the only one–there’s a “<a href="http://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLCF544CF9FE670FB5">KDL Resurrected</a>” YouTube playlist containing 133 videos that now has 1,607 views!  That number would likely be hundreds bigger if almost all the videos had not been removed due to copyright violations.</p>

<p>And so we come to today. I like Pink, and Maroon 5 and Katy Perry as much as anybody, but I’m ready for some fresh pop blood. In just the last two days I’ve heard these three super catchy and extremely danceable songs on the radio:</p>

<!--- Calvin Harris ft. Ellie Goulding, "I Need Your Love"
--->
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/AtKZKl7Bgu0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
<!--- Cobra Starship ft. Sabi, "You Make Me Feel"
--->
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/HpyZEzrDf4c" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
<!--- Capital Cities, "Safe and Sound"
--->
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/47dtFZ8CFo8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Lets all cross our fingers that this is just the beginning.</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes:</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Genres never <em>actually</em> die–they just leave popular consciousness. This year Stevie B rerecorded Spring Love with Pit Bull, and I’m not sure anyone noticed.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Feeling Negative]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/25/feeling-negative/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/25/feeling-negative</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spend a lot of time on this blog raving about <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/11/kid-book-review-library-trip-report-3/">great kid books</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/02/22/not-dead-yet/">great music</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/01/17/mincer-1958/">great writing for grown ups</a>, and even <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/08/an-homage-to-chris-welty/">great teaching</a>, but don’t get the idea that I think everything is all sunshine and roses. There are plenty of things I don’t appreciate. Here are just three:</p>

<p>{% img right /images/hv-grateful-dead.jpg [title “Maybe the Ugliest Shirt of All-Time”] %}</p>

<h2 id="the-grateful-dead">1. The Grateful Dead</h2>

<p>When I think of the Dead, the first things that come to mind are dirty feet, ugly tie-dyed shirts, drugs, and silly annoying songs that just go on and on and on.  If you’re into that sort of thing, then I’m really sorry you can’t follow them around anymore.  At least you’ve got Phish.</p>

<h2 id="ezra-jack-keats">2. Ezra Jack Keats</h2>

<p>{% img left /images/hv-willie.jpg [title “Whistle for Willie”] %}</p>

<p>This is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ezra_Jack_Keats">Ezra Jack Keats</a> week at my girls’ preschool and besides <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/05/10/carle-vs-lioni/">Eric Carle</a>, there isn’t a more over-rated children’s book author/illustator.  I’m not an expert on Jack Keats, but I have read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Snowy-Day-Board-Book/dp/0670867330">The Snowy Day</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Whistle-Willie-Board-Book-Keats/dp/0670880469">Whistle for Willie</a> and thus feel perfectly justified generalizing to his whole body of work. I like that he his stories take place in cities. I like that he’s got African-American characters. And I’m not arguing he wasn’t an important trail blazer–he was. I’m just arguing that the books themselves are uninspired and boring.  In the last forty years lots of authors have taken the torch and done a better job with it. My favorites are <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Rain-Stomper-Addie-Boswell/dp/0761453938">The Rain Stomper</a> (by Boswell Addie, illustrated by Eric Velasquez), <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Corduroy-Don-Freeman/dp/0140501738">Corduroy</a> (by Don Freeman), and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bear-Bike-Stella-Blackstone/dp/1905236980">Bear on a Bike</a> (by Stella Blackstone, illustrated by Debbie Harter)</p>

<h2 id="new-orleans">3. New Orleans</h2>

<p>{% img right /images/hv-voodoo.jpg [title “VOODOO”] %}</p>

<p>For some people, New Orleans is a great city. It’s got world class sea food and its own brand of jazz. It’s got a casino downtown and a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bourbon_Street">whole street</a> full of daiquiris and debauchery. But for a vegetarian who doesn’t drink, doesn’t gamble, and whose musical tastes are a little less hip, New Orleans doesn’t have much to offer. I used to think the best thing about the city was voodoo and while that sounds all cool and mysterious, when you take a closer look, it’s not. Chicken blood, bits of hair, and stabbing little dolls to hurt real people is just creepy. Of course, there is <a href="http://www.auduboninstitute.org/visit/insectarium">the Insectarium</a> which is also a little creepy, but was a lot of fun with the girls when we visited a couple weeks ago. </p>

<p>OK, I’ll admit it: I’m not usually such a Debby Downer, but  accumulated sleep debt from a busy winter and spring has taken a toll on my normally sunny disposition. Hopefully the end of the semester will take care of this I’ll soon be back to being a Cheerful Charlie!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Heavy Metal for Kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/24/heavy-metal-for-kids/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/24/heavy-metal-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When most people think of heavy metal, the major themes that come to mind are death, evil, testosterone, violence, and maybe misogyny.  And sure, the vast majority of heavy metal is probably inappropriate for most kids. Especially little kids. But that doesn’t mean <strong>all</strong> metal is inappropriate. Some songs are downright kid-friendly and they’re a great way to inject some fresh blood into the typical parent’s rather limited musical repertoire.</p>

<p>Before I dive into my list of recommended tracks, you should know that there exists an actual just-for-kids metal band from Finland called <a href="http://www.hevisaurus.com">Hevisaurus</a> and they are awesome. They dress in dinosaur outfits and the videos are the good kind of crazy. Unfortunately, singing in Finnish is a deal breaker for me–my kids love fun lyrics and this music doesn’t sound all that different from traditional Scandinavian metal. We might as well be listening to early <a href="http://www.youtube.com/artist/dimmu-borgir">Dimmu Borgir</a> or <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jtasXTviObo">Opeth</a>.</p>

<p>My list comes in two parts. First are the songs that are actually family-friendly. The music isn’t too scary and the words don’t have any unacceptably rude surprises. And they rock.  Songs on the second list also rock and might seem OK for kids at first.  It’s just that some of the words might induce an awkward conversation (best case) or nightmares (worst case). </p>

<h3 id="part-1-the-best-of-the-best">Part 1: The best of the best</h3>

<p><strong>1. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pVThw0EE_Jo">Crazy Train</a> (Ozzy Osbourne):</strong></p>

<p>This song is almost perfect–Kids love trains and laughing, and so does Ozzy. If you ignore the fake blood and the bat-eating (and maybe the finger tattoos), Ozzy is just a silly old man–he reminds me a lot of Santa Claus without the hat or the beard. This song even has words John Lennon could have written:</p>

<pre>
    Maybe it's not too late
    To learn how to love
    And forget how to hate
</pre>

<p>(Full disclosure: This was my high school yearbook quote.)</p>

<p><strong>2. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EFMD7Usflbg">Rock and Roll All Night</a> (Kiss):</strong></p>

<p>The make-up and the costumes are super-fun and the song’s extremely catchy. Some of the lyrics are a little suggestive, but not enough to make me uncomfortable:</p>

<pre>
    You show us everything you've got
    Baby, baby that's quite a lot
    And you drive us wild, we'll drive you crazy
</pre>

<p><strong>3. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J2O69EO1QZc">Merry Go Round</a> (Mötley Crüe):</strong></p>

<p>This song is another slam dunk–carousels are on my older daughters’ list of the top five things in life along with ponies, princesses, fairies, and <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/10/06/violence-in-kids-books/">minotaurs</a>.</p>

<p><strong>4. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0UIB9Y4OFPs">Pour Some Sugar on Me</a> (Def Leppard):</strong></p>

<p>Kids love sugar and messes and this song has both. The band name also provides a good teachable moment about spelling–adults make mistakes too!</p>

<p><strong>5. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i2RKWJD5ops">Ice Cream Man</a> (Van Halen):</strong></p>

<p>It’s not the heaviest song in the world, but it does have an Eddie Van Halen guitar solo and who doesn’t like ice cream? The only issue is that this song is (surprise) not about ice cream at all, but the kids don’t have to know David Lee Roth is a drug-addled perv.</p>

<p><strong>6. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=orbFLK8n35E">Kids Will Rock</a> (Rough Cutt):</strong></p>

<p>Not too many folks have heard of Rough Cutt–they were one of the hair metal bands that didn’t quite make it big in the 80’s though I’m not sure why. This song is about kids and even has a chorus of kids join in at the end!</p>

<p><strong>7. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uX0Fp-T6YTc">Raise Your Hands to Rock</a> (Mötley Crüe):</strong></p>

<p>Songs that demand specific actions are always a big hit and this one couldn’t be catchier.</p>

<p><strong>8. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kdfRhU7IFPE">Jump</a> (Van Halen):</strong></p>

<p>Another movement song and this one might be even more fun to act out than the last.</p>

<p><strong>9. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rjCBV6o_DSE">Stand up and Shout</a> (Dio):</strong></p>

<p>Standing up and shouting is fun, but this song is borderline too fast and heavy. Ronnie also mentions being “nailed to the wheel” in passing, but even though I’ve listened to this song hundreds of times, I never noticed until reading the lyrics five minutes ago.</p>

<p><strong>10. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sxdmw4tJJ1Y">Rock You Like a Hurricane</a> (The Scorpions):</strong></p>

<p>We’ve been reading a ton of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Magic-School-Bus-Inside-Hurricane/dp/0590446878">Magic Schoolbus</a> books lately and hurricanes are pretty cool.</p>

<h3 id="part-2-dont-quite-make-the-cut">Part 2: Don’t quite make the cut</h3>

<p><strong>1. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LMLwslRNThM">Bark at the Moon</a> (Ozzy):</strong></p>

<p>I wanted so much for this song to be okay mostly because I’ve played it for the girls in the past and they like it. Hopefully they haven’t listened too closely to the words which contain gems like:</p>

<pre>
    Years spent in torment
    Buried in a nameless grave 
    Now he has risen 
    Miracles would have to save 
    Those that the beast is looking for 
</pre>

<p><strong>2. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EQ3swBEBqBc">Givin the Dog a Bone</a> (AC DC):</strong></p>

<p>I love dogs and I’m OK with innuendo, but this song crosses the subtlety line right away:</p>

<pre>
    She take you down easy
    Going down to her knees
    Going down to the devil
    Down down at ninety degrees
    She blowing me crazy
    'til my ammunition is dry
    She's using her head again
    She's using her head
</pre>

<p><strong>3. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ogYGDdl2Zs4">Give It All</a> (Ratt):</strong></p>

<p>I thought I might be able to spin this song as a tune about putting in your best effort. Too bad Stephen Pearcy is actually talking about how much love he is going to give his partner that night.</p>

<p><strong>4. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-a9DW_zhV84">Modern Day Cowboy</a> (Tesla):</strong></p>

<p>This song is about cowboys and it’s a story about the Cold War that even teaches lessons about geography and spelling with lines like “the USA! the USSR!” Unfortunately even cold wars involves guns:</p>

<pre>
    Bang Bang, shoot'em up.
    Bang Bang, blow you away.
</pre>

<p><strong>5. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H4zwAYiUybA">Hungry</a> (Winger):</strong></p>

<p>Kids get hungry and Winger is catchy as heck. But this song is not about being hungry for food:</p>

<pre>
    Girl I'm hungry for your love
    Girl I'm hungry
    Baby let me in
    Hungry for your love
    Hungry I can't get enough
</pre>

<p><strong>6.  <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mGWjwnvHpY8">Don’t Talk to Strangers</a> (Dio):</strong></p>

<p>This song had such promise as a fun song that teaches a valuable lesson. Too bad Ronnie James Dio comes across as a paranoid psychotic:</p>

<pre>
    Don't talk to strangers
    Cause they're only there to do you harm
    Don't write in starlight
    'Cause the words may come out real
    Don't hide in doorways
    You may find the key that opens up your soul
    Don't go to Heaven cause it's really only Hell
    Don't smell the flowers
    They're an evil drug to make you loose your mind
    Don't dream of women
    'Cause they'll only bring you down
</pre>

<p><strong>7. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MII3ns2KTBc">Iron Man</a> (Black Sabbath):</strong></p>

<p>The story of Iron Man is in many ways a like that of Rudolph the Red Nosed Reindeer. He looks different from everyone else and people mistreat him. And just as Rudolph led the sleigh on that foggy night, Iron Man “travelled time for the future of mankind.” But instead of joining in everyone’s reindeer games, Iron Man “kills the people he once saved.” Oh well.</p>

<h3 id="part-3-confession-time">Part 3: Confession time:</h3>

<p>I am a true child of 80’s metal and would very much like to share my passion for heavy music with my children. That’s why I’ve gone to the trouble to curate this list of songs that won’t get me fired as a dad. But a few issues remain:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The girls don’t actually like these songs very much. I’m hoping they will grow on them, but for now they far prefer kid music, boy bands, girl-pop, and even Latin music and reggae. </li>
  <li>None of my recommended songs are all that heavy. Korn, Metallica, and Slayer are all conspicuously absent. I’m going to be listening to “real” metal on my own time until the girls are quite a bit older. </li>
  <li>I don’t suggest watching any of the video versions of these songs.  All the subtlety goes out the window and is usually replaced by pyrotechnics and half-naked women. </li>
  <li>Suppose the your kids love this play list. There isn’t really anywhere else kid-appropriate to go. It was surprisingly hard to come up with even these few songs. </li>
</ol>

<p>All that said, my girls do put up with it in small doses and I certainly enjoy it!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How our home music system got a little more complicated and a lot more awesome]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/16/home-music-streaming-2/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/16/home-music-streaming-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-music-apps.png" alt="music apps" title="The music row of my iPhone home screen" /></p>

<p>Our household is heavily invested in iTunes. We have a big collection on an iMac that never sleeps. We have an AppleTV in the living room and an Airport Express in the kitchen that serve as AirPlay destinations. With the iOS Remote app, we can stream whatever we want wherever we want. It doesn’t depend on Bluetooth or on keeping iPods synced up to date, and now that our wifi network is working well<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, <a href="/blog/2012/03/02/home-music-streaming/">it’s great</a>. But I wanted more. </p>

<p>It turns out that our current 13,585 songs is not enough. Pretty often I’ll hear a new “artist”<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> on the radio and want to hear more from them. In the olden days I would carefully listen to 90 second samples in the iTMS and fret about <a href="/blog/2012/02/06/albums/">whether to invest in the whole album</a>. Now I can login to <a href="http://www.spotify.com">Spotify</a> on the desktop and listen to as much as I want over and over. If only there was a way to easily spread this goodness around the house. Of course there is.</p>

<p>The key to the system is a piece of Mac software made by <a href="http://rogueamoeba.com">Rogue Amoeba</a> called <a href="http://rogueamoeba.com/airfoil/">AirFoil</a>. It costs $25 and it will push the audio output of any app to any Airplay destinations. The next piece of the puzzle is an iPhone app called <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/reemote-for-airfoil/id396381723">Reemote</a> ($4.99) that remotely controls AirFoil. Another iPhone app called <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/app/remoteless-for-spotify/id353392482">Remoteless</a> ($2.99) lets me control the desktop Spotify and do things like search for artists, albums, or songs to play.  Each app requires a free helper app that runs on the Mac. If you’re willing to put up with Spotify’s ads (so far I am), the service is free! </p>

<p>Once Spotify, iTunes, and the two helper apps are up and running, here’s how it works. If I want to play music from my library, I bring up Reemote and make sure Airfoil streaming is turned off to my three destinations. Then I use Remote just as I used to. If I then want to play something with Spotify, I tell Remote to stream only to the computer and tell Reemote to stream to either the kitchen or the living room or both. Then I use Remoteless to get Spotify going. The process is surprisingly efficient when all three apps are on your iPhone’s home screen. The system itself is a little finicky and does occasionally require me to restart Spotify on the desktop, but the extra power is so worth it.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>With one click of a checkbox in the Airport Utility, the kitchen Airport Express now does double duty as a network extender. Suddenly reception downstairs went from 1-2 bars at best to mostly 5 bars.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Are Carly Rae Jepson and Owl City artists? By my definition, absolutely!<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
