<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[music | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/music/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-01T12:01:36-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[1983: Revisited]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/09/1983-revisited/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/09/1983-revisited</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/hv-holy-diver.jpg"></p>

<p>In the weeks after I posted <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/18/crucial-years-in-metal-1983/">my case for 1983</a> as a crucial year in heavy metal history, I went through a crisis of faith. What about Judas Priest? What about Iron Maiden? And what if I forgot an even bigger band or album? Luckily I could turn to my metal sensei in this time of need. The same Mike who dragged me to the import metal bins at the Rockin’ Mania record store in Framingham and opened my eyes to a whole world of music was just an email away. Here’s what he had to say:</p>

<!--more-->

<blockquote>
  <p>Nice article, but you missed out on a lot of other stuff was going on around that time. First, while I was a big fan of all Maiden’s albums up to and including Seventh Son, I think the albums before and after 1983’s Piece of Mind  are actually more influential.  In 1982 Maiden toured the world with Judas Priest.  They headlined everywhere except the US.  This album and tour really exposed Maiden to the fans in America and turned them into the pre-eminent act of the decade.  1984 brought Powerslave which launched Maiden into the mainstream with heavy rotation on MTV for both Aces High and Two Minutes to Midnight.  This was accompanied by the first tour by a western rock artist into the Soviet Bloc, years before the much ballyhoo’d Billy Joel tour.  So, the final word on Maiden: Piece of mind has a couple of their biggest live hits but lacked the impact of the other two records. </p>

  <p>There are a few records that aren’t on your list which I believe some credit: </p>

  <p>First, Dio’s Holy Diver.  Enough said.</p>

  <p>Try not to shit on the next two before I get done.</p>

  <p>Def Leppard Pyromania.  These guys pretty much single handedly started the hair metal era.  I know there are a lot of other bands that were important to the genre, but this album really kicked it off.</p>

  <p>Quiet Riot Metal Health.  Not the most creative musically, but it had some catchy stuff.  The important part regarding this one is the fact that it was the first metal album to reach number one on Billboard’s top 100.  Unheard of ground for a band of this genre.</p>

  <p>I’m glad you gave a nod to Ozzy’s Bark at the Moon.  Not his best work by any stretch, but it did resurrect his career from the aftermath of Randy Rhodes’ death.</p>

  <p>I am still a fan of Shout at the Devil.  It is the only true metal album Crue ever put out and is my favorite even though some of my favorite songs come from other records.</p>

  <p>You were always a little more into the hair bands than I, but I do have to give credit to the genre for helping to bring metal to the mainstream.  A friend and I were discussing the phenomenon of mainstreaming the other day.  I am constantly amazed by the music accepted by the mainstream media that we had to stay up until 1 in the morning to hear on the radio.  Not only that, but the generic rock bands are so much heavier than rock of our era.  Imagine what our friends would have thought of Linkin Park back in 1985.  Or more entertaining would be to play some Motionless in White or Asking Alexandria. </p>

  <p>I could go on, but I have to get ready for a barbecue.  I look forward to your thoughts.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I got lucky with Iron Maiden’s <em>Piece of Mind</em>, and Judas Priest didn’t release an album in 1983. The incredible <em>Screaming for Vengeance</em> came out in 1982, and was followed by the less incredible <em>Defenders of the Faith</em> in 1984. Omitting Dio’s <em>Holy Diver</em>, however, was my worst nightmare–That album is pure fantasy metal and has been unbelievably influential. I bet millions of kids around the world played that cassette to death in the eighties just like I did.</p>

<p>Mike always had a soft spot for Quiet Riot that I still don’t understand. After these lyrics, how can anyone take this band seriously?</p>

<pre><code>Cum on feel the noize
Girls rock your boys
We'll get wild, wild, wild
Wild, wild, wild
</code></pre>

<p>But Mike is right–Quiet Riot were pop metal and they were the first metal band to have the number one album in the country. It’s a shame it had to be them.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/hv-def-leppard.jpg"></p>

<p>I thought long and hard about including “Pyromania” on my list, but at the end of the day I decided Def Leppard was a hard rock band that happened to have good hair and bad spelling. That said, I loved this album, and they were heavier than most stuff on the radio at the time. I killed this cassette too.</p>

<p>As for mainstreaming of heavy music, Mike’s experience in Southern California couldn’t be more different from mine in New Haven, CT. Until Mike’s email, I’d never even heard of Motionless in White or Asking Alexandria, let alone heard them on the radio. My choices are country, classic rock, hip hop, or tween pop. The heaviest it gets is old Van Halen and AC/DC. If you want metal around here, you’ve got to go looking pretty far away from the main stream. Luckily, there’s <a href="http://orgtheory.wordpress.com/2014/03/10/world-wide-heavy-metal/">plenty out there</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dokken versus the World]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/02/dokken-versus-the-world/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/02/dokken-versus-the-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-dokken.jpg"></p>

<p>I love Dokken and I know <a href="http://cvcomics.com/requiem/?p=26">I’m not alone</a>. George Lynch is an amazing guitarist, and Don Dokken has a perfect hair metal voice. They really are the musician’s hair metal band. But even I have to admit that Dokken was not the most original band in the world. For years, it bugged me that their song “Tooth and Nail” ripped off Foreigner’s “Tooth and Nail”. And just recently I realized that <em>many</em> of their songs share titles with other big eighties (or late seventies) songs. In a few cases, Dokken came first, but with most, Dokken looks more like the inspired party than the inspiration. I thought it would be fun to explore when Dokken’s song was better (or worse) with a little head-to-head competition.</p>

<!--more-->

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/uttV1VZUgQQ?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/SrOMVKH8GT4?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091173.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091173/">1. Erasure vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 1.
Erasure, (Break these) "Chains of Love", 1988
Dokken, "Breaking the Chains", 1981
-->

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/t1_5eRtDvAM?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/XFDDjXfAD5Q?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091180.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091180/">2. Foreigner vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 2.
Foreigner, "Tooth and Nail", 1984
Dokken, "Tooth and Nail", 1984
-->

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/yq3Ad3vGG1w?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/ECr98ZOnsig?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091184.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091184/">3. JoBoxers vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 3.
JoBoxers, "Just Got Lucky", 1982
Dokken, "Just Got Lucky, 1984
-->

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/1Cw1ng75KP0?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/1YAjQYJ7PVs?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091187.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091187/">Heart vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 4.
Heart, "Alone", 1987
Dokken, "Alone Again", 1984
-->

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/IivGqwQvdCI?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/L7Yno5p2D30?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091189.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091189/">5. Debbie Gibson vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 5.
Debbie Gibson, "Only in My Dreams", 1986
Dokken, "In My Dreams", 1985
-->

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/iUODdPpnxcA?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/glkmflBYf64?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091194.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091194/">6. Paul Simon vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 6.
Paul Simon, "Slip Slidin' Away", 1977
Dokken, "Slippin' Away", 1985
-->

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/C-TSvxZ40RQ?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/MKF5R8doqDE?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091195.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091195/">7. Aerosmith vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 7.
Aerosmith, "Lightning Strikes", 1982
Dokken, "Lightnin' Strikes Again", 1985
-->

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/3MG1YaMq0Tk?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/XPTFqVluR3A?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091196.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091196/">8. Thompson Twins vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 8.
Thompson Twins, "Lies", 1982
Dokken, "Don't Lie to Me", 1985
-->

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/pAgnJDJN4VA?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/siBW8NgcEGI?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091199.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091199/">9. AC/DC vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 9.
AC/DC, "Back in Black", 1980
Dokken, "Back for the Attack", 1985
-->
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Irish Pride]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/26/irish-pride/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/26/irish-pride</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://cvcomics.com/requiem/?p=691"><img src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-primordial.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>I grew up outside Boston surrounded by Irish-American kids named Sully and Patrick. Even though my last name was McKee, I was different. I was told that my ancestors were MacKays from Scotland who migrated to Ireland and changed their name to McKee to avoid discrimination. I read Scottish folk tales, fantasized about competing in the Highland Games, and seriously considered getting a kilt. I tracked down my tartan, and as a young adult toured Scottish castles and got lost in the moors on my mountain bike. I know this sounds ridiculous coming from a suburban American kid, but Scotland felt like home.
<!--more-->
Then when I was about 30 I told my dad this story and he just laughed. It turns out while one of my distant relatives was indeed Scottish, the rest of his side of the family was full-blooded Irish. I couldn’t believe it. I like U2’s early work as much as the next guy, but suddenly I was supposed to embrace St. Patrick’s Day, leprechauns, and the color green? </p>

<p>In the years since, I’ve tried to have an open mind and learn more about my new homeland. It hasn’t come naturally, but I am happy to report that I’ve found a band that seems to have kindled a little bit of Irish pride in me. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primordial_(band)">Primordial</a> was founded in 1987 near Dublin and has released seven albums that are an incredible mixture of epic black metal and Irish folk music. While the instruments are not traditional, many of the melodies are. The lyrics range from wild fantasy to Irish history. The singer (Alan Averil) is amazing–you feel exactly what he’s feeling.</p>

<p>I found Primordial through the <a href="http://cvcomics.com/requiem">Requiem Metal Podcast</a> where you can listen to a <a href="http://cvcomics.com/requiem/?p=691">two</a> <a href="http://cvcomics.com/requiem/?p=704">part</a> episode about the band and hear several of their songs. They have truly unique sound that really speaks to me. Maybe I’ll wear green tomorrow.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crucial Years in Metal: 1983]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/18/crucial-years-in-metal-1983/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/18/crucial-years-in-metal-1983</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-shout-at-the-devil.jpg"></p>

<p>Late at night, as I putter around the house folding laundry or washing dishes or putting away toys, I often listen to podcasts. Most are mainstream. For sports, I listen to the <a href="http://sports.espn.go.com/espnradio/podcast/archive?id=2864045">BS Report</a> and <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/grantland-nfl-podcast/id730254718?mt=2">Grantland NFL</a>; for tech stuff, I listen to <a href="http://atp.fm">Accidental Tech Podcast</a> and <a href="http://www.macpowerusers.com">Mac Power Users</a>; and for real life, I like <a href="http://www.thisamericanlife.org">This American Life</a> and <a href="http://dadsbeingdads.net">Dads Being Dads</a>.</p>

<p>My current favorite podcast, however, is not mainstream. The <a href="http://cvcomics.com/requiem/">Requiem Metal Podcast</a> features two guys (Mark Rudolph and Jason Hundey) playing and talking about their favorite extreme metal. They started broadcasting in 2008 and have since produced 170 episodes. Every one stands on its own and I’ve had great fun digging into their back catalog to learn more about bands like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Immortal_(band)">Immortal</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emperor_(band)">Emperor</a>, and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolt_thrower">Bolt Thrower</a>.</p>

<p>In their lead up to episode 100, they profiled what they considered the 10 most “crucial” years in metal. These are years that had not just great album releases, but albums that had a big impact on the future of the whole heavy metal genre. Even though Mark and Jason were little kids in the 80’s, they definitely appreciate them in hindsight, and their top 10 includes 4 years from the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decade_of_Decadence_81-91">decade</a>: 1984 (#5), 1985 (#10), 1988 (#9), and 1989 (#1).</p>

<p>I attended high school from 1982 to 1986 and listened to a tremendous amount of metal during that time. I started with hard rock, moved into glam/hair, expanded into classic metal, and loved exploring thrash and the beginnings of extreme metal. My friend Mike and I used to hang out at our local independent record store (Rockin’ Mania) and flip through whatever new (not <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nu_metal">Nü</a>) metal came in each week. If the cover looked interesting one of us (usually Mike) would buy it. That’s how we discovered Metallica’s <em>Ride the Lightning</em>, Mercyful Fate’s <em>Don’t Break the Oath</em>, and the amazing Best of Metal Blade compilation albums.</p>

<p>I know I’m biased because 1983 was a particularly crucial year in metal for me, but three very important albums in the history of metal did come out that year:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><em>Kill em all</em> (Metallica). This was the first album by the biggest metal band of all time. It’s not as good as their next two, but it’s one of the first pure thrash records and it rocks.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em>Shout at the Devil</em> (Motley Crüe) I still remember seeing the album cover in a mall with my mom and being simultaneously scared, repulsed and intrigued. The <a href="http://www.darklyrics.com/lyrics/motleycrue/shoutatthedevil.html#1">first song on the album</a> is a weird Satanic-ish sermon (that I can still quote verbatim) and the music is surprisingly heavy for people who think of the Crüe as that band who sang “Girls Girls Girls” and “Home Sweet Home”. For tons of kids like me, this album was a powerful gateway into the world of real metal. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em>Melissa</em> (Mercyful Fate) Many people have written about how influential this band was on the development of the black metal genre, and extreme metal in general, but on the podcast, Mark often disparages Mercyful Fate by calling them “goofy” or “circus metal”. I’m here to tell you it didn’t come off that way <strong>at all</strong> back in the day. When my friend Mike bought their second album (<em>Don’t Break the Oath</em>) on a whim, we were completely creeped out the first time he played it. We just didn’t know what to do with the blasphemous lyrics, shreiking vocals, and unbelievably catchy guitar work. I had a copy on cassette which I ended up listening to a few times and then throwing in the trash. Mike did the same thing with his album–it’s like we thought we were destined to burn in hell if we kept them. Now, a little older and wiser we can appreciate the music and laugh at the lyrics. <em>Melissa</em>, their first album, isn’t as good as <em>Don’t Break the Oath</em>, but you can’t have a second without a first.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>After high school, I moved away from home and away from metal. When hair metal disappeared from the radio, I thought metal itself  had died. In the late 1990’s and early 2000’s I knew Nü Metal was a thing, but only dabbled a bit with bands like Korn, Disturbed, and even Linkin Park. Later in the 2000’s I learned that music called black metal and death metal existed, but extreme metal can be an acquired taste and I just wasn’t ready. Now, with Mark and Jason’s help, I’m really enjoying filling in the huge gaps in my metal education.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Black metal for kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/04/black-metal-for-kids/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/04/black-metal-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Black metal is nasty stuff. Most of it revolves around Satanic imagery, shreiking vocals and guitars, incredibly fast “blast beat” drums, and spooky low fi production. Most bands hail from Scandinavia, and in the mid 90’s the nastiness reached a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lords-Chaos-Satanic-Underground-Edition/dp/0922915946">particularly nasty level</a> as bands competed with each other to see who was the most evil by burning churches and murdering each other. And yet, I really appreciate the dark moodiness and musicality.</p>

<p>You can imagine my surprise when I found an honest-to-goodness Norwegian black metal band that is perfect for kids and adults. Now, whenever we get in the car, my two year old requests their music and proceeds to laugh and sing along! How did this happen? A confluence of two amazing things.</p>

<p>As I’ve already reported, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/21/fun-and-games-at-the-library/">my girls love the Rainbow Magic books</a>. While the heros are Kirsty, Rachel, and the fairies, the villains are Jack Frost and the goblins. Their home is an icy castle north of Fairy Land and they are frankly hilarious. The goblins call each other names, trip over each other, and are some of the least scary “monsters” you’ll ever meet. I remember in one book Rachel and Kirsty got their way by tickling the goblins.</p>

<p>The band <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Immortal_(band)">Immortal</a> has been recording black metal since before their first full-length release: <em>Diabolical Fullmoon Mysticism</em> in 1992. Their music is classic black metal, but many of their songs simply describe frigid mountains and the grumpy king who reigns over them. B’s favorite song is “Mountains of Might.” It starts with organ which B says is “carousel music” and contains vocals which she calls “a goblin talking:”</p>

<pre><code>The storm is getting colder
In a place of the frozen sun
Alone on the mountainside
Breathing the clearest winds
The winds are everblowing
Blowing off the glaciers
Snow descend of the valley
Into the high impassable drifts
So rightly I am watching
These mountains that I know
Forever standing here
These mountains northern face
Mountains of might
Mountains of might
Mountains of might
Icicled peeks as far as the eye can see
I will reign this place alone
Cold winds blew into the valley wall
Snow was deeper there
The storm is getting colder
In a place of the frozen sun
Alone on the mountainside
Breathing the clearest winds
Mountains of might
Mountains of might
Mountains of might
</code></pre>

<p>The acoustic break in the middle is when “the goblins are dancing.” The whole album (<em>Blizzard Beasts</em>) is recorded with the vocals mixed extra loud so they don’t get lost. My favorite part is how Abbath (the lead singer) pronounces glaciers as “glaysseers”. The <a href="http://www.metrolyrics.com/antarctica-lyrics-immortal.html">lyrics of “Antarctica”</a> (from <em>Sons of Northern Darkness</em>) are similarly child-friendly and the music is similarly goblin-friendly.</p>

<p>The only downside to Immortal for kids is common to all heavy metal: the terribly inappropriate music videos. Immortal follows black metal tradition and performs in corpse paint while making lots of scary faces. They also seem to love weird spiked bondage gear. They look ridiculous and I try to avoid <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-VBdAY8eA9w">their videos</a> too. It doesn’t have to be this way. Consider the video below to be my small contribution to making the world a better place:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/tGXN58iZH5k" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>If you are excited to try and get your kids into other metal subgenres, make sure and check out <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/24/heavy-metal-for-kids/">my earlier post on this subject</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
