<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-04T23:19:33-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Black metal for kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/04/black-metal-for-kids/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/04/black-metal-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Black metal is nasty stuff. Most of it revolves around Satanic imagery, shreiking vocals and guitars, incredibly fast “blast beat” drums, and spooky low fi production. Most bands hail from Scandinavia, and in the mid 90’s the nastiness reached a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lords-Chaos-Satanic-Underground-Edition/dp/0922915946">particularly nasty level</a> as bands competed with each other to see who was the most evil by burning churches and murdering each other. And yet, I really appreciate the dark moodiness and musicality.</p>

<p>You can imagine my surprise when I found an honest-to-goodness Norwegian black metal band that is perfect for kids and adults. Now, whenever we get in the car, my two year old requests their music and proceeds to laugh and sing along! How did this happen? A confluence of two amazing things.</p>

<p>As I’ve already reported, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/21/fun-and-games-at-the-library/">my girls love the Rainbow Magic books</a>. While the heros are Kirsty, Rachel, and the fairies, the villains are Jack Frost and the goblins. Their home is an icy castle north of Fairy Land and they are frankly hilarious. The goblins call each other names, trip over each other, and are some of the least scary “monsters” you’ll ever meet. I remember in one book Rachel and Kirsty got their way by tickling the goblins.</p>

<p>The band <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Immortal_(band)">Immortal</a> has been recording black metal since before their first full-length release: <em>Diabolical Fullmoon Mysticism</em> in 1992. Their music is classic black metal, but many of their songs simply describe frigid mountains and the grumpy king who reigns over them. B’s favorite song is “Mountains of Might.” It starts with organ which B says is “carousel music” and contains vocals which she calls “a goblin talking:”</p>

<pre><code>The storm is getting colder
In a place of the frozen sun
Alone on the mountainside
Breathing the clearest winds
The winds are everblowing
Blowing off the glaciers
Snow descend of the valley
Into the high impassable drifts
So rightly I am watching
These mountains that I know
Forever standing here
These mountains northern face
Mountains of might
Mountains of might
Mountains of might
Icicled peeks as far as the eye can see
I will reign this place alone
Cold winds blew into the valley wall
Snow was deeper there
The storm is getting colder
In a place of the frozen sun
Alone on the mountainside
Breathing the clearest winds
Mountains of might
Mountains of might
Mountains of might
</code></pre>

<p>The acoustic break in the middle is when “the goblins are dancing.” The whole album (<em>Blizzard Beasts</em>) is recorded with the vocals mixed extra loud so they don’t get lost. My favorite part is how Abbath (the lead singer) pronounces glaciers as “glaysseers”. The <a href="http://www.metrolyrics.com/antarctica-lyrics-immortal.html">lyrics of “Antarctica”</a> (from <em>Sons of Northern Darkness</em>) are similarly child-friendly and the music is similarly goblin-friendly.</p>

<p>The only downside to Immortal for kids is common to all heavy metal: the terribly inappropriate music videos. Immortal follows black metal tradition and performs in corpse paint while making lots of scary faces. They also seem to love weird spiked bondage gear. They look ridiculous and I try to avoid <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-VBdAY8eA9w">their videos</a> too. It doesn’t have to be this way. Consider the video below to be my small contribution to making the world a better place:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/tGXN58iZH5k" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>If you are excited to try and get your kids into other metal subgenres, make sure and check out <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/24/heavy-metal-for-kids/">my earlier post on this subject</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Extreme Bird Watching]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/02/extreme-bird-watching/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/02/extreme-bird-watching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-dead-fish.jpg" /></p>

<p>Spring has finally arrived in Connecticut. The snow is gone, replaced by snowdrops and crocuses, and the birds have returned. We&rsquo;ve had great fun watching robins, bluejays, and red-winged blackbirds pulling on worms and building nests, and hearing their songs fill the air. </p>

<p>On the way home from school the other day we got an extra-special treat. As we drove by the reservoir, two hawks<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> flew over the car fighting over something. The birds were big and their prey was big too. The hawks dipped and dove and then lost control of their prize, letting it fall right into the street in front of us. </p>

<p>When it bounced and rolled to a stop we saw it was a huge fish!  The whole rest of our trip home we wondered if the fish would still be there the next day and since it was a pretty busy street, hoped we wouldn&rsquo;t see a road-killed hawk (or two) lying near by.</p>

<p>The next morning we were never so happy to see a dead fish all alone by the side of the road. We had to pull over so everyone could get out to take a closer look. Whoever said bird watching was boring?</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Maybe they were ospreys, but we get a lot of red-tailed hawks around here and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red-tailed_Hawk#Diet">Wikipedia</a> says they do occasionally eat fish.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fun and Games at the Library]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/21/fun-and-games-at-the-library/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/21/fun-and-games-at-the-library</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-alphabet-rug.jpg" /></p>

<p>Consumption, analysis, and <a href="http://randsinrepose.com/archives/the-builders-high/">creation</a>. A lot of my time can be assigned to one of these three categories, and while all three have their place, I find it very easy to slouch into consumption and shirk creation. I feel better about myself when I&rsquo;m in balance, so I&rsquo;m always looking for opportunities to make things. That&rsquo;s one reason the girls and I have been making up so <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/12/pretty-pretty-princess/">many</a> <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/21/non-violent-dungeons-and-dragons-for-kids/">new</a> <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/17/sequence-for-kids/">games</a> lately. </p>

<p>Our trips to the library have always been more than simply dropping off and picking up bags of books. We like to take our time and hang out too. These are our three favorite games to play while we&rsquo;re there:</p>

<p><strong>1. The Rug Game:</strong> The main branch of the New Haven Free Public Library has a huge children&rsquo;s room and in the middle is a big circular rug with the alphabet and associated pictures printed around the edge. Since R was little we&rsquo;ve played a game where I tell her to find something and she has to run to an appropriate letter. We started with the basics:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Run to the octopus!</li>
  <li>Where is the dog?</li>
  <li>Find the birthday cake!</li>
</ul>

<p>We moved on to more tricky questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What keeps you dry in the rain? (Umbrella)</li>
  <li>Who has 8 arms? (Octopus)</li>
  <li>Find a red fruit! (Apple)</li>
</ul>

<p>When other kids join in, the questions have to have at least two correct answers so everyone can find their own letter:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Who swims in the water? (Fish, octopus, turtle)</li>
  <li>Find a fun toy! (yoyo, kite)</li>
  <li>What has a shell? (Turtle, egg)</li>
</ul>

<p>As the kids get older, the questions get downright tricky:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What rhymes with cry? (Pie)</li>
  <li>Who has a princess for a daughter? (Queen)</li>
  <li>Who is black and white? (Zebra)</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>2. Rainbow Magic:</strong> R is currently obsessed with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rainbow_Magic">this series</a> of beginning chapter books. They are formulaic in the same way <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dora_the_Explorer">Dora and Boots</a> are formulaic beginning readers and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hardy_Boys">The Hardy Boys</a> are formulaic tween boy schlock. The books come in sets of seven (e.g. <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0545175178/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0545175178&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=highvari-20">The Pet Fairies</a>) and each book involves two girls (Rachel and Kirsty) helping a particular fairy retrieve some magic item before Jack Frost and/or his goblins can get it. The books are quite harmless, and the thing is kids <em>like</em> formula&ndash;figuring it out is like solving a puzzle. B is not so into the stories yet, but she&rsquo;s been swept up in R&rsquo;s enthusiasm, and at the library she loves to gather up a big pile of the books, pore over the covers, and flip for pictures of goblins. We recently made up a game where she files her books by the first letter of the fairy&rsquo;s name on the alphabet rug. Fun and even a little educational!</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-picture-book-scavenger-hunt.jpg" /></p>

<p><strong>3. Picture Book Scavenger Hunt:</strong> This is a game I&rsquo;ve been trying to get the girls excited about for years, and during our last library outing it finally took hold. I made a list of animals, characters and objects, and the girls had to find a picture of each in a book. We settled in between two big shelves and started digging. It was surprisingly difficult&ndash;I would have told you that a third of all picture books contain princesses, fairies, pirates, and dogs. It turns out dogs are easy to find, but everything else took a little hunting. </p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve written a lot recently about games we&rsquo;ve made up and had a good time playing. I hope some of you are inspired to try a few out. I hope even more that you are inspired to create your own games. That&rsquo;s the most fun of all.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pretty Pretty Princess!]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/12/pretty-pretty-princess/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/12/pretty-pretty-princess</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-pretty-pretty-princess.jpg" /></p>

<p>I was talking to one of R&rsquo;s former pre-school teachers the other day, and she mentioned a board game she used to play with her daughter and husband called <em>Pretty Pretty Princess</em>. It involved moving pieces around the board (ala Candy Land) and collecting real jewelry that you get to wear. You win when you put on the tiara and shout out &ldquo;I&rsquo;m a Pretty Pretty Princess!&rdquo; My first thought was that both of my girls would love this game and I should look for it on Amazon as soon as possible.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> My second thought was that we already owned most of the parts and it would be even more fun to make the game ourselves.</p>

<p>We started by rolling out a big piece of paper and taping it to the dining room table. I drew a winding track and divided it into spaces. The girls went to town with their markers and drew bracelets, necklaces, rings, and earrings all over the board while I tracked down some dice (<a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/21/non-violent-dungeons-and-dragons-for-kids/">not hard</a>) and our tiaras. We selected our game pieces from our bag of <a href="http://www.schleich-s.com/en/US/toys/">Schleich animals</a> and My Little Ponies, grabbed our kids&rsquo; jewelry box, and started playing.</p>

<p>Rolling the dice and moving her piece the right number of spaces were challenges for B (not quite three years old), but picking jewelry out of the box made it all worthwhile. R enjoyed the game even though the pace was a little bit slow. We&rsquo;ll play this version a few more times, but I&rsquo;m already looking forward to making it more complicated by adding forks in the road, special squares, and some weird rules. </p>

<p><strong>Footnotes:</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I did eventually look up <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00000IWHP/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B00000IWHP&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=highvari-20">the game on Amazon</a> and it doesn&rsquo;t look any more fun than our homemade version.  And holy mackerel, it&rsquo;s $99!<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Economics and Data Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/09/economics-and-data-analysis/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/09/economics-and-data-analysis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We live in a world where more and more people and organizations make <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Super-Crunchers-Why-Thinking-By-Numbers-Smart/dp/0553384732">decisions based on data</a>. These include business decisions, policy-making decisions, and even many personal decisions. <a href="http://www.quora.com/Google/What-do-economists-do-at-Google-their-responsibilities-as-Googles-employees">Google employs hundreds of quantitative analysts</a> to analyze auctions, forecast revenue, predict customer needs, and surely lots of other things we don’t know about. A good friend of mine just spent the last month carefully analyzing student loan data for the <a href="http://www.federalreserve.gov">Federal Reserve</a>. I even just read about a guy who <a href="http://www.wired.com/wiredscience/2014/01/how-to-hack-okcupid/all/">scraped dating data from OK Cupid</a> to find himself a wife.</p>

<p>Business and the government often look to economists to do this kind of data analysis for two main reasons. First, economists have been using data to answer questions about optimal behavior for a long time and have developed a set of statistical methods tuned for these problems that we call <em>econometrics</em>. These tools are particularly applicable to the non-experimental (aka “observational”) data that is piling up all around us. The second reason is that economists are good at thinking mathematically about human behavior and markets–two concepts at the heart of many important questions. </p>

<p>I am constantly telling my undergraduate students to take as many classes on econometrics, statistics, and/or data analysis as they can.  Only one semester of statistics/econometrics is required to get a bachelor’s degree in economics at Yale, and this introductory course covers the basics of probability, statistical inference, and linear regression.  The payoff to taking the second class is huge–that’s where students actually gain proficiency with elementary methods and build up to important methods like instrumental variables and difference-in-differences that can separate causation from correlation.</p>

<p>I recently did an informal survey of ten top-tier economics departments and learned that seven of the ten now require two semesters (or quarters) of statistics and/or econometrics.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> I will be shocked if in five years it’s not at least nine out of ten. Even now, many advanced applied elective courses teach statistical methods so that students can understand (and contribute to) the research they read.</p>

<p>At the beginning of my last semester in college I had a conversation with a fellow senior that has really stuck with me. He went on and on about how excited he was to be taking Econ 101. At least part of his logic was that he didn’t want to graduate without knowing something about the economy. I had not taken any economics up to this point and had no idea what he was talking about. I didn’t get it at all. Now I do. Economics training gives people tools for understanding how the world works. That training needs to keep up with our increasingly data-driven world.</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes:</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Harvard, MIT, Berkeley, Brown, Penn, and Duke require their economics majors to take two semesters of econometrics and/or statistics. Stanford requires two quarters. Yale, Amherst, and Princeton require one semester. Yale also offers an Econ/Math degree that requires two semesters of econometrics.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't Throw Them to the Wolves]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/04/thrown-to-the-wolves/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/03/04/thrown-to-the-wolves</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-wolfpack.jpeg" /></p>

<p>I recently heard <a href="http://bbs.yale.edu/people/michael_koelle-1.profile">Michael Koelle</a> (Associate Professor of Molecular Biophysics and Biochemistry at Yale) give a very interesting <a href="http://teaching.yale.edu/programs/faculty/award-winning-teachers-teaching-lunchtime-colloquia">presentation on teaching</a>. He led by saying he wasn&rsquo;t going to talk about anything trendy like MOOC&rsquo;s or flipping the classroom or project-based learning, but would instead focus on how how he teaches traditional big lecture courses. He proceeded to tell us about the most progressive lecture courses I&rsquo;ve ever heard of. Among other things, he never lectures for more than 15 minutes at a time and peppers his classes with interactivity and small group exercises. While his whole talk was inspiring and full of concrete advice and ideas, I want to write today about something he brought up almost in passing.</p>

<p>Professor Koehlle&rsquo;s department introduces junior faculty to teaching big lectures by having them co-teach with someone senior the first few times. The junior sees first-hand what goes into a good lecture, learns the nuts and bolts with a safety net, and has someone right there who can answer questions and critique individual classes. What a great model! </p>

<p>The far more common practice is to throw junior faculty to the wolves in a big course. If you happen to be a natural or are willing to invest far more than makes sense for someone hoping to get tenure, it might result in a decent class. More often than not, it&rsquo;s a train wreck. It occurs to me that while many departments can&rsquo;t afford to have two faculty teaching their big classes, there are other (cheaper) ways to mentor juniors:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Have experienced senior faculty pay attention to juniors while they are teaching a challenging class for the first time. That means observing lectures, having lunch meetings about how things are going, and encouraging juniors to ask questions about teaching.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When a junior takes over an existing class, give them as much of the previous instructor&rsquo;s materials as possible. Lecture slides are a start, but notes, problem sets and old exams are also helpful. If the department has <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/13/course-materials/">ownership of the materials</a>, this is easy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Let juniors get their first teaching experience in a high-level class. It sounds weird to people outside academia, but the more advanced classes are much easier to teach. The students in these classes are more bought into the discipline&rsquo;s norms, and the material is closer to what the instructor works on every day while doing their research. Introductory classes need to be far more polished and have a much more diverse group of students. I love diversity but it&rsquo;s a lot harder to teach. Electives are easiest of all because every student in the class wants to be there.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Exploit university resources outside the department for helping teachers. At Yale, the <a href="http://teaching.yale.edu">Yale Teaching Center</a> will help instructors learn from their evaluations, review syllabi, and even do classroom observation. Letting faculty know about these services is a nice first step, but my experience is that only the above average teachers take advantage of them. It should be mandatory for all juniors (and probably seniors too).</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Junior faculty in top departments are evaluated for promotion based on their research productivity. Mentoring is a way to improve their teaching without having to take time away from their research. In fact, there are techniques many juniors don&rsquo;t know that will <em>save</em> them time spent teaching. Starting with high-quality course materials means less time preparing class. Clearer lectures mean fewer confused students visiting during office hours. A better match between lecture content and exam content means fewer irate student emails.</p>

<p>If a department is serious about upgrading the quality of its undergraduate instruction, doing a better job of mentoring junior faculty is low hanging fruit. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Little Pony: Revelation]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/02/27/mlp-revelations/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/02/27/mlp-revelations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a rough winter filled with snow days and sickness and not enough sleep. Tonight the wind is howling and the temperature is supposed to drop to the single digits. To get us in the mood for spring, the girls and I hunkered down in front of YouTube to hear Twilight Sparkle and the rest of the My Little Ponies sing “Winter Wrap-up”.</p>

<!--- My Little Pony: "Winter Wrap-up
--->
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/dyrAkwJ6WsY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>In the video, the ponies are also tired of winter and are preparing for spring. Actually, scratch that, they aren’t getting ready for spring–they have decided it’s time for spring and they are physically bringing it into being. The Pegasus ponies are annihilating the storm clouds and removing the snow from roofs and trees. Apple Jack and the other earth ponies are plowing the snow off the fields and lakes, and planting seeds. Fluttershy is waking up all the hibernating animals with a little bell. That’s when it hit me: These ponies are not mere cartoon characters at all–They’re gods!</p>

<p>The rulers of Equestria (Princess Celestia and Princess Luna) are obviously the old gods of the Sun and Moon. I’m surprised they aren’t named Princess <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ra">Ra</a> and Princess <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khonsu">Khonsu</a>. It also turns out each of the <a href="http://mlp.wikia.com/wiki/Characters#Main_characters">Mane Six</a> ponies has a clear analog in Greek mythology:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Twilight Sparkle is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Athena">Athena</a>, Goddess of Wisdom. </li>
  <li>Pinkie Pie is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dionysus">Dionysus</a>, God of ritual madness and ecstasy–aka partying.</li>
  <li>Rainbow Dash is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hermes">Hermes</a>–the winged messenger of the gods who is quick and cunning and patron of athletics and sports.</li>
  <li>Apple Jack is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demeter">Demeter</a>, Goddess of the Harvest.</li>
  <li>Rarity is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aphrodite">Aphrodite</a>, Goddess of Beauty and Love.</li>
  <li>Fluttershy is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artemis">Artemis</a>, Protector of the Animals.</li>
</ul>

<p>I think spring had better come soon before I go completely insane.</p>

<p>Hurry up ponies!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Three Pieces of Stat Nerd Trivia]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/02/14/stat-nerd-trivia/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/02/14/stat-nerd-trivia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve recently learned three bits of trivia that only a statistics nerd could love. They won’t help you think deeply about data. They won’t help you analyze data. In fact, they’ll probably push useful knowledge out of your head and make you dumber. Read further at your own risk.</p>

<p><strong>1. Where does the word “logit” come from?</strong></p>

<p>One of the earliest probablistic models of a binary process is the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Probit">probit</a>. It was developed by Chester Bliss in 1934, and in this paper he coined the term as a shortening of the phrase “probability unit”. The idea is that a one unit increase in an independent variable changes the probability of the outcome occurring by a constant number of probability units. Probits can be translated into actual probabilities using a particular non-linear transformation: the cumulative distribution function of the standard normal. That is, we have:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\Pr(y_i) = \Phi(\beta_0 + \beta_1 x_i)
</script>

<p>In 1944, Joseph Berkson developed a similar model that also mapped the real line to the (0,1) interval, this time using the logistic function:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\Pr(y_i) = \frac{\exp(\beta_0 + \beta_1 x_i)}{1 + \exp(\beta_0 + \beta_1 x_i)}
</script>

<p>By analogy, this model was given the name logit.</p>

<p><strong>2. Why does Stata store dates as the number of days since January 1, 1960?</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://www.dur.ac.uk/geography/staff/geogstaffhidden/?id=335">Nick Cox</a> knows a lot about <a href="http://www.stata.com">Stata</a>, and even he does not know exactly why this date was chosen as the origin for internal dates. His <a href="http://www.stata.com/statalist/archive/2003-08/msg00379.html">best guess</a> is that it was copied from “some data base or spreadsheet program”. My guess is that Stata copied SAS which uses the same date as the date-time origin. </p>

<p>This led me to wonder why SAS chose the date, and Derek Morgan (in <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=s1h94CZjGCEC&amp;pg=PA2">The Essential Guide to SAS Dates and Times</a>) says “One story has it that the founders of SAS wanted to use the approximate birth date of the IBM 370 system, and they chose January 1, 1960 as an easy-to-remember approximation.” According to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epoch_(reference_date)#Notable_epoch_dates_in_computing">Wikipedia</a> S-Plus also uses the same reference date.</p>

<p><strong>3. How are we supposed to pronounce McNemar’s test?</strong></p>

<p>Suppose you have a set of matched pairs of observations and want to know if the distribution of some categorical outcome is the same for each side of the pair. You should use <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McNemar_test">McNemar’s test</a> to see if the observed differences are statistically significant.
I went years pronouncing <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quinn_McNemar">Quinn McNemar</a>’s name as “mik-nee’-mahr” and getting likely getting laughed at behind my back by biostatisticians. It turns out the <a href="http://www.medilexicon.com/medicaldictionary.php?t=90653">proper pronunciation</a> is “mak’ne-mahr”. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ax265c6pqvA">Ashwini Kalantri</a> pronounces it well as he explains how it works.</p>

<p><strong>Note:</strong> The pretty math equations are rendered with <a href="http://www.mathjax.org">Mathjax</a> and integrating this with Javascript was trivial thanks to <a href="http://www.lucypark.kr/blog/2013/02/25/mathjax-kramdown-and-octopress/">Lucy Park</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Second Blogoversary]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/02/13/my-second-blogoversary/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/02/13/my-second-blogoversary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the past few weeks this blog has achieved two big milestones: December 21 marked the second anniversary of <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2011/12/21/first-post/">my first post</a>, and on December 30, I published my 100th article. To mark the occasion, I thought it would be fun to reflect on the past two years quantitatively.</p>

<p>In <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/22/happy-blogoversary/">2012</a>, I published 54 articles with 29,699 words, and in 2013, I posted 44 articles with 27,938 words–a decline, but not a major one. The average length of an article went up (550 words vs. 635 words) as did the standard deviation of the word count per article (296 words vs. 394 words). The increasing variance on this dimension can be seen visually in these two overlaid histograms:</p>

<p><img src="http://highvariance.net/images/analyze-2014-02-09/wchist.png" /></p>

<p>So is this blog high variance in article length? That’s hard to say without scraping a bunch of other blogs and analyzing the data. <a href="http://mattgemmell.com/how-i-write/">Matt Gemmell</a> says the distribution of his article lengths is bimodal:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When I’m not writing to a count, I have two natural lengths of piece:</p>

  <ul>
    <li>700 to 1,000 words for a compact exposition on a topic. This is also an ideal bite-sized chunk of text for the reader, and fits well on a single page. It’s no coincidence that the majority of commissioned magazine pieces fall into this band.</li>
    <li>2,000 to 3,500 words for a more detailed exploration or discussion.</li>
  </ul>

  <p>The zone between the two is a death march.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I seem to have one natural length, but its range is a bit broader than Matt’s shorter pieces, as only half my articles fall within 369 and 724 words. If you include Matt’s longer pieces, he clearly wears the higher variance crown.</p>

<p>The yearly numbers mask an interesting monthly pattern. While I wrote a little less in 2013, I was more consistent in my output during the year. In both years I started strong, gradually slowed down, and then picked up the pace again in the fall:</p>

<p><img src="http://highvariance.net/images/analyze-2014-02-09/ac.png" />
<img src="http://highvariance.net/images/analyze-2014-02-09/wc.png" /></p>

<p>Most article content seems to have settled into a small set of categories (<a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/categories/tech/">tech</a>, <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/categories/kids/">kids</a>, <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/categories/education/">education</a>, and <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/categories/music/">music</a>. You could even make an argument that you’re reading a mixture of four distinct extremely low-traffic blogs with the occasional off-the-wall post thrown in. The below picture shows article counts by tag for each year for each tag that had more than one article. Many articles are tagged more than one way and every article I’ve published had at least one of the tags shown below. I wrote a bit more about education and Conan in 2013 and a bit less about music, but I’m not sure those trends will continue in 2014.</p>

<p><img src="http://highvariance.net/images/analyze-2014-02-09/tags.png" /></p>

<p>On the demand side, High Variance had 8,504 unique visitors in 2013 (up from 2,017) and 13,809 page views (up from 4,000). Chris Blattmann <a href="http://chrisblattman.com/2013/04/18/links-i-liked-220/">pointed his firehose my way</a> in mid-April, but even if I ignore that week (961 unique visitors and 1,578 page views), readership is still way up for the year.</p>

<p><img src="http://highvariance.net/images/analyze-2014-02-09/traffic-2013.png" /></p>

<p>To celebrate, I’ve made a few minor tweeks to the site. First, I’ve added an <a href="http://ifttt.com">IFTTT</a> rule that tweets every time I post something new. You can follow me at <a href="https://twitter.com/intent/follow?screen_name=HighVarianceNet">HighVarianceNet</a>. Second, I’ve made it easier to share content on the site by adding links for tweeting articles and sharing them on Facebook. Third, I’ve signed up as an <a href="https://affiliate-program.amazon.com/gp/associates/join/landing/main.html">Amazon associate</a>. That means if you follow a link from this site to Amazon and then buy the product, you’ll pay the same price but I’ll get a few cents. Maybe by the end of next year I’ll be able to celebrate with a free cup of coffee.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploiting Irrationality]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/01/30/exploiting-irrationality/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/01/30/exploiting-irrationality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-floss.png" /></p>

<p>When I was growing up, none of the several clocks in the house told the correct time. My mother would set them all between 5 and 30 minutes fast in an effort to fool herself into leaving the house when she was supposed to. I thought this was completely insane. Why not just wake up early enough to do what you needed to do, and then do that? Why play these games with yourself when pure rationality would suffice?</p>

<p>The answer (of course) is that my mother is far from completely rational, and this system worked for her in a way that my proposed system just didn&rsquo;t. And while I like to think that I&rsquo;m not as crazy as my mother, I&rsquo;m not an automaton either. It&rsquo;s taken me a long time to give in to that and start exploiting some of my foibles for good.</p>

<p>A few weeks ago, I read <a href="http://www.macworld.com/article/2085007/the-iphone-habit-apps-that-help-you-keep-your-new-years-resolutions.html">an article</a> by my productivity sensei (<a href="http://macsparky.com">David Sparks</a>) where he recommended an iPhone app called <a href="http://habitlist.com">Habit List</a> for folks trying to kickstart good habits. There&rsquo;s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Habit">some scientific research</a> that says if you can somehow get yourself to do something regularly for a few weeks, it becomes a lot easier to continue doing it. There&rsquo;s also some <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Candy_Crush">evidence</a> that games can be addictive. In a nutshell, Habit List makes doing mundane things into a game. By the time you&rsquo;re bored with the game, the habit has been formed.</p>

<p>Since I installed Habit List, I&rsquo;ve managed to floss every day except one (thanks stomach flu!). My exercise program has been less successful, but that&rsquo;s more the fault of the cold weather and that same stomach flu than a failure of the app. You can bet that I&rsquo;ll be plugging in some more easy-to-ignore-but-good-for-me chores soon.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Complementarities of Literature and Music]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/01/19/complementarities-of-literature-and-music/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/01/19/complementarities-of-literature-and-music</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some things just go well together. I have friends who like to select <a href="http://winefolly.com/tutorial/wine-with-fish-pairing-guide/">just the right wine</a> to go with their meal. Cookies always taste better with <a href="http://www.gotmilk.com">milk</a>. And of course a PB&amp;J sandwich is much better than a plain peanut butter sandwich or a plain jam sandwich. Economists are good at coming up with fancy names for obvious concepts, and we call these <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complementary_good">complementary goods</a>.</p>

<p>Just because I don’t listen to music while I read doesn’t mean this idea can’t be applied to literature and music. Some <a href="http://www.songfacts.com/category-songs_inspired_by_books.php">songs</a> or albums are inspired by good books, and listening to one makes you appreciate the other that much more. Even better is when a musician or band’s work creates a mood that perfectly matches an author’s vision. I’ve recently found the perfect example.</p>

<p>As regular readers of this site know, I am a huge fan of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_E_Howard">Robert E. Howard</a>’s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conan_the_Barbarian">Conan</a> stories. Conan himself is strong, principled, and fun-loving. He does all the things we want to do but are unable to because of either physical, legal, or sometimes moral constraints. To read Conan’s savage adventures is to be immersed in a fantastic and vividly portrayed land of magic and mayhem.</p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amon_Amarth">Amon Amarth</a> is the white wine to Conan’s fish. They are a Swedish <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melodic_death_metal">melodic death metal</a> band whose songs are rich and powerful tales of battles between mortals and gods of the north. The drums, guitars, and vocals are fierce–just like Conan. Listening to their music on headphones is the perfect way to make a winter trip to the grocery store into an epic quest for sustenance. The fact is that words cannot do them justice. I hereby present to you the truly awesome Amon Amarth: </p>

<!--- Amon Amarth, "Twilight of the Thunder God"
--->
<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/mfcTbK-U1YQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Home Music System 3.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/31/home-music-streaming-3/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/31/home-music-streaming-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://daringfireball.net/2013/12/the_year_in_apple_and_technology">John Gruber</a> loves to talk about how technology improves primarily through a series of small steps and the occasional big jump. While the first iPhone was revolutionary, the iPhone 5s is a far better product due to several incremental improvements, none of which got much attention along the way. In the last year, three small things changed in my home music system that make it better than <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/16/home-music-streaming-2/">the last time I wrote about it</a> and a <strong>lot</strong> better than when I <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/02/home-music-streaming/">first wrote about it</a>.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-itunes-radio.jpeg" /></p>

<h2 id="itunes-radio">1. iTunes Radio</h2>

<p>Right after releasing iOS 7, Apple updated it’s Remote app to 4.0. This is the app that lets you control iTunes on your computer from your phone. The main changes to the app were to the user interface–it became “lighter,” with thin fonts and textual buttons, and allowed you to move backwards by grabbing the left side of the screen and swiping. Feature-wise, it wasn’t much different from the previous version. This drove me crazy because iTunes Radio had just been launched and the new Remote app had not yet added support for it.</p>

<p>When iTunes Radio was just a rumor, I wasn’t very interested as it seemed like it would be a simple clone of Pandora. The strange thing is that it <strong>did</strong> turn out to be a straight-forward clone of <a href="http://www.pandora.com">Pandora</a>, but I listened to it much more than I ever listened to Pandora. The integration with the iTunes Store is really nice. iTunes Radio keeps track of all the songs I’ve ever listened to, and with one click I can see a song in the iTunes Store, check out the whole album, and <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/02/06/albums/">maybe even buy it</a>. I also like the stations that are built in–tween pop is pretty good (for the kids, of course) and pop country is well curated too. </p>

<p>Like Pandora, I can pick any artist and iTunes will create a custom radio station for them. Since there’s no Metalcore station built-in, I made a station out of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Killswitch_Engage">Killswitch Engage</a>, the prototypical metalcore band. Unlike Pandora (as far as I can tell), iTunes Radio lets me “tune” the station to play more or less popular tracks by related artists by choosing “Hits,” “Variety,” or “Discovery” mode. And the pretty uncluttered UI in the iOS app is just what you would expect from Apple–definitely nicer than Pandora’s.</p>

<p>In early December, Apple released Remote 4.1 with support for iTunes Radio and now I can stream it all over the house. Remote won’t show my Radio listening history and it’s laggier than I’d like, but I still use it all the time.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-pioneer-a4.jpeg" /></p>

<h2 id="my-new-pioneer-a4">2. My new Pioneer A4</h2>

<p>Lots of folks are perfectly happy playing music on their iPhone and sending it to a nearby speaker with either Bluetooth or a dock. My Airplay-from-a-server set up has several advantages that in my mind outweigh the small amount of added complexity and expense.  Since my phone is only controlling the music and not playing it, it doesn’t use up any power or need to be close by when the music is playing. That means I can wander to the other side of the house with my phone in my pocket and the music doesn’t come crashing to a halt. The sound quality over Airplay is better than over Bluetooth, and I don’t have to store any big music files on my phone–my whole library just sits on the Mac in my office. </p>

<p>My favorite feature of the set up is being able to stream simultaneously to several speakers around the house, and this just got even better as I’ve added a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Pioneer-XW-SMA4-K-Speaker-featuring-Wireless/dp/B00903HKXI">Pioneer A4 Airplay speaker</a> in the basement. The A4 got an amazingly <a href="http://thewirecutter.com/reviews/the-best-airplay-speaker/">positive review</a> in <a href="http://thewirecutter.com">the Wirecutter</a>, and was just $200, even though it sounds like it should cost much more. The set up instructions are horrific, but the set up itself was not so bad. I’m a little perplexed about why Pioneer would discontinue it without an obvious replacement product, but they did. If you have one or manage to get your hands on one, I highly recommend holding the input button down for 3 seconds to turn on Quick Start Mode. This changes the start up time from 35 seconds to under 5 seconds, and while they don’t tell you how much extra power it burns standing by, it’s definitely worth it.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-airfoil.jpeg" /></p>

<h2 id="simplified-configuration-for-spotify">3. Simplified configuration for Spotify</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.rogueamoeba.com/airfoil/">Airfoil</a> is the application on my Mac that grabs output from <a href="https://www.spotify.com/us/">Spotify</a> and sends it to any Airplay destination(s) I choose in the house. When Apple released <a href="http://arstechnica.com/apple/2013/10/os-x-10-9/">Mavericks</a>, the new power management features broke Airfoil. The latest version of Airfoil works around this and also bakes in support for remote control, so I don’t need to run a separate Airfoil helper application anymore. <a href="http://remoteless.no">Remoteless</a>, the iOS app for controlling Spotify on the Mac also released an update recently that supports Airfoil directly, so I no longer need a separate Airfoil remote app on my phone.  The only software programs I need now to play almost any album anywhere in the house are Spotify and Airfoil running on the Mac, and Remoteless on iOS.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PDF Expert 5.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/30/pdf-expert-5/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/30/pdf-expert-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-pdf-expert-5.jpeg" /></p>

<p>More than a year ago I wrote <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/05/16/pdf-annotation-on-the-ipad-in-2012/">a quick review</a> of what I thought were the three best PDF annotation apps on the iPad. The clear winner for my needs was <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/app/id743974925?mt=8&amp;ign-mpt=uo%3D4">PDF Expert</a>. Things haven&rsquo;t changed much since then. <a href="http://brooksreview.net">Ben Brooks</a> just did a <a href="http://thesweetsetup.com/apps/best-pdf-manager-editor-ipad/">super-comprehensive review</a> over at <a href="http://thesweetsetup.com">The Sweet Setup</a>, and the latest version of PDF Expert (5.0) floated to the top. I just upgraded and worked it through its paces grading twenty 15-20 page papers. </p>

<p>All the features PDF Expert had before are still there, and now they all work just a little better. The new annotation toolbar sits on the side taking up very little room. You can have multiple documents open simultaneously in separate tabs. I flipped back and forth between each student&rsquo;s final paper and their graded midterm draft so I could see if how they incorporated my earlier feedback. The synchronization with Dropbox is more reliable than it was&ndash;I used to get the occasional failed sync and 5.0 has been rock solid.</p>

<p>There are lots of new features I haven&rsquo;t even tried yet. The most intriguing is a review mode that let&rsquo;s you edit the text and then transforms those edits into MS Word Track Changes style annotations. If I&rsquo;m working on a document with someone, I would <em>much</em> rather see their changes in a source format (like MS Word) where I can choose to accept or reject the changes. On the other hand, if I&rsquo;m giving heavy-handed feedback to a student on a draft, this might be just the ticket.</p>

<p>My only complaint about 5.0 is ridiculously minor: when I backspace delete in a text box, the text flickers. That&rsquo;s it&ndash;everything else works great. </p>

<p>For the last several months I&rsquo;ve done most of my PDF annotation on the Mac. A big screen and a real keyboard are advantages that are hard to beat. PDF Expert 5.0 has brought me back to the iPad. In portrait mode, I can thumb-type fast enough and the new toolbar is very efficient. With my reading glasses and a 12 point font, my iPad&rsquo;s screen size is fine. It&rsquo;s nice to be able to spend some productive time on my couch again.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conan the Snowman]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/27/conan-the-snowman/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/27/conan-the-snowman</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-conan-the-snowman.jpg" /></p>

<p>Conan the Snowman, was a fierce barbaric soul,<br />
With a sword of steel and a battle cry, total victory was his goal.  </p>

<p>Conan the Snowman, is a fantasy, they say.<br />
He was from far North, but the children know, he raided their village one day.  </p>

<p>There must have been some anger in that well-worn blade he held,<br />
For when he swung it round his head, his enemies they were felled.    </p>

<p>Oh, Conan, the Snowman, was alive as he could be;<br />
and the children say he could laugh and slay,<br />
any man and his family.  </p>

<p>Thumpety thump, thump, thumpety thump, thump,<br />
look at their heads roll. </p>

<p>Thumpety thump, thump, thumpety thump, thump,<br />
vanquishing his foe.  </p>

<p>Conan the Snowman, knew the sun was hot that day,<br />
so he said, &ldquo;Let&rsquo;s fight, all day and all night, until rain washes the blood away.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Raging through the village, with his deadly sword in hand,<br />
Running here and there, all around the square,
sayin&rsquo;, &ldquo;Kill me if you can.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Then he wandered east to a fearsome beast and met it eye to eye.<br />
and only paused a moment, when we heard him scream out, &ldquo;Die!&rdquo;  </p>

<p>For Conan, the Snowman, made all his enemies pay,<br />
But he waved goodbye, sayin&rsquo; &ldquo;You better cry,<br />
I&rsquo;ll be back again some day.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Our Favorite Board Game: Sequence for Kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/17/sequence-for-kids/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/17/sequence-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-sequence-for-kids.jpg" /></p>

<p>With the holidays upon us it seems like every geek blogger I read has been recommending family-friendly board games. <a href="http://macsparky.com/blog/2013boardgames">MacSparky</a> sent me to <a href="http://fannypackmafia.com/blog/2013/12/8/my-favorite-board-games-from-2013-part-one">Fanny Pack Mafia</a>, <a href="http://www.marco.org/2013/12/12/gift-guide-actually-used-for-a-year">Marco</a> says <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0007YDBLE/?tag=marcoorg-20">Power Grid</a> is really good, and <a href="http://kottke.org/13/11/how-to-quickly-get-good-at-chess">Kottke</a> is sending me to <a href="http://www.gautamnarula.com/how-to-get-good-at-chess-fast/">Gautam Narula</a> to improve my chess game. This is all well and good, but these games are a bit much for my 2.5 and 5 year old kids.  Maybe that&rsquo;s why our favorite game hasn&rsquo;t been on any of these lists.</p>

<p>The rules for <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00005UM9P/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B00005UM9P&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=highvari-20">Sequence for Kids</a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=highvari-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B00005UM9P" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
are simple. The game starts with each player getting three cards and a pile of their own colored chips. The cards have animals on them as does the board which is a 6x7 square grid. A turn consists of playing a card and putting one of your chips on a square that has the same animal that was on the card. Players replenish their hand by picking another card from the deck at the end of their turn. The goal is to get four chips in a row. There are two &ldquo;magical&rdquo; animals: The Unicorn card lets a player put their chip on any square while the Dragon card lets a player remove any chip from the board.</p>

<p>Many games for little kids are designed simply to teach rule following and maybe some hand-eye coordination as the player spins a spinner or picks a card and moves their token along a track. Chutes and Ladders and Candyland are the canonical examples of a genre that rots adult brains. Sequence includes enough strategy that kids are challenged, and enough randomness that they have a chance to win against adults.</p>

<p>The set of skills kids can learn (or practice) while playing is surprisingly rich:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Forward thinking:</strong> Players need to make sequences of two before they can make three and then four to win. They need to recognize when their opponent is about to win, and then block them if possible. </li>
  <li><strong>Patience:</strong> Players should save their special cards for when they need them for defense or offense.</li>
  <li><strong>Reasoning about uncertainty:</strong> I wonder if my opponent has a Lion in their hand and could win next turn?  I wonder if I could pick a Lion from the deck for my next turn? Maybe two Lions have already been played and none are left!</li>
  <li><strong>Pattern recognition:</strong> Where are my winning opportunities? Four in a row wins whether it is across, down or diagonal.</li>
  <li><strong>Creativity:</strong> R thinks the magic animals are the best part of the game and we often make up our own rules to create more. Sometimes the Kangaroo card lets you put down a chip on a Kangaroo and another square next to it. Sometimes the Shark can eat another animal and let you put your own chip in its place. The possibilities are endless.</li>
  <li><strong>Reading:</strong> The game even promotes reading in a subtle way. The cards have pictures of the animals for non-readers, words for the animal  (e.g. &ldquo;Penguin&rdquo;) for learning readers, and even a fun name for the animal (e.g., &ldquo;Percy&rdquo;) for actual readers. </li>
</ul>

<p>Perhaps the best part of the game is that it&rsquo;s easy to modify the game for players of any age. We often play with cards face up.  This makes reasoning about your opponent&rsquo;s next move a little clearer and has two other big advantages: Little uncoordinated hands don&rsquo;t have to try to hold three cards at once, and it&rsquo;s a lot easier to teach strategy when you can see what cards your kid is holding.  I&rsquo;ve also played a fairly rule-free version of the game with one and two year-olds where we just deal out cards and place chips on the board. These kids love the animals and the bright colors of the chips and even like matching the animals to the squares on the board. </p>

<p>Sequence for Kids really is fun for the whole family!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Second Time Around]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/16/kid-book-review-second-time-around/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/16/kid-book-review-second-time-around</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the best things about having a second child is getting to do all your favorite little kid things again.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Near the top of that list for me is re-reading our best picture books, and L, at 2.5 years old is just now appreciating the stories as well as the pictures. These five books have been particularly popular over the last few weeks:</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-uncle-elephant.jpg" title="[title &#34;Uncle Elephant&#34;]" alt="[title &#34;Uncle Elephant&#34;]" /></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Uncle-Elephant-Can-Read-Book/dp/0064441040">Uncle Elephant</a> (written and illustrated by Arnold Lobel) Like all of Arnold Lobel’s books, the illustrations are classic, the stories are clever, and the messages are deep. A boy loses his parents at the beginning and he bonds with his Uncle who takes care of him until his parents come back. Among other things, they walk in the garden, sing songs, and grant wishes to spiders. Uncle Elephant is the grandfather everyone wanted when they were growing up. We’ve also been enjoying Lobel’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s?url=search-alias=aps&amp;field-keywords=lobel%20frog%20and%20toad">Frog and Toad stories</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="">Pup and Hound Catch a Thief</a> (written by Susan Hood, illustrated by Linda Hendry) This criminally under-rated series of books is published by Kids Can Press where it gets lost in a slew of mediocre tales of poorly behaved cats (<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mittens-My-First-Can-Read-ebook/dp/B006JQTQNG">Mittens</a>) and dogs (<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Pizza-Sam-Kids-Can-Read/dp/1553373316">Sam</a>). The rhymes and artwork are cute, and the stories have twists at the end that both L and I can appreciate.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img class="left" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-lyle-walks-the-dogs.jpg" title="[title &#34;Lyle Walks the Dogs&#34;]" alt="[title &#34;Lyle Walks the Dogs&#34;]" /></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lyle-Crocodile-Walks-Dogs/dp/B006Z31NI4">Lyle Walks the Dogs</a> (written by Bernard Waber, illustrated by Paulis Waber) Not to be confused with <a href="">Zack’s Alligator</a> Bridget, Lyle the Crocodile is as sweet as Bridget is sassy. In this counting book Lyle builds a business through competent hard work and positive word of mouth.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Curious-George-Rides-Bike-Rey/dp/B0099R035M">Curious George Rides a Bike</a> (written and illustrated by H.A. Rey) My personal favorite George book when I was a kid, I’m happy to report that L loves it too, even if she does admonish George for not wearing a helmet.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-there-are-cats-in-this-book.jpg" title="[title &#34;There are cats in this book&#34;]" alt="[title &#34;There are cats in this book&#34;]" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/There-Are-Cats-This-Book/dp/0763639230">There Are Cats in This Book</a> (written and illustrated by Viviane Schwarz) I’m cheating here since we just discovered this book a month ago at the library, but it’s just so good and so perfect for the two year old age group that I had to include it. It follows in the interactive mode of Herve Tullet’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Press-Here-Herve-Tullet/dp/0811879542">Press Here</a> asking the reader to do things (like toss a ball of yarn or look inside a box) and reacting to them. The only potential downside is that the pop-up features are not totally robust, but isn’t that what Scotch tape is for? I just realized there’s a well-reviewed sequel (<a href="http://www.amazon.com/There-Are-Cats-this-Book/dp/0763649546">There are no cats in this book</a>) and can’t wait to check that out too!</li>
</ul>

<hr />
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>One of the worst things about a second child is having to do all your least favorite things again, but I’m a glass-half-full guy. <a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Photo Management Quest, Part 3: Dropbox and Friends]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/13/pq3-dropbox-and-friends/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/13/pq3-dropbox-and-friends</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(Note: You might want to read my other <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/photo/">posts about photo management</a> for context first.)</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-dropbox.jpg" /></p>

<p>I am extremely happy to report some actual forward progress in this episode of My Photo Management Quest.  The short story is that all my photos now live on Dropbox in a nice hieararchical folder structure where I can browse and share them from any of my computers or iOS devices. My new system isn’t perfect, but it’s pretty good and I think it’s a solid foundation for the future.</p>

<h2 id="moving-from-iphoto-to-dropbox">Moving from iPhoto to Dropbox</h2>

<p>iPhoto is fundamentally an application for doing light editing and organization of photos on a single computer. Any new system that involves access from multiple different devices is going to require getting your photos out of iPhoto’s black box. My first step was to do <a href="http://www.macstories.net/tutorials/moving-from-iphoto-to-dropbox/">what Federico Vittici at MacStories did</a> through a combination of <a href="http://code.google.com/p/phoshare/">PhoShare</a> and <a href="http://www.noodlesoft.com/hazel.php">Hazel</a>.  The process created a set of year folders, and in each of those, a set of month folders that contain all my photos named and sorted by date. I also followed his lead and created a Hazel rule to move files from the Camera Uploads folder (where Dropbox puts my just-taken photos and videos) into my new Photos hierarchy. That means I need do absolutely nothing after I click my iPhone’s shutter button for my photos to be organized and accessible (by me) forever in the cloud. What a breath of fresh air compared to Apple’s Photo Stream!</p>

<p>My photos currently take up about 20GB, and Dropbox charges $99 per 100GB. Give how rock solid Dropbox is and how many iOS apps support it, I think that’s a great deal. </p>

<h2 id="further-organization-and-editing-on-the-mac">Further Organization and Editing on the Mac</h2>

<p>I’ve been manually adding a bit more organization in two ways. First, I’ve split some months into separate events. For example, I created a “2013-10-halloween” folder (inside the “2013” folder) that contains the requisite costume and pumpkin photos. These photos no longer live in the generic “2013-10” folder. I’ve also created a few special folders (e.g., “yummy-things”) outside the date-based hierarchy that have <em>copies</em> of some pictures in the date-based hierarchy.  That way I can find those pictures by date or subject. I can also easily share these folders (read-only) with friends and family using Dropbox shared links. </p>

<p>The best way I’ve found so far to actually create these new folders is Coverflow view in Finder. It’s <a href="https://discussions.apple.com/message/23562534#23562534">buggy in Mavericks</a> and it doesn’t let me see enough at the same time, but it works. I’m sure there are better ways (maybe <a href="http://unboundformac.com">Unbound for Mac</a> when it’s more stable, maybe <a href="http://www.arcsoft.com/photoplus/">Photo+ by Arcsoft</a>, maybe <a href="http://www.lynapp.com">Lyn</a>) but I haven’t settled on one yet.</p>

<p>One of the biggest advantages of having my photos live in the file system is that I’m not locked into iPhoto for editing–I can now use whatever app I want. <a href="http://www.pixelmator.com">Pixelmator</a> is nice and I’m sure I’ll eventually settle on an even lighter weight app for easy stuff (e.g., cropping/red-eye reduction/brightness adjustment).</p>

<h2 id="browsing-on-ios">Browsing on iOS</h2>

<p>Now that my photos live in Dropbox, I have at least three choices of iOS apps to browse them.  The <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/iphoneapp">Dropbox app</a>’s photo tab lets me scroll through thumbnails of all my photos sorted by date and download full resolution versions as needed. I can also browse the folder structure through the standard file browing UI and grab photos, though I don’t get a pretty set of big thumbnails.  Playing videos and sharing links to files and folders is easy.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-heliog.png" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.heliogapp.com">Heliog</a> is fast and pretty–it preserves my folder hierarchy and shows nice screens of thumbnails. I can share folders or sets of photos and easily move photos between folders. The downsides are that it doesn’t play video and I can’t delete photos from the photo view (have to be in the album view). These both seem easily fixable.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-unbound.jpg" /></p>

<p>Right now, I think <a href="http://unboundapp.com">Unbound</a> is the best of the bunch.  Unlike Heliog, it plays videos and let’s me delete photos from the photo view. Like Heliog, sharing Dropbox links is easy and browsing is fast–you can even make the app cache folders for quicker (or offline) access. Unbound will show you all the photo’s EXIF data and even show where a photo was taken on a map. Moving pictures between folders is easy, but I don’t think it’s possible to copy pictures to other albums. It shows me all my folders, but flattens the hierarchy–i.e., my month folders are no longer grouped by year. The ordering is correct, so this isn’t actually so bad.</p>

<h2 id="the-future">The Future</h2>

<p>The next step for my photo management system is to integrate the rest of our family photos. Right now they’re scattered across several computers, folders and hard drives with tons of duplicates. Dropping these photos into my Camera Uploads folder will immediately sort them into my master folder structure, but it won’t remove duplicates. There are lots of apps out there that promise to remove duplicates, but I’m scared to death that they’ll remove too much and the one app I tried (<a href="http://www.duplicatephotofixer.com/PhotoCleaner.aspx">Photos Duplicate Cleaner</a>) didn’t come close to catching everything. </p>

<p>In the early days of the internet, companies like Yahoo tried organizing the web by manually creating big hiearchical lists of sites. Now we just Google for what we want and leave it to racks of servers and fancy algorithms to index it. The same thing has happened to mail. I used to carefully file all my mail into topic-specific folders, but now I just dump it all into one archive folder and rely on search when I need to find something. Photos will eventually be handled the same way. People won’t have to spend gobs of time dividing stacks of photos into events or tagging photos with their friends’ names–that’s what EXIF data and face recognition are for.  Everpix (may they rest in peace) was moving in this direction and I’ve heard <a href="http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2013/12/honan-photography/">great things about what Google+ is doing with pictures</a>. </p>

<p>I am very excited to try some more cutting edge services as they roll out. With our photos safely backed up and accessible on Dropbox, I won’t have to worry about being locked into a deadend or that the service will mess up my photos.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> I’ll have the best of both worlds.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>For the record, Everpix did both: they made export very difficult and compressed photos, losing detail that I might eventually want. <a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Online tech in an in-person seminar: An experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/10/online-tech-in-an-in-person-seminar/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/10/online-tech-in-an-in-person-seminar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve written about <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/05/20/seminars/">how I like to run seminar classes</a> before and you may have noticed that my approach is decidedly low tech. My students read the week’s articles before class and fill out a “worksheet” for each one. Before this semester, the most important question on the worksheet was “What didn’t you understand?” I would look over their answers to identify weak spots that we would  cover in class.</p>

<p>This semester I tried something new: I took “What didn’t you understand?” off the worksheet and asked my students to post questions they had about the reading on a <a href="http://piazza.com">Piazza</a> online discussion forum. If two (or more) students have the same question, only the first has to post it–the others could just mark it as a “good question.” They could also answer each other’s questions and I could “approve” answers or provide my own. I had high hopes for the new system. I thought it would be easier for the students, and would make it easier for me to see what the hot button issues were and even provide some feedback before class. </p>

<p>It didn’t work very well. Even with a fair amount of cajoling during the semester, I would only get 4-5 students (of 24) participating in the forum each week. Based on feedback during the last class, it seems there were three primary reasons. First, it wasn’t clear to many of them that they could post their questions anonymously and they didn’t want to embarrass themselves in front of their fellow students by posting potentially “dumb” questions. Second, several students felt they were done with the assignment after they filled out their worksheets. They didn’t want to take the time to go to the Piazza web site for more work. Third, they didn’t like posting questions that weren’t going to get answered on the forum.</p>

<p>I’m not ready to give up on the idea, but I’m also not sure what to do differently next semester. I can try more cajoling on the first day of class and I can let everyone know that they can post anonymously. I can also commit to answering questions before class. The worksheets and questions are due on Monday night, so that gives me plenty of time before Wednesday’s class to provide at least basic answers. I’m still not sure this will be enough to get mass participation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Three Great Product Features]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/04/three-great-product-features/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/04/three-great-product-features</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Great products get reviewed and talked about, but great features of good products often fly under the radar. They can seem obvious in hindsight or just have a niche group that really appreciates them. Here are three of my favorites that deserve more notice.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-control-center.png" /></p>

<p><strong>1. Control Center</strong></p>

<p>Hands down my favorite new feature of iOS 7, the Control Center removes lots of little dead moments from my life. Every night I lock my phone into portrait mode when I get in bed. I use the flashlight at least twice a day. I select an Airplay destination or use the music controls about twice a day. And in the morning I free up the phone’s orientation again. Since I don’t even have to unlock the phone to do any of this, it saves me at least five seconds each time. That adds up to a minimum of 30 seconds a day and three whole hours a year.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-whispersync.jpg" /></p>

<p><strong>2. Whispersync</strong></p>

<p>After the kids go to sleep and I’m cleaning the kitchen or putting toys away, I like to listen to audiobooks. When it’s particularly gripping, I continue to read the book on my phone in bed using the Kindle app. Whispersync means I automatically pick up right where I left off on the audio. The next night when I start listening again, the Audible app jumps to where I was in the e-book. I can’t imagine too many people take advantage of this, but I love it. </p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-sneeze-shield.jpg" /></p>

<p><strong>3. Sneeze Shield</strong></p>

<p>Maybe our bedroom is dusty. Maybe I have allergies. Maybe I get a lot of low-grade colds. I don’t know why I sneeze a few times almost every morning when I wake up, but I do. And with two little kids, we all get our share of normal-grade colds. This means we go through a lot of tissues. Sneeze Shield means the tissue doesn’t fall apart when a grown up blows into it. I don’t miss handfuls of wet snot at all.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Photo Management Quest, Part 2: Loom]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/29/pq2-loom/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/11/29/pq2-loom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(Note: You might want to read <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/09/im-not-happy/">my first photo management rant</a> and <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/30/pq1-adobe-revel-and-everpix">Part 1</a> for context.)</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-loom.png" /></p>

<p>Ever since
<a href="http://www.theverge.com/2013/11/5/5039216/everpix-life-and-death-inside-the-worlds-best-photo-startup">Everpix went belly up</a>,
photo management has been a common topic on the blogs I read and the
podcasts I listen to. The current
<a href="http://thesweetsetup.com/apps/our-favorite-photo-stream-alternative/">consensus favorite</a>
is <a href="http://www.loom.com">Loom</a> and when I read their feature list I was
pretty excited. They seemlessly sync your iOS Camera Roll and your Mac’s
iPhoto Library with the cloud. Unlike Everpix, they store original files
instead of lossy compressed versions. Unlike Everpix and Adobe Revel,
they store photos AND videos. Their web app lets you browse your photo
collection from anywhere. I loved that you could create and manage
albums of photos from anywhere. Even their pricing ($40/yr for 50GB and
$99/yr for 255GB) was reasonable.</p>

<p>I signed up for the service, and while it took longer than I thought it
should, the iOS app eventually pushed my 300 photo Camera Roll up to the
cloud.  After enjoyably browsing this little collection on my phone,
iPad, and Mac (using the web app), I decided to pony up for a month of 255GB
of storage and try uploading my whole iPhoto library.  I won’t bore you
with the details, but after six days of synchronization hangs, duplicate
photos, and unanswered support email, I gave up.</p>

<p>It’s possible that the problem was just me as I haven’t found anyone
else complaining about Loom synchronization on the web.  My internet
connection’s upload speed is not that great–just 1.5 Mbps–but this is
the first time I’ve had a product give me trouble. Dropbox has been
successfully syncing more than 50 GB of files for about three years now
and I have used BackBlaze to successfully replicate about a terabyte of data.</p>

<p>I found the whole experience rather depressing. The service even on paper
wasn’t perfect. They don’t remove duplicate photos. They don’t offer
even rudimentary editing tools. They won’t stream videos through any of
their apps. They won’t synchronize folders on Windows machines with the
cloud. That said, their feature set was above my bar and they seemed
like they were moving in the right direction.  This time software
quality was the show stopper. </p>

<p>Sigh. The quest continues.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
