<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[High Variance]]></title>
  <subtitle><![CDATA[This is my blog.]]></subtitle>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-08T15:49:33-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Details #IMWAYR]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/12/08/kbr-details/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/12/08/kbr-details</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I was a kid, I liked nothing better then settling down in a corner with a big detailed picture book like <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Richard-Scarrys-Busy-Town/dp/0307168034">Busy, Busy Town</a> and poring over each page looking for things I’d never seen before. My 6-year-old daughter is exactly the same, although the particular books she enjoys are different. Here are three of her favorites:</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-crabtree.jpeg" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Crabtree-Jon-Nichols/dp/1936365820">Crabtree</a> (by Jon and Tucker Nichols, 2013) Alfred Crabtree is a weird dude who loses his false teeth and spends the story searching his belongs for them. This takes a while because he seemingly never throws anything away. The quirky drawings, odd organization, and carefully typed captions are all hilarious. <a href="http://kottke.org">Jason Kottke</a> (Internet-curator-extraordinaire) <a href="http://kottke.org/14/03/crabtree">recommended this book</a>, and he has yet to steer me wrong. The only downside is that it will be hard to find a copy to buy if your library doesn’t have one.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-welcome-to-mamoko.jpeg" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Welcome-Mamoko-Aleksandra-Mizielinska/dp/0763668915">Welcome to Mamoko</a> (by Aleksandra Mizielinska and Daniel Mizielinski, 2010) We actually got this book because we loved the authors’ <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Maps-Aleksandra-Mizielinska/dp/0763668966">Maps</a> so much. The story is introduced with a big cast of characters and a question about each (e.g., “Olaf Brown has a big day ahead. Who helps him out of a spot of trouble?”). What follows is a sequence of double page wordless scenes with all the characters in different urban settings. Even my three year-old loves to try to figure out what’s going on.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-incredible-comparisons.jpeg" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Welcome-Mamoko-Aleksandra-Mizielinska/dp/0763668915">Incredible Comparisons</a> (written by Russell Ash, illustrated by Stephen Biesty, 1996) My 6-year-old loves books with bite-sized amazing facts, and in this DK book almost every fact is accompanied by a beautiful picture. A blue whale weighs as much as 26 elephants. The moon is as wide as Australia. Angel Falls is three times taller than the Eiffel Tower. The Great Pyramid weighs as much as 16 Empire State Buildings! Highly recommended.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://highvariance.net/images/imwayr.jpg" /></p>

<p>Sheila at <a href="http://bookjourney.wordpress.com/">Book Journey</a> started <strong>It’s Monday! What are You Reading?</strong>, and Jen over at <a href="http://www.teachmentortexts.com/">Teach Mentor Texts</a> along with Kellee and Ricki at <a href="http://www.unleashingreaders.com/">Unleashing Readers</a> host kidlit versions.  All three sites are great places to find new books for yourself and your kids.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zebras and Expertise on the Internet]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/12/07/zebras-and-expertise-on-the-internet/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/12/07/zebras-and-expertise-on-the-internet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Internet is full of people talking about stuff they don’t know much about. It’s common at <a href="https://answers.yahoo.com">Yahoo Answers</a> and <a href="http://www.answers.com">Answers.com</a>, but <a href="http://amazon.com">Amazon</a> reviews and <a href="https://www.wikipedia.org">Wikipedia</a> are rife with it too. Even when bloggers are experts in one area, they often write much more broadly. As <a href="http://idlewords.com/about.htm">Maclej Ceglowski</a> delightfully points out in <a href="http://www.idlewords.com/2005/04/dabblers_and_blowhards.htm">his article about Paul Graham’s lack of expertise on painting</a>, even the top of the food chain is not immune. </p>

<p>I think it’s fantastic. You don’t need to be an expert to have something interesting to say. Regular people notice things experts don’t, and they often have a perspective closer to mine. Non-experts can also be <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Funniest-Amazon-Product-Reviews/lm/RM0256CJKINZJ">incredibly entertaining</a>.</p>

<p>As a consumer I’m careful not to take anything too seriously, but many folks are more trusting than me of the average blogger. As a producer, I worry about this all the time, as I love thinking and writing about things on the edge (or well over the edge) of my expertise. When I wildly speculate I try to be clear about it, but I feel a little bad that some readers might not notice. </p>

<p>It has turned out that the most common way for people to find this site is by searching for “are zebras mean” or “do zebras bite.” I don’t know jack about this subject, but that didn’t stop me from writing <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/01/why-are-zebras-so-mean-and-horses-so-nice/">a few hundred words about it</a> a couple years ago.  African Safari guide <a href="http://www.quora.com/Rory-Young-1">Rory Young</a> recently wrote <a href="http://www.quora.com/Can-zebras-be-domesticated-and-trained/answer/Rory-Young-1">a terrific article on Quora</a> that shares real knowledge about why zebras can be so nasty.  It makes me very happy to be able to send my potentially disappointed visitors on to some real answers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finding my niche #IMWAYR]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/12/01/kbr-finding-my-niche/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/12/01/kbr-finding-my-niche</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you look in the right places on the Internet, you can find terrific suggestions for books to read with your kids. Many of these recommendations are written by teachers and librarians who are tapped into the very latest and coolest new books. The downside is that I now have long wish lists of books that my local library hasn’t had a chance to buy yet. A year from now, my library might have some, but until then, my only option is to shell out real money for a brand new copy.</p>

<p>The fact is there are real gems hiding on the shelves of most libraries waiting to be discovered or rediscovered. That’s what you’ll find here: good books that I know can be found at at least one library (mine) and hopefully yours. </p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-the-quiet-place.jpeg" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Quiet-Place-Sarah-Stewart/dp/0374325650">The Quiet Place</a> (written by Sarah Stewart, illustrated by David Small, 2012) This book is told as a series of letters written by a young girl who moves from Mexico to the US. She starts nervous but excited and even though she has a wonderful mother and brother, she misses the family and home she’s left behind. Gradually, she makes a new home and new friends. I don’t think the author was an immigrant herself, but she really captures the experience and brought a tear to my eye.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-pish-posh.jpeg" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Pish-Posh-Said-Hieronymus-Bosch/dp/0152622101">Pish, Posh, Said Hieronymus Bosch</a> (written by Nancy Willard, illustrated by Leo, Diane, and Lee Dillon, 1991) On the one hand, it seems totally insane to turn Bosch’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hieronymus_Bosch#mediaviewer/File:The_Garden_of_Earthly_Delights_by_Bosch_High_Resolution.jpg">psychadelic visions of hell</a> into a children’s book, but on the other, kids love big eccentric detailed illustrations (e.g., <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Richard-Scarrys-Busy-Town/dp/0307168034">Richard Scarry’s Busy, Busy Town</a>) and those are right in Bosch’s wheel house. This is the story of the artist, his housekeeper, and their unusual house, and it totally works.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-bog-baby.jpeg" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bog-Baby-Jeanne-Willis/dp/0375861769">Bog Baby</a> (written by Jeanne Willis, illustrated by Gwen Millward, 2009) I love stories about kids who find animals, take them home, and then realize that wild animals need to be wild. Angelina Ballerina learns the lesson with a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Angelina-Butterfly-Ballerina-Katharine-Holabird/dp/0448440156">butterfly</a>, Mole learns the lesson with a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mole-Baby-Bird-Marjorie-Newman/dp/1582347840">baby bird</a>, and in this book, two sisters learn the lesson with a fantastical creature called a bog baby.  The pen and ink illustrations are unique and beautiful.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-alpha-oops.jpeg" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/AlphaOops-Day-Z-Went-First/dp/0763660841">AlphaOops: The Day Z Went First</a> (written by Alethea Kontis, illustrated Bob Kolar) Why does A always get to go first? Z decides it’s time to mix things up and hilarity ensues. Both my girls (now 6 and 3.5 years old) thought this book was a lot of fun.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://highvariance.net/images/imwayr.jpg" /></p>

<p>Sheila at <a href="http://bookjourney.wordpress.com/">Book Journey</a> started <strong>It’s Monday! What are You Reading?</strong>, and Jen over at <a href="http://www.teachmentortexts.com/">Teach Mentor Texts</a> along with Kellee and Ricki at <a href="http://www.unleashingreaders.com/">Unleashing Readers</a> host kidlit versions.  All three sites are great places to find new books for yourself and your kids.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jenny and the Cat Club #IMWAYR]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/11/24/kbr-jenny-and-the-cat-club/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/11/24/kbr-jenny-and-the-cat-club</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-jenny-and-the-cat-club.jpg" /></p>

<p>Over the summer I discovered a <a href="(http://www.teachmentortexts.com/)">whole community of folks</a> on the Internet who read and blog about kids books. It was very exciting and I had great fun reading their work and sharing mine <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/14/monday-reading/">here</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/21/violence-in-picture-books/">here</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/28/kbr-eclectic/">here</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/08/04/poetry-for-kids/">here</a> and <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/09/01/kbr-travel-edition/">here</a>. Then the Fall came and I fell into the teaching vortex. Sunday nights turned into lecture preparation marathons, and I&rsquo;ve been spending Monday mornings and afternoons presenting the fruits of this labor. I&rsquo;ve scratched my blogging itch on <a href="http://teachbetter.co">Teach Better</a>, but the <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/kbr/">Kid Book Review</a> section of <a href="http://highvariance.net">High Variance</a> has lain fallow. What better way to celebrate my first Monday off in ages (for Thanksgiving Break), than with an <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/imwayr">#IMWAYR</a> post!</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-the-fire-cat.jpg" /></p>

<p>When I was a kid, one of my very favorite books was <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Fire-Cat-Can-Read-Book/dp/0064440389">The Fire Cat</a> by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esther_Averill">Esther Averill</a>. The main character was not bad or good&ndash;Like people in the real world, Pickles was a mix of both. He was born strong and ambitious, but with no idea what to do with his gifts. He spends his time terrorizing smaller cats, but eventually learns to be kind and finds his true calling working in a fire house.</p>

<p>It wasn&rsquo;t until I went to buy this book for my daughter a few years ago that I discovered Esther Averill had written a whole series of wonderful books about cats living in New York City! And in 2003, the New York Review reprinted most of them with nice affordably priced hardcover bindings. The books revolve around the adventures of a shy but strong (<a href="http://www.amazon.com/School-Cats-Review-Childrens-Collection/dp/159017173X">stronger than Pickles even</a>) black cat named Jenny Linsky and her friends in the Cat Club that meets in her garden.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-the-fire-cat.jpg" /></p>

<p>The series contains stories for a variety of ages starting with the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Jennys-Birthday-Book-Esther-Averill/dp/1590171543">Jenny&rsquo;s Birthday Book</a> for very little kids, moving to <a href="">The Fire Cat</a> which is an early reader, and culminating in several chapter books like the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Hotel-York-Review-Childrens-Collection/dp/1590171594">The Hotel Cat</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Captains-Streets-Review-Childrens-Collection/dp/1590171748">Captains of the City Streets</a>, that make great bedtime reading.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve never had the pleasure of reading these books, the clear starting point is <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Jenny-Cat-Club-Collection-Childrens/dp/1590170474">Jenny and the Cat Club</a> where you learn how Jenny joined the club and meet all its colorful members. I can&rsquo;t recommend these books highly enough.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://highvariance.net/images/imwayr.jpg" /></p>

<p>Sheila at <a href="http://bookjourney.wordpress.com/">Book Journey</a> started <strong>It&rsquo;s Monday! What are You Reading?</strong>, and Jen over at <a href="http://www.teachmentortexts.com/">Teach Mentor Texts</a> along with Kellee and Ricki at <a href="http://www.unleashingreaders.com/">Unleashing Readers</a> host kidlit versions.  All three sites are great places to find new books for yourself and your kids.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taking a break from sports]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/09/18/taking-a-break-from-sports/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/09/18/taking-a-break-from-sports</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Real life is messy. We balance several life goals (family, career, personal) and many of these goals are difficult to even articulate clearly let alone achieve. For me, sports has always been an escape from life’s complexity. It’s a place where the goals are crystal clear and usually simple: <a href="http://seattletimes.com/html/seahawks/2022823508_seahawks03xml.html">Win</a>. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brazil_national_football_team">Win beautifully</a>. <a href="http://www.nba.com/history/players/abduljabbar_stats.html">Achieve milestones no has ever reached</a>. </p>

<p>I’ve been a sports fan my whole life, and I’ve always enjoyed seeing what people or teams can do when they push themselves as far as possible to achieve an extremely clear goal. Recently though, most of the big stories in sports have been about awful behavior of players, owners, and leagues:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.nfl.com/news/story/0ap3000000393519/article/vikings-adrian-peterson-indicted-in-child-injury-case">Adrian Peterson beating his kid</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/ray-rice-video-2014-9">Ray Rice beating his wife</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.ibtimes.com/why-was-michael-sam-cut-rams-personnel-decision-not-homophobia-1676156">Michael Sam tearing it up in preseason and then getting cut</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.sbnation.com/nfl/2014/2/14/5411608/worst-of-the-richie-incognito-jonathan-martin-report-miami-dolphins">The Dolphins bullying their own</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://nesn.com/2013/10/league-of-denial-shows-nfl-ignoring-concussion-evidence-mike-websters-fall-roger-goodell-digging-in/">The whole ongoing concussion saga in the NFL</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.sbnation.com/nba/2014/5/30/5764162/clippers-sale-timeline-donald-sterling-steve-ballmer">Donald Sterling</a> and <a href="http://espn.go.com/nfl/story/_/id/11454088/nfl-bans-jim-irsay-indianapolis-colts-six-games-fines-500k">Jim Irsay</a></li>
</ul>

<p>These stories sometimes get people talking about important social issues, but I find the whole thing rather depressing. I’m tired of caring about and rooting for people and institutions that I can’t respect. </p>

<p>A week ago I decided to take a break from sports. I was inspired by a new book called <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Against-Football-Fans-Reluctant-Manifesto/dp/161219415X">Against Football</a>, but it was the Adrian Peterson story and the reaction of other players to it that pushed me over the edge. Beating your kid with a stick until he’s bruised and bleeding isn’t right no matter how you were raised.</p>

<p>So: No more <a href="http://newyork.cbslocal.com/station/wfan/">sports radio</a> in the car. No more keeping up with the <a href="http://espn.go.com">ESPN news feed</a>. No more reading <a href="http://grantland.com">Grantland</a>. No more listening to <a href="http://espn.go.com/espnradio/podcast/archive?id=2864045">the BS report</a>. It’s freed up quite a bit of time and I’ve found other ways to escape. I’m reading more <a href="http://kottke.org">kottke.org</a> and catching up on my friends’ blogs. I’m getting more done at work.</p>

<p>At some point I’ll probably return to sports, but I want to come back for a good reason. I haven’t thought of one yet.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Travel Edition #IMWAYR]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/09/01/kbr-travel-edition/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/09/01/kbr-travel-edition</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every summer we fly off to California for one or two weeks of fun in the sun. At least during the day we have fun in the sun. There are also many of hours of fun in the dark every morning since we start the trip on Eastern Daylight Time, and there’s plenty of downtime mid-afternoon when we just want to chill. At home and away, books fill in these gaps between real-life adventures.</p>

<p>This trip we followed a three-prong reading strategy: First we packed a bunch of our favorite paperback books. We would have liked to bring more, but our bags were pretty heavy already. We had a mix of chapter books for R and picture books for both girls. Second, we brought our whole library of ebooks on our iPads. <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/02/13/ebooks-and-kids/">I far prefer physical picture books</a> and there aren’t nearly as many choices as I’d like, but there are some good ones and you can’t beat the weight. Third, we went to the <a href="http://www.lapl.org/branches/brentwood">local library</a> as soon as we arrived and picked up a big pile of books.</p>

<p>These are our top picks for the trip:</p>

<p><img src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-ipad-ebooks.jpg" /></p>

<p><strong>On the iPad:</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/book/would-you-rather-be-princess/id492520763?mt=11">Would You Rather Be a Princess or a Dragon</a> (written and illustrated by Barney Saltzberg) It’s a cute story that teaches kids that everyone has a little princess and dragon inside them.</p>

<p><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/gb/book/muddypaws-parragon-read-along/id434449727?mt=11">Muddypaws</a> (by Simon Mendez and Moira Butterfield) I find this story about a boy naming his new puppy a little brain-numbing, but both girls absolutely love it.</p>

<p><strong>From the library:</strong></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-grace-for-president.jpeg" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/James-Giant-Peach-Roald-Dahl/dp/0142410365">James and the Giant Peach</a> (written by Roald Dahl) One of my favorites as a kid turns out to be one of R’s favorites too. Dahl’s characters and dialog are just so vivid and funny.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Clink-Kelly-DiPucchio/dp/006192928X">Clink</a> (written by Kelly DiPucchio, illustrated by Matthew Myers) If you liked <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Corduroy-Don-Freeman/dp/0140501738">Corduroy</a>, you’ll like this story of an old toy robot who finally finds a boy who loves him.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Grace-President-Kelly-S-DiPucchio/dp/1423139992">Grace for President</a> (written by Kelly DiPucchio, illustrated by LeUyen Pham) What an inspiring story of how a girl becomes president of her class.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Sipping-Spiders-Through-Straw-Campfire/dp/0439584019">Sipping Spiders Through a Straw: Campfire Songs for Monsters</a> (written by Kelly DiPucchio, illustrated by Gris Grimly) Until I wrote this list I didn’t realize how big a part Kelly DiPucchio played in our vacation! Both girls are still singing these crazy songs.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://highvariance.net/images/imwayr.jpg" /></p>

<p>Originally hosted by Sheila at <a href="http://bookjourney.wordpress.com/">Book Journey</a>, Jen over at <a href="http://www.teachmentortexts.com/#axzz1u6wnaZyt">Teach Mentor Texts</a> along with Kellee and Ricki at <a href="http://www.unleashingreaders.com/">Unleashing Readers</a> host kidlit versions of <strong>It’s Monday! What are You Reading?</strong> All three sites are great places to find new books for yourself and your kids.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Milestones]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/08/23/milestones/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/08/23/milestones</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-bathing-suits.jpg" /></p>

<p>Learning to walk, talk, or ride a bike are all big milestones in a child&rsquo;s life. We usually remember how old our kids were when they reached them, but the actual point in time is somewhat arbitrary. How many steps is considered walking? When does babbling turn into talking? When do they really have control of the bike?</p>

<p>What isn&rsquo;t arbitrary is that moment when you say to yourself &ldquo;Holy Shit! They&rsquo;re really doing it!&rdquo; R is completely fearless in the water and has always been an enthusiastic splasher. I have to watch her like a hawk any time we&rsquo;re near a pool or at the beach, and I can&rsquo;t count how many times she has over-estimated her abilities and needed a helping hand or a full fledged rescue. She took a short swimming class last summer and learned to hold her breath and go under water, but as far as I could tell there wasn&rsquo;t much actual instruction. This summer she had swimming lessons at camp, but she reported spending most of her time wearing a floaty bubble aroud her waist.</p>

<p>For the past two weeks we&rsquo;ve been on vacation in California, and we&rsquo;ve had some good times playing in the pool and in the surf. Yesterday in the pool R was enjoying climbing on and off a boogie board in the shallow end. When it got away from her and floated to the deep end, she dog-paddled over to get it and kicked her way back. I blinked my eyes a few times and told her I thought she could have made it to the ladder (on the other side of the pool) if she wanted to. She shook her head and said &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t think so,&rdquo; but the gears were turning. A few minutes later she just went for it. I swam right next to her. She arrived at the ladder with a big smile on her face. And then swam all the way back. </p>

<p>Holy shit, the girl can swim!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Kids Hooked on Poetry #IMWAYR]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/08/04/poetry-for-kids/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/08/04/poetry-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I still remember in third grade when my grandmother got me my first book of poetry. I looked at it suspiciously and cast it aside. I don’t think I opened it more than a couple times and I have no idea what happened to it. Much later (as a pretentious young adult), I started taking poetry as seriously as song lyrics, and slowly built up a real appreciation for it.  But even after all these years, it still feels a little like a foreign language.</p>

<p>My theory has always been that I would be fluent in poetry if only it had been a regular part of my life when I was little. In our household we’re testing that theory with the girls by mixing a fair bit of poetry in with our usual large helpings of stories and nature books. So far, it’s going well–The girls think of poems as a completely normal form of expression. I think the key is reading widely, but making sure to hit subjects that the girls already enjoy. Here are some of our favorite collections:</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/poems/hv-sharing-the-seasons.jpg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Sharing-Seasons-A-Book-Poems/dp/1416902104">Sharing the Seasons: A Book of Poems</a> (collected by Lee Bennett Hopkins, illustrated by David Diaz) These vivid poems are clever and really capture the variety of life across the seasons. This collection is probably the house favorite and R loves to recite this spring poem:</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Don’t You Dare” by Beverly McLoughland  </p>

  <p>Stop! cried Robin,<br />
Don’t you dare begin it<br />
Another tweety rhyme<br />
With a redbreast in it.  </p>

  <p>Another cheery verse<br />
With a cherry tree,<br />
Don’t you dare<br />
Write another spring poem about me!  </p>

  <p>Take your pad and pencil<br />
To the reedy bog<br />
When you feel a poem coming–<br />
Think Frog.  </p>
</blockquote>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/poems/hv-flower-fairies.jpeg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Complete-Book-Flower-Fairies/dp/0723248397">The Complete Book of the Flower Fairies</a> (written and illustrated by Cicely Mary Barker) This collection is incredible and I don’t say that lightly. Ms. Barker is most known for her beautifully detailed drawings, but I think the accompanying poems are just as wonderful. If the flower grows in England, Ms. Barker has almost certainly written about its fairies.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The Dandelion Fairy”  by Cicely Mary Barker</p>

  <p>Here’s the Dandelion’s rhyme:<br />
See my leaves with tooth-like edges;<br />
Blow my clocks to tell the time;<br />
See me flaunting by the hedges,<br />
In the meadow, in the lane,<br />
Gay and naughty in the garden;<br />
Pull me up-I grow again,<br />
Asking neither leave nor pardon.<br />
Sillies, what are you about<br />
With your spades and hoes of iron?<br />
You can never drive me out-<br />
Me, the dauntless Dandelion!  </p>
</blockquote>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/poems/hv-a-childs-book-of-poems.jpeg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Childs-Book-Poems-Gyo-Fujikawa/dp/1402750617">A Child’s Book of Poems</a> (collected and illustrated by Gyo Fujikawa) I’ve been <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2011/12/30/bad-behavior/">a huge fan</a> of Mr. Fujikawa’s pen and ink drawings since I came across <a href="http://www.amazon.com/What-Busy-Day-Gyo-Fujikawa/dp/1402768192">Oh, What a Busy Day</a>. This collection is full of “serious” poetry by the likes of Wordsworth, Blake, Coleridge and Tennyson as well as plenty of silly rhymes by the prolific Anonymous.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Rain in Summer” by Henry Wadworth Longfellow  </p>

  <p>How beautiful is the rain!<br />
After the dust and heat,<br />
In the broad and fiery street,<br />
In the narrow lane,<br />
How beautiful is the rain!<br />
How it clatters along the roofs,<br />
Like the tram of hoofs!</p>

  <p>How it gushes and struggles out<br />
From the throat of the overflowing spout!<br />
Across the windowpane<br />
It pours and pours;<br />
And swift and wide,<br />
With a muddy tide,<br />
Like a river down the gutter roars<br />
The rain, the welcome rain!  </p>
</blockquote>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/poems/hv-wonton.jpeg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Won-Ton-Tale-Told-Haiku/dp/0805089950">Wonton: A Cat Tale Told in Haiku</a> (written by Lee Wardlaw, illustrated by Eugene Yelchin) I’ve been meaning to write about the best cat books for cat lovers, and this book would definitely make that list too. It follows a cat on his journey from the shelter to a new home. And as the title says, the author really does tell the story as a series of perfect haiku.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The New Place”</p>

  <p>Deep, dark bed cave. Me?<br />
Hiding? I’m no scaredy cat!<br />
I like dust bunnies!  </p>

  <p>“Here, kitty, kitty.”<br />
Ha. I’ll stay put till I know:<br />
Are they friend…or foe?  </p>

  <p>Yawn. String-on-a-stick.<br />
Fine. I’ll come out and chase it<br />
to make you happy.  </p>
</blockquote>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/poems/hv-water-boatman.jpeg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Water-Boatman-Caldecott-Ribbon-Nonfiction/dp/0618135472">Song of the Water Boatman &amp; Other Pond Poems</a> (by Joyce Sidman, illustrated by Beckie Prange) If you’re looking for fantastic nature-focused poetry, you’ve come to the right place. This book has entertained us, educated us, and even <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/04/02/salamanders-and-peepers/">inspired adventures</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>I’m always looking for more kid-appropriate (and kid-accessible) poetry so please share your favorites below!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://highvariance.net/images/imwayr.jpg" /></p>

<p>Originally hosted by Sheila at <a href="http://bookjourney.wordpress.com/">Book Journey</a>, Jen over at <a href="http://www.teachmentortexts.com/#axzz1u6wnaZyt">Teach Mentor Texts</a> along with Kellee and Ricki at <a href="http://www.unleashingreaders.com/">Unleashing Readers</a> host kidlit versions of <strong>It’s Monday! What are You Reading?</strong> All three sites are great places to find new books for yourself and your kids.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Eclectic Edition #IMWAYR]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/28/kbr-eclectic/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/28/kbr-eclectic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The three picture books described below have little in common beyond being very popular in our house. One is a diamond in the rough, another is a fantastic collection of poems, and the third is a quirky reference book. None are new, but one or two might be new to you:</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-henrys-happy-birthday.jpeg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Henrys-Happy-Birthday-Holly-Keller/dp/0688094511">Henry’s Happy Birthday</a> (written and illustrated by Holly Keller in 1990) The soul of Dick and Jane lives on in a lot of forgettable books in beginning reader series out there. These stories are often so formulaic you wonder why anyone would pick one up when there are so many other great books to choose. We got this book as a hand-me-down and when I saw it was part of the Weekly Reader Children’s Book Club series, I had low expectations.</li>
</ul>

<p>Henry has a vision for his birthday, and things don’t according to  plan. Among other things, he’s not allowed to wear his favorite t-shirt, his wrapped presents look lame, his cake isn’t chocolate, and he loses in musical chairs. He’s pretty disappointed, but things quickly take a turn for the better when his dad surprises him with a birthday crown and a bunch of balloons. He ends up having a great day. In our household we really value the ability to appreciate the good in situations and having faith that things will work out in the end. This story is terrific at teaching those lessons. The illustrations are definitely not high art, but they are cute and work well with the text.</p>

<p><em>Henry’s Happy Birthday</em> should be required reading the night before any birthdays or highly anticipated play dates.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-bow-wow-meow-meow.jpeg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/bow-wow-meow-rhyming-cats/dp/0152163956">Bow wow Meow Meow</a> (written and illustrated by Douglas Florian in 2003)  I’m not sure how I’ve managed to miss out on Douglas Florian all these years, but I sure am happy I found him a few weeks ago at the library. This collection of short poems about dogs and cats is hilarious for all ages. R and B regularly quote “Who always yanks the tail of the manx?” and R memorized all of the amazing opener: “Dog Log”. The illustrations are creative and fun too.</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-animals-speak.jpeg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Animals-Speak-Lila-Prap/dp/B0046LUKX6">Animals Speak</a> (written and illustrated by Lila Prap in 2006) Ever wonder what horses say in Hungarian or what frogs say in Farsi? Here are your answers. R studied this book for weeks and had lots of fun finding out how her multilingual friends would say neigh, buzz, or meow. The book’s pictures and flags of the world make it much more approachable for kids than <a href="http://www.eleceng.adelaide.edu.au/Personal/dabbott/animal.html">Derek Abbott’s giant table</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="center" src="http://highvariance.net/images/imwayr.jpg" /></p>

<p>Originally hosted by Sheila at <a href="http://bookjourney.wordpress.com/">Book Journey</a>, Jen over at <a href="http://www.teachmentortexts.com/#axzz1u6wnaZyt">Teach Mentor Texts</a> along with Kellee and Ricki at <a href="http://www.unleashingreaders.com/">Unleashing Readers</a> host kidlit versions of <strong>It’s Monday! What are You Reading?</strong> All three sites are great places to find new books for yourself and your kids.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Violence in Picture Books #IMWAYR]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/21/violence-in-picture-books/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/21/violence-in-picture-books</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Violence is rampant in kids’ books. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hobbit">The Hobbit</a> and the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harry_potter">Harry Potter</a> books are filled with magical blades and fierce battles. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hardy_Boys">The Hardy Boys</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nancy_Drew">Nancy Drew</a> are dodging bullets and getting bound to chairs in every other chapter. Even <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlotte%27s_Web">Charlotte’s Web</a> starts with a near ax murder. My kids (age 3 and 5) aren’t quite old enough to be reading these books on their own, and we are pretty careful about what we read to them. A while back I wrote about <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/10/06/violence-in-kids-books/">R’s fascination with Greek mythology</a>, but this turned out to be a phase–The closest she gets to violence these days is a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Case-Fight-Jigsaw-Jones-Mystery/dp/0439678072">food fight with Jigsaw Jones</a>.</p>

<p>Both girls still spend most of their time in the relatively safe world of picture books. I say <em>relatively</em> safe because occasionally we happen across some surprising brutality. Here are a few examples we’ve happened upon recently:</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-millions-of-cats.jpeg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Millions-Edition-Picture-Puffin-Books/dp/0142407089">Millions of cats</a> (written and illustrated by Wanda Gag in 1928) The illustrations are uniquely beautiful black pen and ink drawings and the story is about a very old man who goes out looking for a cat but has trouble deciding and ends up returning to his wife with millions of potential pets. (This happens to me sometimes when I go grocery shopping hungry, albeit on a smaller scale.) Unfortunately, the story takes a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malthus">Malthusian</a> turn when the multitude of cats start fighting about who is the prettiest:</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>They bit and scratched and clawed each other and made such a great noise that the very old man and the very old woman ran into the house as fast as they could. They did not like such quarreling. But after a while the noise stopped and the very old man and the very old woman peeped out of the window to see what had happened. They could not see a single cat! I think they must have eaten each other all up said the very old woman, “It’s too bad!”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Too bad indeed! Luckily one kitten who didn’t think he was prettiest survived. In this case <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QJO3ROT-A4E">One Direction was right</a> when they said “You don’t know you’re beautiful and that’s what makes you beautiful.” Seriously, I loved this book when was a kid and only found the millions of deaths mildly unsettling.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-feathers-and-fools.jpeg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Feathers-Fools-Mem-Fox/dp/0152023658">Feathers and Fools</a> (written by Mem Fox, illustrated by Nicholas Wilton in 1996) Mem Fox has written some tremendous books, but no matter how you slice it, this book about two flocks of birds who don’t get along is not young-child-appropriate. You might as well just read the latest news stories of the Israeli-Palestinian conflict to your kids at bed time:</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>But the swans, seeing them coming, made ready. 
Soon cries filled the air and blood darkened the earth. 
A cloud of feathers rose into the sky and haunted the sun. </p>

  <p>Of all the birds, not one remained alive. 
Silence hung over the gardens. 
And over the the lake. </p>

  <p>Then, in the shadows of the gardens, an egg hatched, and a small bird staggered out into the bloodstained silence. </p>

  <p>Among the reefs beside the lake a second egg hatched, and another small bird teetered out into the ruins </p>
</blockquote>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-poor-mr-nosey.jpg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mr-Nosey-Men-Little-Miss/dp/0843174781">Mr. Nosey</a> (written and illustrated by Roger Hargreaves in 1971) I’ve written before about <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/19/mister-men-and-little-misses/">how much I love the Mister Men and Little Misses</a>, but this particular book is one that I actively avoid. Mr. Nosey is just one of many annoying but endearing Mister Men in the series who get their comeuppance. What’s different here is that Mr. Nosey is actually physically abused. Even worse is the pleasure the abusers take in hurting their victim:</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>“BANG” went a hammer right on the end of Mr. Nosey’s nose.</p>

  <p>“Oh dear. I AM sorry!” said old Mr. Chips, who was nailing up a loose plank in the fence.</p>

  <p>Poor Mr. Nosey had to go home immediately and bandage his poor red sore nose.</p>

  <p>Mr. Chips grinned a broad grim.(sic!)</p>

  <p>The Plan was working very well indeed.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The real world is violent place. Eventually my girls will have to learn this and figure out how to live in it. We’re going to shelter them until we think they’re ready. I don’t know when that will be, but I know it won’t be for a while.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://highvariance.net/images/imwayr.jpg" /></p>

<p>Originally hosted by Sheila at <a href="http://bookjourney.wordpress.com/">Book Journey</a>, Jen over at <a href="http://www.teachmentortexts.com/#axzz1u6wnaZyt">Teach Mentor Texts</a> along with Kellee and Ricki at <a href="http://www.unleashingreaders.com/">Unleashing Readers</a> host kidlit versions of It’s Monday! What are You Reading? All three sites are great places to find new books for yourself and your kids.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My favorite podcast app: It's not what you think]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/16/network/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/16/network</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.macstories.net/reviews/overcast-review/">whole</a> <a href="http://www.macworld.com/article/2454285/review-overcast-is-a-winning-podcast-app.html">Internet</a> <a href="http://www.imore.com/overcast-iphone-review-podcasts-reconsidered">seemed</a> <a href="http://www.512pixels.net/blog/2014/7/overcast">to</a> <a href="http://daringfireball.net/linked/2014/07/16/overcast-1">go</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=overcast">crazy</a> today about the release of <a href="http://marco.org">Marco Arment</a>’s new podcast app for iOS: <a href="https://overcast.fm">Overcast</a>. He’s a nerd celebrity and he’s been teasing his fanbase (myself included) for what seems like a year as he worked on it and talked about it. Marco is an accomplished entrepreneur and engineer, and this release was <em>highly</em> anticipated. As a fan and a regular podcast listener, you might think I would be one of his first customers, but you’d be wrong.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-network-podcast-app.jpg" /></p>

<p>I’ve been using <a href="http://networkapp.net">Network</a> for the last six months and am very happy. The UI couldn’t have less chrome–All you see in the app is the artwork from your podcasts, episode descriptions, and a plus sign for adding new podcasts. Your interaction with the app is almost entirely through gestures. It’s not <em>completely</em> intuitive, but it makes me smile and reminds me a lot of the <a href="http://realmacsoftware.com/clear">Clear</a> to-do and reminders app.</p>

<p><a href="http://vemedio.com/products/instacast">Instacast</a>, <a href="http://www.downcastapp.com">Downcast</a>, <a href="http://www.shiftyjelly.com/pocketcasts">Pocket Casts</a> and now Overcast all have a lot more features than Network, but I don’t need a lot of features and I certainly don’t want to fiddle with my podcast app while I choose avocadoes and listen to <a href="http://atp.fm">John Siracusa</a> complain about LCD TV’s. Some of Overcast’s features (e.g., Smart Speed) do sound cool and non-intrusive, but for now Network is perfect for me–It plays my podcasts and just melts into the background.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It's Monday! What are You Reading? #IMWAYR]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/14/monday-reading/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/14/monday-reading</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So it turns out there are <a href="http://www.teachmentortexts.com/2014/07/its-monday-what-are-you-reading-71414_13.html#axzz37V4D0PXw">people out on the Internet</a> out on the Internet besides me that read and review picture books! Not only that, a whole bunch of them gather on Mondays to share their latest favorites. I guess this has something to do with this “social media” thing that is so trendy these days. Sigh, I feel so old.</p>

<p>Without further ado, here are the three books in heavy rotation on right now with my three year-old that I love:</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-alexander.jpeg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Alexander-Wind-Up-Mouse-Leo-Lionni/dp/0590430122">Alexander and the Wind-up Mouse</a> (written and illustrated by Leo Lionni) I’ve written about <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/05/10/carle-vs-lioni/">my love for Leo Lionni</a> before and this is my personal favorite. It’s got magic lizards, beautiful artwork, and the last page brings a tear to my eye every time I read it. The amazing thing is that my three year old seems to love it just as much as I do.</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="left" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-norman.jpeg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Norman-Doorman-Picture-Puffins-Freeman/dp/0140502882">Norman the Doorman</a> (written and illustrated by Don Freeman) <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Corduroy-Don-Freeman/dp/0140501738">Corduroy</a> gets more attention, but Don Freeman was far from a one-trick pony. This book about a mouse that works at a museum by day and creates art at night is lovely story with a sweet message.</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-zack.jpeg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Zacks-Alligator-Can-Read-Book/dp/0064441865">Zack’s Alligator</a> (written by Shirley Mozelle and illustrated by James Watts) This story is pure fun and I’ve never met a kid who wouldn’t do anything to have Zack’s alligator keychain. It’s like reading a smarter <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Danny-Dinosaur-Syd-Hoff/dp/0064440028">Danny and the Dinosaur</a> with a strong female lead character. </li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tile, a Geek Love Story]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/03/tile-a-geek-love-story/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/03/tile-a-geek-love-story</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The other day I got this email:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-tile-request.png" /></p>

<p>Indeed, I have a story, but I doubt it will be on Tile’s front page anytime soon. <!--More--> It started almost a year ago when I backed my very first <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com">Kickstarter</a> project and ordered four Tiles. These magical one inch squares promised to keep me from ever losing anything ever again. I immediately envisioned attaching them to my keys, my wife’s keys, our wallets, and my daughters’ favorite toys. And I knew once I had them in my hands I would think of a host of new possibilities. I was in geek love. </p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-tile.jpeg" /></p>

<p>Each $18.95 tile was a tiny Bluetooth beacon that could talk to any phone nearby that had the Tile app installed. If my keys fell behind a couch cushion, my phone could make their Tile play a little song announcing where they were. If I accidentally dropped my keys in the bushes, the app would remember where it last saw them and show me on a map. And if I left them on a plane, my app would talk to Tile’s cloud servers and let me know when another Tile user went near them and show me their location. The project had already hit it’s funding goal and was rocketing toward production. I couldn’t wait to get my delivery!</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-tile-key-basket.jpg" /></p>

<p>Months passed as the Tile Team worked through a series of last minute issues, and my interest started to wane. Then I realized that the batteries inside the Tiles expire after a year and are un-replaceable. That is, you have to buy new Tiles every year when your old ones die. And by the time my Tiles finally arrived, I realized that I already had a pretty good system for keeping track of my keys: They are always either in my pocket or in our kitchen key basket. I haven’t lost track of my keys in years. The same goes for my wallet, and even if I were a chronic wallet-loser, the Tile turns out to be too thick to comfortably slide into it.</p>

<p>Many of my early relationships followed the same pattern: Fall deeply in something with someone that was half a creation of my imagination. As I realized that this person was flesh and blood with flaws and features I didn’t immediately appreciate, I walked away. It wasn’t until much later that I learned that you can’t really love anyone without first understanding that there are no ideal types. You have to recognize that everyone is at least a little messy on the inside and the outside.</p>

<p>After a week with my Tiles, I’m starting to appreciate them. On Saturday my wife lost her keys and we spent several minutes scouring the house before we found them. I quickly attached a Tile, and that shouldn’t happen again. I’m also excited to put one in the car and always know where I’ve parked. Less than $20 for a  bit of magic is actually a pretty good deal even if it doesn’t last more than a year. And imagine how much cooler the next version will be!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: The Mister Men and Little Misses]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/19/mister-men-and-little-misses/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/19/mister-men-and-little-misses</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-mister-men-little-misses.jpg" /></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-little-miss-dotty.jpg" /></p>

<p>For weeks now our house has been coated in a thin layer of Mister Men and Little Miss books. We have about 70 of these brilliant little square paperbacks, and both girls love them. My three year old carries bundles of them around the house in little bags. She pages through them looking at the pictures, trying to sound out the names, and laughing her head off. It takes her ten minutes to select just the right set to read at bedtime. My five year old will also grab a stack and try to wrap her brain around the stories and the British vocabulary.</p>

<p>The funny thing is that my wife and I amassed our collection before we had kids. <!--more-->My wife had fond memories of reading them while she babysat during high school and we figured our future kids would love them too. A <a href="http://economics.sas.upenn.edu/faculty/jere-behrman">good friend of ours</a> thought we were nuts. He said  you can only read a book so many times before it rots your brain. Kids often want their parents to read books twice that many times. His strategy was to shun all children&rsquo;s books until he had to read them in hopes of not crossing the misery threshold with some of them. We ignored his advice and blissfully read on, and so far we&rsquo;re still big fans of the Mister Men and Little Misses.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-mister-tickle.jpg" /></p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Hargreaves">Roger Hargreaves</a> started writing stories about the Mister Men in 1971. <em>Mr. Tickle</em>, his first, was 30 pages of bold colorful illustrations  accompanying a funny story of a little man with extraordinarily long arms and a love for tickling people. Roger went on to write 47 books about the Mister Men and another 34 about their female counterparts: the Little Misses. His son Adam has continued to write them since Roger passed away in 1988.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-little-miss-bossy.jpg" /></p>

<p>In some ways, all these books are similar. The characters are fairly one dimensional.  Some are good (like Mr. Happy and Little Miss Fun), some are bad (like Little Miss Bossy and Mr. Mischief), and some just are what they are (like Mr. Tall and Little Miss Shy). The bad ones often (but not always) learn a lesson at the end. But the books are also quirky and unpolished&ndash;you never <em>really</em> know what&rsquo;s going to happen. Some stories have odd twists (<em>Mr. Perfect</em>), others just peter out (like <em>Little Miss Curious</em>), and a few go right where you think they&rsquo;re going (like <em>Mr. Daydream</em>). </p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-mister-men-back.jpg" /></p>

<p>On the back of every book is a picture of every single Mister Man or Little Miss. Both girls love poring over these tiny portraits. The characters have distinctive colors, shapes, shoes, and hats and they often show up as secondary characters in other books. Recognizing them in the stories and finding them on the backs of the books is great fun. I have a feeling our whole family will be reading these stories for years to come.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[1983: Revisited]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/09/1983-revisited/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/09/1983-revisited</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-holy-diver.jpg" /></p>

<p>In the weeks after I posted <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/18/crucial-years-in-metal-1983/">my case for 1983</a> as a crucial year in heavy metal history, I went through a crisis of faith. What about Judas Priest? What about Iron Maiden? And what if I forgot an even bigger band or album? Luckily I could turn to my metal sensei in this time of need. The same Mike who dragged me to the import metal bins at the Rockin’ Mania record store in Framingham and opened my eyes to a whole world of music was just an email away. Here’s what he had to say:</p>

<!--more-->

<blockquote>
  <p>Nice article, but you missed out on a lot of other stuff was going on around that time. First, while I was a big fan of all Maiden’s albums up to and including Seventh Son, I think the albums before and after 1983’s Piece of Mind  are actually more influential.  In 1982 Maiden toured the world with Judas Priest.  They headlined everywhere except the US.  This album and tour really exposed Maiden to the fans in America and turned them into the pre-eminent act of the decade.  1984 brought Powerslave which launched Maiden into the mainstream with heavy rotation on MTV for both Aces High and Two Minutes to Midnight.  This was accompanied by the first tour by a western rock artist into the Soviet Bloc, years before the much ballyhoo’d Billy Joel tour.  So, the final word on Maiden: Piece of mind has a couple of their biggest live hits but lacked the impact of the other two records. </p>

  <p>There are a few records that aren’t on your list which I believe some credit: </p>

  <p>First, Dio’s Holy Diver.  Enough said.</p>

  <p>Try not to shit on the next two before I get done.</p>

  <p>Def Leppard Pyromania.  These guys pretty much single handedly started the hair metal era.  I know there are a lot of other bands that were important to the genre, but this album really kicked it off.</p>

  <p>Quiet Riot Metal Health.  Not the most creative musically, but it had some catchy stuff.  The important part regarding this one is the fact that it was the first metal album to reach number one on Billboard’s top 100.  Unheard of ground for a band of this genre.</p>

  <p>I’m glad you gave a nod to Ozzy’s Bark at the Moon.  Not his best work by any stretch, but it did resurrect his career from the aftermath of Randy Rhodes’ death.</p>

  <p>I am still a fan of Shout at the Devil.  It is the only true metal album Crue ever put out and is my favorite even though some of my favorite songs come from other records.</p>

  <p>You were always a little more into the hair bands than I, but I do have to give credit to the genre for helping to bring metal to the mainstream.  A friend and I were discussing the phenomenon of mainstreaming the other day.  I am constantly amazed by the music accepted by the mainstream media that we had to stay up until 1 in the morning to hear on the radio.  Not only that, but the generic rock bands are so much heavier than rock of our era.  Imagine what our friends would have thought of Linkin Park back in 1985.  Or more entertaining would be to play some Motionless in White or Asking Alexandria. </p>

  <p>I could go on, but I have to get ready for a barbecue.  I look forward to your thoughts.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I got lucky with Iron Maiden’s <em>Piece of Mind</em>, and Judas Priest didn’t release an album in 1983. The incredible <em>Screaming for Vengeance</em> came out in 1982, and was followed by the less incredible <em>Defenders of the Faith</em> in 1984. Omitting Dio’s <em>Holy Diver</em>, however, was my worst nightmare–That album is pure fantasy metal and has been unbelievably influential. I bet millions of kids around the world played that cassette to death in the eighties just like I did.</p>

<p>Mike always had a soft spot for Quiet Riot that I still don’t understand. After these lyrics, how can anyone take this band seriously?</p>

<pre><code>Cum on feel the noize
Girls rock your boys
We'll get wild, wild, wild
Wild, wild, wild
</code></pre>

<p>But Mike is right–Quiet Riot were pop metal and they were the first metal band to have the number one album in the country. It’s a shame it had to be them.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-def-leppard.jpg" /></p>

<p>I thought long and hard about including “Pyromania” on my list, but at the end of the day I decided Def Leppard was a hard rock band that happened to have good hair and bad spelling. That said, I loved this album, and they were heavier than most stuff on the radio at the time. I killed this cassette too.</p>

<p>As for mainstreaming of heavy music, Mike’s experience in Southern California couldn’t be more different from mine in New Haven, CT. Until Mike’s email, I’d never even heard of Motionless in White or Asking Alexandria, let alone heard them on the radio. My choices are country, classic rock, hip hop, or tween pop. The heaviest it gets is old Van Halen and AC/DC. If you want metal around here, you’ve got to go looking pretty far away from the main stream. Luckily, there’s <a href="http://orgtheory.wordpress.com/2014/03/10/world-wide-heavy-metal/">plenty out there</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Subscribe via email]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/04/subscribe-via-email/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/04/subscribe-via-email</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am happy to report that you can now to subscribe to <a href="http://highvariance.net">High Variance</a> by email. Just look under the <strong>Follow</strong> heading on the right side of any page, fill in your email address, and press the <strong>Follow this site via email</strong> button. <a href="https://blogtrottr.com">Blogtrottr</a> will send you a confirmation message, and then you’ll get every new article emailed to you within an hour of it going live. If you prefer, you can still subscribe to the site’s <a href="http://highvariance.net/rss/index.xml">RSS feed</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/intent/user?screen_name=HighVarianceNet">follow me on Twitter</a> for updates.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dokken versus the World]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/02/dokken-versus-the-world/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/02/dokken-versus-the-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-dokken.jpg" /></p>

<p>I love Dokken and I know <a href="http://cvcomics.com/requiem/?p=26">I&rsquo;m not alone</a>. George Lynch is an amazing guitarist, and Don Dokken has a perfect hair metal voice. They really are the musician&rsquo;s hair metal band. But even I have to admit that Dokken was not the most original band in the world. For years, it bugged me that their song &ldquo;Tooth and Nail&rdquo; ripped off Foreigner&rsquo;s &ldquo;Tooth and Nail&rdquo;. And just recently I realized that <em>many</em> of their songs share titles with other big eighties (or late seventies) songs. In a few cases, Dokken came first, but with most, Dokken looks more like the inspired party than the inspiration. I thought it would be fun to explore when Dokken&rsquo;s song was better (or worse) with a little head-to-head competition.</p>

<!--more-->

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/uttV1VZUgQQ?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/SrOMVKH8GT4?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091173.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091173/">1. Erasure vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 1.
Erasure, (Break these) "Chains of Love", 1988
Dokken, "Breaking the Chains", 1981
-->

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/t1_5eRtDvAM?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/XFDDjXfAD5Q?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091180.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091180/">2. Foreigner vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 2.
Foreigner, "Tooth and Nail", 1984
Dokken, "Tooth and Nail", 1984
-->

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/yq3Ad3vGG1w?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/ECr98ZOnsig?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091184.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091184/">3. JoBoxers vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 3.
JoBoxers, "Just Got Lucky", 1982
Dokken, "Just Got Lucky, 1984
-->

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/1Cw1ng75KP0?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/1YAjQYJ7PVs?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091187.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091187/">Heart vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 4.
Heart, "Alone", 1987
Dokken, "Alone Again", 1984
-->

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/IivGqwQvdCI?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/L7Yno5p2D30?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091189.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091189/">5. Debbie Gibson vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 5.
Debbie Gibson, "Only in My Dreams", 1986
Dokken, "In My Dreams", 1985
-->

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/iUODdPpnxcA?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/glkmflBYf64?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091194.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091194/">6. Paul Simon vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 6.
Paul Simon, "Slip Slidin' Away", 1977
Dokken, "Slippin' Away", 1985
-->

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/C-TSvxZ40RQ?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/MKF5R8doqDE?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091195.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091195/">7. Aerosmith vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 7.
Aerosmith, "Lightning Strikes", 1982
Dokken, "Lightnin' Strikes Again", 1985
-->

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/3MG1YaMq0Tk?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/XPTFqVluR3A?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091196.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091196/">8. Thompson Twins vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 8.
Thompson Twins, "Lies", 1982
Dokken, "Don't Lie to Me", 1985
-->

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/pAgnJDJN4VA?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="480" height="360" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/siBW8NgcEGI?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<script type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="http://static.polldaddy.com/p/8091199.js"></script>

<noscript><a href="http://polldaddy.com/poll/8091199/">9. AC/DC vs. Dokken</a></noscript>

<!--- 9.
AC/DC, "Back in Black", 1980
Dokken, "Back for the Attack", 1985
-->
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kid Book Review: Robot Edition]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/21/kbr-robots/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/21/kbr-robots</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>B is really into robots lately, and I thought it would be fun to share her favorite books that feature robots or have exciting robot-related scenes.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-robot-and-bluebird.jpg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Robot-Bluebird-David-Lucas/dp/0374363307">The Robot and the Bluebird</a> (written and illustrated by David Lucas) This is a sweet story that takes on some heavy topics: love, sacrifice and even death. Spoiler alert: The bird comes out ok at the end, the robot not so much. The quirky drawings are wonderful, and honestly I think David Lucas is physically incapable of creating a book that’s not great.</li>
</ul>

<!--more-->

<p><img class="left" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-boy-+-bot.jpg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Boy-Bot-Ame-Dyckman/dp/0375867562">Boy + Bot</a> (written by Ame Dyckman, illustrated by Dan Yaccarino) We picked this up at the library a couple weeks ago and it’s still B’s dinner time favorite. The boy and the robot meet in the forest and start a friendship that’s briefly interrupted by a couple cute misunderstandings. Now whenever I ask B if she likes this book she smiles and says in a slow monotone: “Affirmative.”</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="center" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-lbg-mean-robot.jpg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Ladybug-Girl-Bumblebee-Jacky-Davis/dp/0803733399">Ladybug Girl and Bumblebee Boy</a> (written by Jacky Davis, illustrated by David Soman) This is our go-to bedtime book and it’s got Ladybug Girl playing Bug Squad at the playground with her new friend Sam. B loves when they pretend the tire swing is a mean robot and Lulu jumps on its head. And the other day at the playground we almost convinced a real boy to play Ladybug Bug girl with us! He wanted to be Mosquito Boy until his friend pulled him back to playing Ninjas.</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="center" src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-critter-giant-robot.jpg" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="">Just Go to Bed</a> (written and illustrated by Mercer Mayer) The Critter books are like cheese sandwiches–they aren’t the most creative stories, but they are consistently good. I might appreciate this one more than the girls because we live it almost every night. Critter keeps coming up with excuses for not going to bed while his parents play along but get more and more exasperated. At  one point Critter is a space cadet and Dad (the giant robot) captures him. If only that were the end of the story.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wawa: Philadelphia's Hidden Jewel]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/19/wawa/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/19/wawa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-wawa.jpg" /></p>

<p>I recently made a quick return visit to Philadelphia and rediscovered one of my favorite Philly institutions. It wasn&rsquo;t the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liberty_bell">Liberty Bell</a>, the <a href="http://www.visitphilly.com/music-art/philadelphia/love-statue/">Love sculpture</a>, or even the <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/04/06/tetris-skyscraper_n_5099208.html">giant tetris tower</a>. It was <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wawa,_Inc.">Wawa</a>: the world&rsquo;s greatest convenience store. What makes it so much better than 7-Eleven, ampm, or even the recently departed <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_Hen">White Hen</a>? Two things:</p>

<!--more-->

<ol>
  <li>Wawa has the high tech efficiency of a Japanese factory. They do everything they can possibly think of to get you exactly what you want as fast as possible. When you want a fresh sandwich (or bagel or breakfast burrito or anything else that needs preparation) you don&rsquo;t wait in line and talk to an error prone human. Instead, you tap your way through a perfectly designed touch screen interface and when you finish, your receipt is instantly printed. While you pay for your order (and anything else), they make your food. Wawa is always packed, but no one is ever waiting for anything.</li>
  <li>Wawa has their finger on the pulse of America. Do Americans want roller hot dogs or stale donuts? No! We want fresh baked goods and 10 flavors of fresh-brewed coffee. Do we want two choices for liquid additives for our coffee? No! We want to choose between skim, 1%, 2%, whole, half-and-half, full-on-cream, and three different non-dairy creamers. And they all better be on ice. Wawa is on the cutting edge of smoothies and fancy iced coffee drinks too. At the same time, they&rsquo;ve got a great selection of sodas, candy, and medicine.</li>
</ol>

<p>I admit I&rsquo;m a little biased. My three-year-old and I enjoyed playing find the &ldquo;Wawa&rdquo; in the store (not a hard game given the number of self-branded items) while listening to a continuous stream of 80&rsquo;s music (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BoXu6QmxpJE">Everybody Wang Chung Tonight!</a>). Even so, I&rsquo;m perplexed. Why is America outside of Philadelphia almost completely deprived of the Wawa experience? It made sense before 2008 when the Phillies <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008_World_Series">won the World Series</a> and the city needed <em>something</em> to be proud of. But now? Nothing should be stopping Wawa from total world domination.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Teach Better: My New Teaching Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/11/teach-better/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/11/teach-better</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://teachbetter.co"><img src="http://highvariance.net/images/hv-teach-better.png" /></a></p>

<p>I am very happy to announce the birth of this blog’s first child!</p>

<p><a href="http://teachbetter.co">Teach Better</a> is the new home for everything I have to say about teaching and education in general. <a href="http://highvariance.net">High Variance</a> will remain high variance, and you can continue to come here for regular <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/18/crucial-years-in-metal-1983/">rants about 80’s music</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/09/05/the-stars-align/">heartwarming kid stories</a> and <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/02/26/kid-book-review-monster-edition/">book reviews</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/27/conan-the-snowman/">original Christmas carols</a>, and the occasional <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/02/27/mlp-revelations/">ridiculous theory</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
