<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[honesty | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/honesty/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-03-08T18:48:40-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Playing the Victim]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/13/playing-the-victim/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/13/playing-the-victim</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The eighties are not known as a time of soul bearing honesty (see
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iran–Contra_affair">Iran-Contra</a>), but
eighties music is full of cheesy earnestness about love in its various
messy forms.  Eighties singers told the hard truths even when it made
them look weak.  Here are four great examples of eighties guys who
weren’t afraid to play the victim:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9abYzI9ycjk">Everything She Wants</a> (by
Wham, 1984): George Michael is having a rough time with a no-good
money-grubbing girlfriend.  I smile every time he finds out
she’s pregnant and says “If my best isn’t good enough, how can it be
good enough for two?  I can’t work any harder than I do!” Maybe this was
the incident that turned him off women forever?  Not that there’s
anything wrong with that!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Iu788foYCa8">I’ve Done Everything For You</a>
(Rick Springfield, 1981): Based on my analysis of his catalog, this
guy seems like he was just a bad boyfriend.  He lusted after his friend
<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qYkbTyHXwbs">Jessie’s girl</a>.  He told his girl not to <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cp42V938eBA">talk to strangers</a>.  And here
he says “I’ve done everything for you; you’ve done nothing for me!”
At least he was <a href="http://ztams.com/index.php?action=display&amp;ref=26342">good looking</a>!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uPudE8nDog0">Don’t You Want Me?</a>(by
The Human League, 1981) This is another case of a guy who did
everything–“I picked you out, I shook you up, and turned you around”
and she’s got the nerve to dump him.  What’s unique in this song is that she
gets the opportunity to tell her side of the story.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9dZW1C3neao">The Rain</a> (by Oran Juice
Jones, 1986): Here’s where we see that eighties male victimhood
crossed race lines.  The best part of the song is when we listen in on Mr. Jones
confronting his cheating girlfriend and telling her “You gotta get on
outta here with that alley-cat-coat-wearing, punch-bucket-shoe-wearing
crumbcake I saw you with. Cause you dismissed!”</p>
  </li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
