<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[other | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/other/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-29T13:11:21-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Expanding the Market for Limited Edition Dishes]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/03/09/dishes/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/03/09/dishes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/conan-dishes/yorkies.jpg" alt="Yorkies!" /></p>

<p>Limited edition dishes have a very limited market for two main reasons. First, they feature a very limited selection of art. Cute dogs, American flags, flowers, and Russian folk tales only appeal to so many people.  These plates are basically baseball cards for grandmas. Second, most of these dishes are designed solely for display and could actually kill you if you ate off them–this is crazy since the last time I checked normal people used dishes for serving food, not decorating their walls.  These companies need to expand their stables of artists and use nontoxic paints. </p>

<p>To get things started concretely, I propose the following set of four limited edition dinner plates by Frank Frazetta.  Imagine the look of wonder on your guests’ faces as they clear their plates and reveal the raw ferocity and masculinity of Conan the Barbarian. I know I would buy them. Click through to see them in their full resolution glory!</p>

<p><a href="/images/conan-dishes/d1.jpg"><img src="/images/conan-dishes/d1-small.jpg" alt="Conan!" /></a>
<a href="/images/conan-dishes/d2.jpg"><img src="/images/conan-dishes/d2-small.jpg" alt="Conan!" /></a>
<a href="/images/conan-dishes/d3.jpg"><img src="/images/conan-dishes/d3-small.jpg" alt="Conan!" /></a>
<a href="/images/conan-dishes/d4.jpg"><img src="/images/conan-dishes/d4-small.jpg" alt="Conan!" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Three Favorite Low Traffic Blogs]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/17/favorite-low-traffic-blogs/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/17/favorite-low-traffic-blogs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week a whole bunch of people wrote <a href="http://www.economist.com/blogs/babbage/2013/01/remembering-aaron-swartz">really</a> <a href="http://boingboing.net/2013/01/12/rip-aaron-swartz.html">nice</a> <a href="http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/philg/2013/01/12/aaron-swartz/">things</a> about an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aaron_Swartz">amazing person</a> who is no longer around to read them. Continuing in my <a href="/blog/categories/thanks/">series of thanking people who can still appreciate it</a>, these are my three favorite low traffic blogs:</p>

<h2 id="think-in-projectshttpwwwthinkinprojectscom"><a href="http://www.thinkinprojects.com">Think In Projects</a></h2>
<!---
(24 Google Reader subscribers)
--->

<p>I found out about Rafal’s blog when he commented on <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/05/27/gtd-with-rtm/">a post here</a>, but it’s quickly become my favorite source for thoughtful advice about improving personal productivity.  He reads widely and links to the best articles he finds on the topic. But the reason I keep coming back is his own writing.  For whatever reason, he and I run into very similar issues and he has practical ideas for making progress on those issues. Recently he’s written good stuff about <a href="http://www.thinkinprojects.com/productivity/celebrate-2/">the value in looking back at our accomplishments</a>, <a href="http://www.thinkinprojects.com/productivity/planning-2013/">long range planning</a>, and <a href="http://www.thinkinprojects.com/productivity/on-avoidance-of-stuff/">avoiding what’s important</a>.  He also happens to write extensively about <a href="http://www.rememberthemilk.com">Remember the Milk</a> and <a href="http://evernote.com">Evernote</a>–two tools I respect but don’t currently use.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> Think in Projects is now <a href="http://creatingpersonalflow.com/">Creating Personal Flow</a>. I love the new layout and you can find the content referenced above on the new site here:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://creatingpersonalflow.com/productivity/celebrate-2/">Celebrate</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://creatingpersonalflow.com/productivity/on-avoidance-of-stuff/">On avoidance of stuff</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://creatingpersonalflow.com/productivity/planning-2013/">Planning 2013</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="its-not-a-problem-if-you-cant-solve-ithttpsillynomadtumblrcom"><a href="http://sillynomad.tumblr.com">It’s not a problem if you can’t solve it</a></h2>
<!---
(2 Google Reader subscribers)
--->

<p>This site is written by a former student of mine from Spain who has spent big chunks of this life in Africa and is now living in Japan.  He has a unique perspective on the world and through words and photos he communicates a great sense for both the ordinary and extraordinary in Japan.  Reading his blog I often feel like I’m watching a Japanese version of the Office. Alf also partakes in a tremendous number of extracurricular activities so I get to learn all about soccer leagues, concerts, themed restaurants, and video game arcades too. And seriously, how many people do you know that have taken a <a href="http://sillynomad.tumblr.com/day/2012/12/20">field trip to Hiroshima to play Dungeons and Dragons</a>?</p>

<h2 id="byte-bakerhttpbytebakercom"><a href="http://bytebaker.com">Byte Baker</a></h2>
<!---
(118 Google Reader subscribers)
--->
<p>Shrutarshi Basu is a computer science grad student at Cornell, but I started reading his blog back when he was “just” a nerdy college kid. He writes about what he’s doing (hacking, figuring out life) and what he thinks is important (e.g., programming languages, reading, productivity). While it’s true that we do share some interests, my favorite quality of the site is Shrutarshi’s earnestness. He consciously tries to achieve excellence in whatever he does and he’s open about what’s working and what’s not.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bathroom Fan Love Letters]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/10/30/bathroom-fan-love-letters/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/10/30/bathroom-fan-love-letters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two of my favorite bloggers (<a href="http://www.marco.org">Marco Arment</a> and <a href="http://brooksreview.net">Ben Brooks</a>) recently
published passionate <a href="http://www.marco.org/2012/05/06/bathroom-fan-timer-switches">love</a> <a href="http://brooksreview.net/2012/03/amazon-item/">letters</a> to the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B003TJAGPS">Panasonic WhisperCeiling</a> bathroom
fan, and in Marco’s case, a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00313JXB0">Leviton electronic timer switch</a>.  Since
our downstairs bathroom has had no fan at all for more than a year, and
our upstairs bathroom fan sounded like a jet engine (and took 20 minutes
to de-fog a mirror), I took this as a sign that it was time to upgrade.
It was harder than expected to find an electrician to install them, but
today was the big day.  It’s worked out pretty well for our upstairs
bathroom, but not so much for the downstairs bathroom.  In fact, I was
surprised by three issues that were unmentioned in the “reviews” I read:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>The Panasonic WhisperLite fan/light combo unit is approximately
square and it doesn’t fit in our downstairs bathroom because we have a
cast-iron drain pipe running 8.5” away from the stud where the fan has
to be mounted.  Drat.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The bulbs in the WhisperLite are compact-fluorescent and they send
out a very white light.  I like it, but my wife calls it “institutional”
and she says it reminds her of a public restroom.  This isn’t exactly
where anyone wants to be taking a shower, and if she doesn’t acclimate, I’m
hoping we can just change the bulbs to something a little softer.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Leviton switch requires three wires (including a neutral) and our
downstairs bathroom only has two.  If I want a timer switch we either
spend $200 to run a new line (I’m not <em>that</em> crazy) or we get one of
those <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Intermatic-FD15MWC-15-Minute-Spring-Loaded/dp/B000EVS4WG">spring-loaded knobs</a> that screams hotel sauna.  For now, we’re
sticking with the old manual switch.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>To be fair, the new fan is very quiet and is working like a champ–our
upstairs bathroom isn’t small and during a leisurely shower the mirror
never fogged up.  And the Leviton timer is far more reliable than I was
about remembering to turn off the fan when it’s done its job.  But I
think there is a bigger lesson here: Some products that are perfect for
some people (or bathrooms) are not perfect for others, and we shouldn’t
let ourselves be blinded by the opinions of fan-bois.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tire Talk]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/11/tire-talk/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/11/tire-talk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I went to <a href="http://www.thedevilsgear.com/">a local shop</a> and
bought new tires for the mountain bike I ride around town almost every
day.  The angst I felt while deciding exactly what to buy took me by
surprise.  Part of me wanted something cheap and durable that would roll
smoothly and efficiently on pavement. But another part of me wanted to
replace my worn out racing tires with something aggressive, knobby and
impractical for city streets.</p>

<p>When I was in my twenties and thirties the bike I rode defined me more
than my sunglasses, my haircut, or my car. It was more than my
style—it was a major part of my identity. I know that sounds
ridiculous, but imagine what a truck guy’s truck means to him or what an
Apple nerd’s Mac means to him (or her).  A good friend of mine would
call me regularly and say “Got time for some tire talk?”  We would spend
the next half hour dissecting the pros and cons of different treads;
analyzing the tracks we saw out on the trails; debating whether Kevlar
worth the price premium; discussing trends like “thin on the bottom,
knobby on the sides”, and arguing about what tire shed mud or carved
corners best.  At the end though, the most important question was: “What
are you riding right now?”</p>

<p>Since I hit my forties my life has changed a lot.  I spend the vast
majority of my time working, parenting, or doing house stuff.  Trail
riding (and even trail-running) is mostly on hiatus.  My daylight
leisure time is almost always having fun with the girls and when they’re
sleeping at night I’d rather blog than ride.  In a few years (when the girls are
older) I’m sure I’ll be back, but until then, my riding will be limited
to the streets between my offices and classrooms.  This is far far
better than nothing–I actually love battling traffic and the elements.</p>

<p>So it’s been years since my bike’s gotten dirty, but up until last week,
I still had the option of veering onto any trail and cutting through East
Rock Park at a moment’s notice.  And I liked projecting the image of an
MTB guy on his way to a trailhead (even if I was wearing a corduroy
jacket).  Those days are over.  I chose a pair of
<a href="http://www.kendausa.com/en/home/bicycle/commuter.aspx">cheap tires</a>
that ride way better than my old knobbies on the road.  They even
have a little bit of a tread that could handle some of the East Rock
trails.  But now I’m honest with myself and world.  I’m a bike commuter.
It’s not permanent, but it’s true.  And I’m good with that.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why are zebras so mean and horses so nice?]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/01/why-are-zebras-so-mean-and-horses-so-nice/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/01/why-are-zebras-so-mean-and-horses-so-nice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In Jared Diamond’s
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Guns-Germs-Steel-Fates-Societies/dp/0393317552">Guns Germs and Steel</a>,
he asserts that zebras cause more injuries to zoo keepers than any other
animal. At least that’s how I remember it–I gave my copy away years ago
and never replaced it. In any event, it’s common knowledge that <a href="http://www.theblaze.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/Woman-bitten-by-Zebra.jpg">zebras are mean</a> and you can’t really tame them. Horses on the other hand are
every little girl’s best friend and they are happy to wear <a href="http://michellewrighton.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/dsc_4039.jpg">garlands of flowers</a> and <a href="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3111/2659658105_d8bccd69f1.jpg">nibble apples out of your hand</a>.  Why such a difference when
on the surface zebras just seem like striped horses?</p>

<p>Before I go any further I should say that the rest of this post is a
pure mixture of Wikipedia and armchair theorizing. You have been warned.</p>

<p>The answer has to be geography. The savanna is a
<a href="http://babeinthebush.blogspot.com/2009/08/luangwa-battlefield-of-hippo-part-5.html">tough place</a>. It’s
got cheetahs, hyenas, wild dogs (that also make <a href="http://kids.nationalgeographic.com/kids/stories/animalsnature/african-wild-dogs/">terrible pets</a>),
crocodiles (near the water anyway) and of course lions. Friendly and
laid back on the savanna equals dead. You have to be fierce
(zebras/meerkats), big (elephants/hippos/rhinos/giraffes) or fast and
high strung (impalas and ostriches) to survive.  But what about those friendly
monkeys that like to sit on shoulders in the bazaar?  Don’t they live on
the savanna? Well they can watch the action from the tops of trees and
eat their bananas in peace.  Zebras don’t have that option.</p>

<p>The temperate grasslands where horses evolved are a whole different
story. A lot more empty space and a lot fewer predators mean horses
could afford to just horse around all day before humans came along and
domesticated them.  Even the
<a href="http://www.fws.gov/rockymountainarsenal/kids/puzzles/PredatorsofthePrairie.pdf">temperate grassland predators</a>
are basically wild house pets. Wolves are genetically identical to dogs
and nothing else is big enough to give a horse more than a kick in the
shin.</p>

<p>Of course this very reasonable explanation doesn’t change the fact that
it’s grossly unfair that we can’t ride zebras around for fun–I mean
that would be so cool!  Maybe someday someone will splice nice genes
into the zebra (or striped genes into the horse) and I’ll get to live
the dream. Until then I’ll stick to the mountain bike for my riding
adventures. Oh well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
