<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[other | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/other/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-26T23:26:52-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pride]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/05/06/pride/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/05/06/pride</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last night I dreamt I was at my high school reunion. Near the end of dinner, one of the organizers came to my table and asked if everyone who was gay would raise their hand because they were planning a separate meeting just for gay alumni. Six attendees from our table of 26 raised their hands. I had no idea about five of them, and while my first reaction was surprise, my second was pride in the social change that’s happened over the last 25 years.</p>

<p>In just the last year, we’ve had the first male American athlete in a major sport (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jason_Collins">Jason Collins</a>) come out with near universal acceptance. The number one draft pick in the WNBA draft (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brittney_Griner">Britney Griner</a>) mentioned she was gay and hardly anyone noticed. The Supreme Court seems on the verge of legalizing gay marriage (or at least banning the states from banning gay marriage).  And my (almost) alma mater<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, Framingham High School, now has a club called the <a href="http://www.framingham.k12.ma.us/fhs_alliance.cfm">Gay/Straight Alliance</a>.</p>

<p>The reunion and the casual statements about sexual orientation by my old friends may have been a dream, but the reality is much better. Some of the healthiest and most loving couples I know are gay. Some of the best parents I know are gay. And it’s so nice that this is finally being recognized by a majority of Americans.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I actually attended Framingham South High School, but in 1991 it merged with Framingham North High School to become <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Framingham_High_School">Framingham High School</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Feeling Negative]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/25/feeling-negative/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/25/feeling-negative</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spend a lot of time on this blog raving about <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/11/kid-book-review-library-trip-report-3/">great kid books</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/02/22/not-dead-yet/">great music</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/01/17/mincer-1958/">great writing for grown ups</a>, and even <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/08/an-homage-to-chris-welty/">great teaching</a>, but don’t get the idea that I think everything is all sunshine and roses. There are plenty of things I don’t appreciate. Here are just three:</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-grateful-dead.jpg" title="[title “Maybe the Ugliest Shirt of All-Time”]" ></p>

<h2 id="the-grateful-dead">1. The Grateful Dead</h2>

<p>When I think of the Dead, the first things that come to mind are dirty feet, ugly tie-dyed shirts, drugs, and silly annoying songs that just go on and on and on.  If you’re into that sort of thing, then I’m really sorry you can’t follow them around anymore.  At least you’ve got Phish.</p>

<h2 id="ezra-jack-keats">2. Ezra Jack Keats</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/hv-willie.jpg" title="[title “Whistle for Willie”]" ></p>

<p>This is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ezra_Jack_Keats">Ezra Jack Keats</a> week at my girls’ preschool and besides <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/05/10/carle-vs-lioni/">Eric Carle</a>, there isn’t a more over-rated children’s book author/illustator.  I’m not an expert on Jack Keats, but I have read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Snowy-Day-Board-Book/dp/0670867330">The Snowy Day</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Whistle-Willie-Board-Book-Keats/dp/0670880469">Whistle for Willie</a> and thus feel perfectly justified generalizing to his whole body of work. I like that he his stories take place in cities. I like that he’s got African-American characters. And I’m not arguing he wasn’t an important trail blazer–he was. I’m just arguing that the books themselves are uninspired and boring.  In the last forty years lots of authors have taken the torch and done a better job with it. My favorites are <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Rain-Stomper-Addie-Boswell/dp/0761453938">The Rain Stomper</a> (by Boswell Addie, illustrated by Eric Velasquez), <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Corduroy-Don-Freeman/dp/0140501738">Corduroy</a> (by Don Freeman), and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bear-Bike-Stella-Blackstone/dp/1905236980">Bear on a Bike</a> (by Stella Blackstone, illustrated by Debbie Harter)</p>

<h2 id="new-orleans">3. New Orleans</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-voodoo.jpg" title="[title “VOODOO”]" ></p>

<p>For some people, New Orleans is a great city. It’s got world class sea food and its own brand of jazz. It’s got a casino downtown and a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bourbon_Street">whole street</a> full of daiquiris and debauchery. But for a vegetarian who doesn’t drink, doesn’t gamble, and whose musical tastes are a little less hip, New Orleans doesn’t have much to offer. I used to think the best thing about the city was voodoo and while that sounds all cool and mysterious, when you take a closer look, it’s not. Chicken blood, bits of hair, and stabbing little dolls to hurt real people is just creepy. Of course, there is <a href="http://www.auduboninstitute.org/visit/insectarium">the Insectarium</a> which is also a little creepy, but was a lot of fun with the girls when we visited a couple weeks ago. </p>

<p>OK, I’ll admit it: I’m not usually such a Debby Downer, but  accumulated sleep debt from a busy winter and spring has taken a toll on my normally sunny disposition. Hopefully the end of the semester will take care of this I’ll soon be back to being a Cheerful Charlie!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Expanding the Market for Limited Edition Dishes]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/03/09/dishes/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/03/09/dishes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/conan-dishes/yorkies.jpg" alt="Yorkies!" /></p>

<p>Limited edition dishes have a very limited market for two main reasons. First, they feature a very limited selection of art. Cute dogs, American flags, flowers, and Russian folk tales only appeal to so many people.  These plates are basically baseball cards for grandmas. Second, most of these dishes are designed solely for display and could actually kill you if you ate off them–this is crazy since the last time I checked normal people used dishes for serving food, not decorating their walls.  These companies need to expand their stables of artists and use nontoxic paints. </p>

<p>To get things started concretely, I propose the following set of four limited edition dinner plates by Frank Frazetta.  Imagine the look of wonder on your guests’ faces as they clear their plates and reveal the raw ferocity and masculinity of Conan the Barbarian. I know I would buy them. Click through to see them in their full resolution glory!</p>

<p><a href="/images/conan-dishes/d1.jpg"><img src="/images/conan-dishes/d1-small.jpg" alt="Conan!" /></a>
<a href="/images/conan-dishes/d2.jpg"><img src="/images/conan-dishes/d2-small.jpg" alt="Conan!" /></a>
<a href="/images/conan-dishes/d3.jpg"><img src="/images/conan-dishes/d3-small.jpg" alt="Conan!" /></a>
<a href="/images/conan-dishes/d4.jpg"><img src="/images/conan-dishes/d4-small.jpg" alt="Conan!" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Three Favorite Low Traffic Blogs]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/17/favorite-low-traffic-blogs/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/17/favorite-low-traffic-blogs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week a whole bunch of people wrote <a href="http://www.economist.com/blogs/babbage/2013/01/remembering-aaron-swartz">really</a> <a href="http://boingboing.net/2013/01/12/rip-aaron-swartz.html">nice</a> <a href="http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/philg/2013/01/12/aaron-swartz/">things</a> about an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aaron_Swartz">amazing person</a> who is no longer around to read them. Continuing in my <a href="/blog/categories/thanks/">series of thanking people who can still appreciate it</a>, these are my three favorite low traffic blogs:</p>

<h2 id="think-in-projectshttpwwwthinkinprojectscom"><a href="http://www.thinkinprojects.com">Think In Projects</a></h2>
<!---
(24 Google Reader subscribers)
--->

<p>I found out about Rafal’s blog when he commented on <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/05/27/gtd-with-rtm/">a post here</a>, but it’s quickly become my favorite source for thoughtful advice about improving personal productivity.  He reads widely and links to the best articles he finds on the topic. But the reason I keep coming back is his own writing.  For whatever reason, he and I run into very similar issues and he has practical ideas for making progress on those issues. Recently he’s written good stuff about <a href="http://www.thinkinprojects.com/productivity/celebrate-2/">the value in looking back at our accomplishments</a>, <a href="http://www.thinkinprojects.com/productivity/planning-2013/">long range planning</a>, and <a href="http://www.thinkinprojects.com/productivity/on-avoidance-of-stuff/">avoiding what’s important</a>.  He also happens to write extensively about <a href="http://www.rememberthemilk.com">Remember the Milk</a> and <a href="http://evernote.com">Evernote</a>–two tools I respect but don’t currently use.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> Think in Projects is now <a href="http://creatingpersonalflow.com/">Creating Personal Flow</a>. I love the new layout and you can find the content referenced above on the new site here:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://creatingpersonalflow.com/productivity/celebrate-2/">Celebrate</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://creatingpersonalflow.com/productivity/on-avoidance-of-stuff/">On avoidance of stuff</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://creatingpersonalflow.com/productivity/planning-2013/">Planning 2013</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="its-not-a-problem-if-you-cant-solve-ithttpsillynomadtumblrcom"><a href="http://sillynomad.tumblr.com">It’s not a problem if you can’t solve it</a></h2>
<!---
(2 Google Reader subscribers)
--->

<p>This site is written by a former student of mine from Spain who has spent big chunks of this life in Africa and is now living in Japan.  He has a unique perspective on the world and through words and photos he communicates a great sense for both the ordinary and extraordinary in Japan.  Reading his blog I often feel like I’m watching a Japanese version of the Office. Alf also partakes in a tremendous number of extracurricular activities so I get to learn all about soccer leagues, concerts, themed restaurants, and video game arcades too. And seriously, how many people do you know that have taken a <a href="http://sillynomad.tumblr.com/day/2012/12/20">field trip to Hiroshima to play Dungeons and Dragons</a>?</p>

<h2 id="byte-bakerhttpbytebakercom"><a href="http://bytebaker.com">Byte Baker</a></h2>
<!---
(118 Google Reader subscribers)
--->
<p>Shrutarshi Basu is a computer science grad student at Cornell, but I started reading his blog back when he was “just” a nerdy college kid. He writes about what he’s doing (hacking, figuring out life) and what he thinks is important (e.g., programming languages, reading, productivity). While it’s true that we do share some interests, my favorite quality of the site is Shrutarshi’s earnestness. He consciously tries to achieve excellence in whatever he does and he’s open about what’s working and what’s not.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bathroom Fan Love Letters]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/10/30/bathroom-fan-love-letters/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/10/30/bathroom-fan-love-letters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two of my favorite bloggers (<a href="http://www.marco.org">Marco Arment</a> and <a href="http://brooksreview.net">Ben Brooks</a>) recently
published passionate <a href="http://www.marco.org/2012/05/06/bathroom-fan-timer-switches">love</a> <a href="http://brooksreview.net/2012/03/amazon-item/">letters</a> to the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B003TJAGPS">Panasonic WhisperCeiling</a> bathroom
fan, and in Marco’s case, a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00313JXB0">Leviton electronic timer switch</a>.  Since
our downstairs bathroom has had no fan at all for more than a year, and
our upstairs bathroom fan sounded like a jet engine (and took 20 minutes
to de-fog a mirror), I took this as a sign that it was time to upgrade.
It was harder than expected to find an electrician to install them, but
today was the big day.  It’s worked out pretty well for our upstairs
bathroom, but not so much for the downstairs bathroom.  In fact, I was
surprised by three issues that were unmentioned in the “reviews” I read:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>The Panasonic WhisperLite fan/light combo unit is approximately
square and it doesn’t fit in our downstairs bathroom because we have a
cast-iron drain pipe running 8.5” away from the stud where the fan has
to be mounted.  Drat.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The bulbs in the WhisperLite are compact-fluorescent and they send
out a very white light.  I like it, but my wife calls it “institutional”
and she says it reminds her of a public restroom.  This isn’t exactly
where anyone wants to be taking a shower, and if she doesn’t acclimate, I’m
hoping we can just change the bulbs to something a little softer.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Leviton switch requires three wires (including a neutral) and our
downstairs bathroom only has two.  If I want a timer switch we either
spend $200 to run a new line (I’m not <em>that</em> crazy) or we get one of
those <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Intermatic-FD15MWC-15-Minute-Spring-Loaded/dp/B000EVS4WG">spring-loaded knobs</a> that screams hotel sauna.  For now, we’re
sticking with the old manual switch.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>To be fair, the new fan is very quiet and is working like a champ–our
upstairs bathroom isn’t small and during a leisurely shower the mirror
never fogged up.  And the Leviton timer is far more reliable than I was
about remembering to turn off the fan when it’s done its job.  But I
think there is a bigger lesson here: Some products that are perfect for
some people (or bathrooms) are not perfect for others, and we shouldn’t
let ourselves be blinded by the opinions of fan-bois.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
