<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[other | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/other/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-06-29T17:19:26-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sex, Drugs, and Tough Decisions]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2018/06/29/sex-drugs-tough-decisions/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2018/06/29/sex-drugs-tough-decisions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent this week as a juror in a rape trial. It was heavy. We had a really consequential decision to make and not a lot of evidence to go on:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The testimony of the defendant and the alleged victim.</strong> They both said they met each other at a bar and within a few minutes they went into the men’s bathroom to do some coke. They both said they had sex. The defendant said it was consensual. The alleged victim said she was raped. The one person they said disrupted the encounter never took the stand.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Some photos of bruises on the defendant’s right arm taken 48 hours after the incident</strong>.  These were consistent with bruises one would get from someone restraining her from behind, but the defendant did not remember being held like this. They were also yellowing which implied the injury might have occurred earlier than the incident.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>A medical report from an exam two days after the incident.</strong> There were no injuries beyond the arm bruises, but that wouldn’t be inconsistent with rape. The statement taken at the time was very similar to what the defendant said on the stand, but did differ in some important ways. In the statement she says she was “very drunk” and did not remember actual sex. On the stand, she said she was not very drunk, was well aware of what was happening, and did remember actual sex. </p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>After two days of deliberation, at least 11 of us thought it was more likely that the defendant committed rape than not. But our job was to presume innocence and only convict if the evidence convinced us beyond a reasonable doubt.</p>

<p>Could we come up with a plausible scenario that was consistent with the evidence AND consensual sex? It didn’t have to be his story, but it couldn’t be her story.  Was it plausible that she lied about what happened?  Could it be that she went along with it willingly (but not enthusiastically) and then regretted it? Could it be that she thought her friends or her boyfriend would hear about what happened? Could it be that she felt that the high price of saying it was rape was lower than the high price of her boyfriend finding out that she had consensual sex in a bar bathroom while he was away with his friends for the weekend? Yes. I think it’s unlikely, but plausible. Every other person on the jury thought it was at least plausible too. So we rendered a Not Guilty Verdict.</p>

<p>We followed the rules given to us by the judge and did our job. And we let a man who probably raped a woman go free. It doesn’t feel good, even though I’m also sure we didn’t put an innocent man in jail. I don’t want my girls to grow up in a world where, if a man is alone with a woman (in a bathroom, in a car, in bedroom, …), it’s just not that hard for him to rape her and get away with it. Especially if she’s drunk and scared. Is the burden of proof too high? Do we need to change the legal definition of consent? What can we teach our daughters to protect them? These are the questions I’m struggling with in the aftermath of this trial.</p>

<p>When you spend three days trying to imagine exactly what happened between a man and a woman in a bar bathroom, it haunts you. This isn’t like watching a movie. You’re trying to imagine yourself there. You’re thinking hard about what’s possible, what’s plausible, what’s likely, and what you know for sure. And we literally spent several hours each day for three days doing this. I wasn’t in that bathroom, but these scenes are seared into my memory. We intently studied the faces of the defendant and victim on the stand in the court room looking for clues and insights into their credibility. There are so many details I’ll never forget. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thinking about getting a unicycle?]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2016/06/04/unicycle/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2016/06/04/unicycle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>{% img /images/hv-unicycles.jpg %}</p>

<p>Some people reach midlife and buy a fancy red sports car to recapture their youth. I bought a fancy red unicycle that was on sale for Valentine’s Day at <a href="http://unicycle.com">unicycle.com</a>. I’ve since worked my way up to comfortably riding the six blocks or so between my office and my the parking lot each day. At first, the tiniest obstacles would totally throw off my balance. My messenger bag! A crack in the sidewalk! A slight turn! A breeze! I’m better now and it’s still super fun. </p>

<p>Every day I get smiles, finger points, and questions. The most common  are “Where did you get that thing?” and “Is it hard to learn?” This makes me think there’s a nontrivial population of folks out there that are intrigued by the idea of getting and riding a unicycle, but don’t quite know what’s involved or how to get started. Don’t worry–I’m here to help.</p>

<p>There are <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s?url=search-alias=aps&amp;field-keywords=unicycle">really cheap (sub $100) unicycles</a> out there, but I had one in middle school and managed to break it in just a couple months. The cheap ones also have really uncomfortable saddles. The good news is that even really nice unicycles are relatively cheap compared to bikes. Mine is a <a href="http://www.unicycle.com/unicycles/mountain-unicycle/nimbus-26-inch-mountain-unicycle-red.html">Nimbus 26” Muni</a> (“Mountain Unicycle”). They cost $360 and are completely bomb-proof. The knobby tires look cool and it’s fun to be able to ride on dirt roads and grass.</p>

<p>If you’re pretty tall, then get a 26” wheel; otherwise get one with a 24” wheel. Anything smaller and you’ll be riding slower than you walk. If money isn’t a serious issue and you want something to ride around town, get a <a href="http://www.unicycle.com/unicycles/road-26-28-29-inch/nimbus-ii-26-inch-unicycle-blue.html">Nimbus II</a> ($290)–It’s pretty darned similar to my Muni but with a smooth tire. If you’re on a budget, get a <a href="http://www.unicycle.com/unicycles/road-26-28-29-inch/club-26-inch-road-red-unicycle.html">Club 26”</a> ($150). The learning curve with any unicycle is steep, but you make a little progress each day. It might take several weeks before you can ride, and that makes the per hour cost super low.</p>

<p>So what’s the upshot of all of this? Just go to <a href="http://unicycle.com">unicycle.com</a>, buy one, and invest some time in learning to ride. You won’t regret it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zebras and Expertise on the Internet]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/12/07/zebras-and-expertise-on-the-internet/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/12/07/zebras-and-expertise-on-the-internet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Internet is full of people talking about stuff they don’t know much about. It’s common at <a href="https://answers.yahoo.com">Yahoo Answers</a> and <a href="http://www.answers.com">Answers.com</a>, but <a href="http://amazon.com">Amazon</a> reviews and <a href="https://www.wikipedia.org">Wikipedia</a> are rife with it too. Even when bloggers are experts in one area, they often write much more broadly. As <a href="http://idlewords.com/about.htm">Maclej Ceglowski</a> delightfully points out in <a href="http://www.idlewords.com/2005/04/dabblers_and_blowhards.htm">his article about Paul Graham’s lack of expertise on painting</a>, even the top of the food chain is not immune. </p>

<p>I think it’s fantastic. You don’t need to be an expert to have something interesting to say. Regular people notice things experts don’t, and they often have a perspective closer to mine. Non-experts can also be <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Funniest-Amazon-Product-Reviews/lm/RM0256CJKINZJ">incredibly entertaining</a>.</p>

<p>As a consumer I’m careful not to take anything too seriously, but many folks are more trusting than me of the average blogger. As a producer, I worry about this all the time, as I love thinking and writing about things on the edge (or well over the edge) of my expertise. When I wildly speculate I try to be clear about it, but I feel a little bad that some readers might not notice. </p>

<p>It has turned out that the most common way for people to find this site is by searching for “are zebras mean” or “do zebras bite.” I don’t know jack about this subject, but that didn’t stop me from writing <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/01/why-are-zebras-so-mean-and-horses-so-nice/">a few hundred words about it</a> a couple years ago.  African Safari guide <a href="http://www.quora.com/Rory-Young-1">Rory Young</a> recently wrote <a href="http://www.quora.com/Can-zebras-be-domesticated-and-trained/answer/Rory-Young-1">a terrific article on Quora</a> that shares real knowledge about why zebras can be so nasty.  It makes me very happy to be able to send my potentially disappointed visitors on to some real answers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Subscribe via email]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/04/subscribe-via-email/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/04/subscribe-via-email</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am happy to report that you can now to subscribe to <a href="http://highvariance.net">High Variance</a> by email. Just look under the <strong>Follow</strong> heading on the right side of any page, fill in your email address, and press the <strong>Follow this site via email</strong> button. <a href="https://blogtrottr.com">Blogtrottr</a> will send you a confirmation message, and then you’ll get every new article emailed to you within an hour of it going live. If you prefer, you can still subscribe to the site’s <a href="http://highvariance.net/rss/index.xml">RSS feed</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/intent/user?screen_name=HighVarianceNet">follow me on Twitter</a> for updates.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wawa: Philadelphia's Hidden Jewel]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/19/wawa/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/19/wawa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>{% img /images/hv-wawa.jpg %}</p>

<p>I recently made a quick return visit to Philadelphia and rediscovered one of my favorite Philly institutions. It wasn’t the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liberty_bell">Liberty Bell</a>, the <a href="http://www.visitphilly.com/music-art/philadelphia/love-statue/">Love sculpture</a>, or even the <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/04/06/tetris-skyscraper_n_5099208.html">giant tetris tower</a>. It was <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wawa,_Inc.">Wawa</a>: the world’s greatest convenience store. What makes it so much better than 7-Eleven, ampm, or even the recently departed <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_Hen">White Hen</a>? Two things:</p>

<!--more-->

<ol>
  <li>Wawa has the high tech efficiency of a Japanese factory. They do everything they can possibly think of to get you exactly what you want as fast as possible. When you want a fresh sandwich (or bagel or breakfast burrito or anything else that needs preparation) you don’t wait in line and talk to an error prone human. Instead, you tap your way through a perfectly designed touch screen interface and when you finish, your receipt is instantly printed. While you pay for your order (and anything else), they make your food. Wawa is always packed, but no one is ever waiting for anything.</li>
  <li>Wawa has their finger on the pulse of America. Do Americans want roller hot dogs or stale donuts? No! We want fresh baked goods and 10 flavors of fresh-brewed coffee. Do we want two choices for liquid additives for our coffee? No! We want to choose between skim, 1%, 2%, whole, half-and-half, full-on-cream, and three different non-dairy creamers. And they all better be on ice. Wawa is on the cutting edge of smoothies and fancy iced coffee drinks too. At the same time, they’ve got a great selection of sodas, candy, and medicine.</li>
</ol>

<p>I admit I’m a little biased. My three-year-old and I enjoyed playing find the “Wawa” in the store (not a hard game given the number of self-branded items) while listening to a continuous stream of 80’s music (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BoXu6QmxpJE">Everybody Wang Chung Tonight!</a>). Even so, I’m perplexed. Why is America outside of Philadelphia almost completely deprived of the Wawa experience? It made sense before 2008 when the Phillies <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008_World_Series">won the World Series</a> and the city needed <em>something</em> to be proud of. But now? Nothing should be stopping Wawa from total world domination.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
