<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[other | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/other/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-19T10:56:51-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Subscribe via email]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/04/subscribe-via-email/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/06/04/subscribe-via-email</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am happy to report that you can now to subscribe to <a href="http://highvariance.net">High Variance</a> by email. Just look under the <strong>Follow</strong> heading on the right side of any page, fill in your email address, and press the <strong>Follow this site via email</strong> button. <a href="https://blogtrottr.com">Blogtrottr</a> will send you a confirmation message, and then you’ll get every new article emailed to you within an hour of it going live. If you prefer, you can still subscribe to the site’s <a href="http://highvariance.net/rss/index.xml">RSS feed</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/intent/user?screen_name=HighVarianceNet">follow me on Twitter</a> for updates.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wawa: Philadelphia's Hidden Jewel]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/19/wawa/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/19/wawa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-wawa.jpg"></p>

<p>I recently made a quick return visit to Philadelphia and rediscovered one of my favorite Philly institutions. It wasn’t the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liberty_bell">Liberty Bell</a>, the <a href="http://www.visitphilly.com/music-art/philadelphia/love-statue/">Love sculpture</a>, or even the <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/04/06/tetris-skyscraper_n_5099208.html">giant tetris tower</a>. It was <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wawa,_Inc.">Wawa</a>: the world’s greatest convenience store. What makes it so much better than 7-Eleven, ampm, or even the recently departed <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_Hen">White Hen</a>? Two things:</p>

<!--more-->

<ol>
  <li>Wawa has the high tech efficiency of a Japanese factory. They do everything they can possibly think of to get you exactly what you want as fast as possible. When you want a fresh sandwich (or bagel or breakfast burrito or anything else that needs preparation) you don’t wait in line and talk to an error prone human. Instead, you tap your way through a perfectly designed touch screen interface and when you finish, your receipt is instantly printed. While you pay for your order (and anything else), they make your food. Wawa is always packed, but no one is ever waiting for anything.</li>
  <li>Wawa has their finger on the pulse of America. Do Americans want roller hot dogs or stale donuts? No! We want fresh baked goods and 10 flavors of fresh-brewed coffee. Do we want two choices for liquid additives for our coffee? No! We want to choose between skim, 1%, 2%, whole, half-and-half, full-on-cream, and three different non-dairy creamers. And they all better be on ice. Wawa is on the cutting edge of smoothies and fancy iced coffee drinks too. At the same time, they’ve got a great selection of sodas, candy, and medicine.</li>
</ol>

<p>I admit I’m a little biased. My three-year-old and I enjoyed playing find the “Wawa” in the store (not a hard game given the number of self-branded items) while listening to a continuous stream of 80’s music (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BoXu6QmxpJE">Everybody Wang Chung Tonight!</a>). Even so, I’m perplexed. Why is America outside of Philadelphia almost completely deprived of the Wawa experience? It made sense before 2008 when the Phillies <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008_World_Series">won the World Series</a> and the city needed <em>something</em> to be proud of. But now? Nothing should be stopping Wawa from total world domination.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Extreme Bird Watching]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/02/extreme-bird-watching/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/04/02/extreme-bird-watching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-dead-fish.jpg"></p>

<p>Spring has finally arrived in Connecticut. The snow is gone, replaced by snowdrops and crocuses, and the birds have returned. We’ve had great fun watching robins, bluejays, and red-winged blackbirds pulling on worms and building nests, and hearing their songs fill the air. </p>

<p>On the way home from school the other day we got an extra-special treat. As we drove by the reservoir, two hawks<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> flew over the car fighting over something. The birds were big and their prey was big too. The hawks dipped and dove and then lost control of their prize, letting it fall right into the street in front of us. </p>

<p>When it bounced and rolled to a stop we saw it was a huge fish!  The whole rest of our trip home we wondered if the fish would still be there the next day and since it was a pretty busy street, hoped we wouldn’t see a road-killed hawk (or two) lying near by.</p>

<p>The next morning we were never so happy to see a dead fish all alone by the side of the road. We had to pull over so everyone could get out to take a closer look. Whoever said bird watching was boring?</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Maybe they were ospreys, but we get a lot of red-tailed hawks around here and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red-tailed_Hawk#Diet">Wikipedia</a> says they do occasionally eat fish.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Little Pony: Revelation]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/02/27/mlp-revelations/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/02/27/mlp-revelations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a rough winter filled with snow days and sickness and not enough sleep. Tonight the wind is howling and the temperature is supposed to drop to the single digits. To get us in the mood for spring, the girls and I hunkered down in front of YouTube to hear Twilight Sparkle and the rest of the My Little Ponies sing “Winter Wrap-up”.</p>

<!--- My Little Pony: "Winter Wrap-up
--->
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://highvariance.net//www.youtube.com/embed/dyrAkwJ6WsY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>In the video, the ponies are also tired of winter and are preparing for spring. Actually, scratch that, they aren’t getting ready for spring–they have decided it’s time for spring and they are physically bringing it into being. The Pegasus ponies are annihilating the storm clouds and removing the snow from roofs and trees. Apple Jack and the other earth ponies are plowing the snow off the fields and lakes, and planting seeds. Fluttershy is waking up all the hibernating animals with a little bell. That’s when it hit me: These ponies are not mere cartoon characters at all–They’re gods!</p>

<p>The rulers of Equestria (Princess Celestia and Princess Luna) are obviously the old gods of the Sun and Moon. I’m surprised they aren’t named Princess <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ra">Ra</a> and Princess <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khonsu">Khonsu</a>. It also turns out each of the <a href="http://mlp.wikia.com/wiki/Characters#Main_characters">Mane Six</a> ponies has a clear analog in Greek mythology:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Twilight Sparkle is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Athena">Athena</a>, Goddess of Wisdom. </li>
  <li>Pinkie Pie is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dionysus">Dionysus</a>, God of ritual madness and ecstasy–aka partying.</li>
  <li>Rainbow Dash is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hermes">Hermes</a>–the winged messenger of the gods who is quick and cunning and patron of athletics and sports.</li>
  <li>Apple Jack is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demeter">Demeter</a>, Goddess of the Harvest.</li>
  <li>Rarity is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aphrodite">Aphrodite</a>, Goddess of Beauty and Love.</li>
  <li>Fluttershy is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artemis">Artemis</a>, Protector of the Animals.</li>
</ul>

<p>I think spring had better come soon before I go completely insane.</p>

<p>Hurry up ponies!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Three Pieces of Stat Nerd Trivia]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/02/14/stat-nerd-trivia/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/02/14/stat-nerd-trivia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve recently learned three bits of trivia that only a statistics nerd could love. They won’t help you think deeply about data. They won’t help you analyze data. In fact, they’ll probably push useful knowledge out of your head and make you dumber. Read further at your own risk.</p>

<p><strong>1. Where does the word “logit” come from?</strong></p>

<p>One of the earliest probablistic models of a binary process is the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Probit">probit</a>. It was developed by Chester Bliss in 1934, and in this paper he coined the term as a shortening of the phrase “probability unit”. The idea is that a one unit increase in an independent variable changes the probability of the outcome occurring by a constant number of probability units. Probits can be translated into actual probabilities using a particular non-linear transformation: the cumulative distribution function of the standard normal. That is, we have:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\Pr(y_i) = \Phi(\beta_0 + \beta_1 x_i)
</script>

<p>In 1944, Joseph Berkson developed a similar model that also mapped the real line to the (0,1) interval, this time using the logistic function:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\Pr(y_i) = \frac{\exp(\beta_0 + \beta_1 x_i)}{1 + \exp(\beta_0 + \beta_1 x_i)}
</script>

<p>By analogy, this model was given the name logit.</p>

<p><strong>2. Why does Stata store dates as the number of days since January 1, 1960?</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://www.dur.ac.uk/geography/staff/geogstaffhidden/?id=335">Nick Cox</a> knows a lot about <a href="http://www.stata.com">Stata</a>, and even he does not know exactly why this date was chosen as the origin for internal dates. His <a href="http://www.stata.com/statalist/archive/2003-08/msg00379.html">best guess</a> is that it was copied from “some data base or spreadsheet program”. My guess is that Stata copied SAS which uses the same date as the date-time origin. </p>

<p>This led me to wonder why SAS chose the date, and Derek Morgan (in <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=s1h94CZjGCEC&amp;pg=PA2">The Essential Guide to SAS Dates and Times</a>) says “One story has it that the founders of SAS wanted to use the approximate birth date of the IBM 370 system, and they chose January 1, 1960 as an easy-to-remember approximation.” According to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epoch_(reference_date)#Notable_epoch_dates_in_computing">Wikipedia</a> S-Plus also uses the same reference date.</p>

<p><strong>3. How are we supposed to pronounce McNemar’s test?</strong></p>

<p>Suppose you have a set of matched pairs of observations and want to know if the distribution of some categorical outcome is the same for each side of the pair. You should use <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McNemar_test">McNemar’s test</a> to see if the observed differences are statistically significant.
I went years pronouncing <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quinn_McNemar">Quinn McNemar</a>’s name as “mik-nee’-mahr” and getting likely getting laughed at behind my back by biostatisticians. It turns out the <a href="http://www.medilexicon.com/medicaldictionary.php?t=90653">proper pronunciation</a> is “mak’ne-mahr”. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ax265c6pqvA">Ashwini Kalantri</a> pronounces it well as he explains how it works.</p>

<p><strong>Note:</strong> The pretty math equations are rendered with <a href="http://www.mathjax.org">Mathjax</a> and integrating this with Javascript was trivial thanks to <a href="http://www.lucypark.kr/blog/2013/02/25/mathjax-kramdown-and-octopress/">Lucy Park</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
