<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tech | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/tech/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-23T00:38:51-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exams and Online Classes]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/08/23/exams-and-online-classes/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/08/23/exams-and-online-classes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With just a few exceptions, no one likes exams.  Students don’t like the stress of taking the exams, instructors have to write the exams, and someone usually has to grade them. In-class exams don’t give enough time for testing very much material, and if the test is too long, it punishes students who know their stuff but are just a little slow. Take-home exams can cover more content, but it can be very tempting for students to cheat by getting help from friends or the Internet. Unfortunately, we need objective assessments of how much each student has mastered the course material, and right now exams are the best tool we have.</p>

<p>In an online class, exams are even trickier.  In my econometrics class this summer, we held our midterm and final exams in the virtual classroom.  At exam time, I emailed them a PDF with all the questions and my students wrote their answers on paper while my teaching assistant and I watched them through their webcams. We used pencil and paper because answering the questions required doing a fair amount of math and I wanted to see their work.  I didn’t want them to use valuable time slowly typing in symbols and equations. After two hours, they scanned their written answers (mostly with their phone cameras) and emailed them to me.  When I confirmed receipt and readability, the students were free to go.  </p>

<p>The process was easy and convenient, but had one major flaw: it would have been pretty easy to cheat. I say this believing in my heart that none of my students cheated and having absolutely no evidence to even make me suspicious.  Even so, any one of them could have forwarded the exam PDF to a friend (or professional) and had them email back their answers.  The incentives for doing so are actually quite strong: Yale classes are not cheap and they get real Yale credit for my online class. Not to mention the fact that most elite college students care a lot about their GPA.</p>

<p>A second problem we ran into was that students’ Internet connections were not always reliable.  When these connections dropped, some students didn’t even notice for a while and others had trouble reconnecting.  It wouldn’t have been fair to just disqualify those students, but again, it was a pretty huge opportunity to cheat. </p>

<p>We considered three alternative testing procedures, but I think only one would be a clear improvement over what we did.  First, we thought about requiring students to have a separate webcam that would let us view their computer screen.  In this scenario, they couldn’t use their computer for evil, but I still think it would be relatively easy for them to cheat with an alternative device outside the frame of view.  Second, we investigated using an online service that locks down their computer for only exam taking purposes. <a href="https://webassessor.com">Webassessor</a> provides this service along with online proctors, but it would also require good webcam placement.  And both of these alternatives are still reliant on continuous connection to the Internet.</p>

<p>The solution I like best is to use an in-person testing service where students go to a controlled physical location to take their exam.  <a href="https://www.prometric.com">Prometric</a> has more than 10,000 test taking centers all over the world–that means a huge fraction of the world’s population is within two hours drive of a center so it’s not all that inconvenient to travel to one one or two times during a course.</p>

<p>Timing is an issue for all these solutions–that is, you’d like all your students to take the exam simultaneously so the early students can’t share information with those that take the exam later.  If your students are scattered around the globe, at least some of them will have to take their exam in the middle of the night and that doesn’t seem fair.  My students in the far east had to take their exams at either 10pm or 11pm.  One way around this problem would be to have two versions of the exam–one for each half of the planet.</p>

<p>Next time I teach an online class where the stakes are high, I’m going to try to use a service like Prometric.  I’ll let you know how it goes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Opposite of a MOOC]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/07/24/opposite-of-a-mooc/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/07/24/opposite-of-a-mooc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>MOOC’s are Massive Open Online Courses and they are what everyone in higher education is talking about. These classes  are usually free, have huge enrollments, and per student are pretty cheap to run relative to a typical college class. The quality can be decent and MOOC’s open up access to higher education to literally billions of people around the world. MOOC’s also have the potential to decrease the cost of education for the millions of people that would normally attend a traditional in person college.</p>

<p>Yale currently allows anyone on the Internet to watch record lectures from many of its best classes through <a href="http://oyc.yale.edu">Yale Open Courses</a>, but with zero interactivity, the user experience is quite different from taking a “real” course.  Yale has also recently entered a relationship with Coursera, the leading MOOC provider, and plans to dip its foot in the MOOC pool this year with a few classes.</p>

<p>At the same time, Yale has been breaking new ground through its Summer Session online classes which aim to let students experience as close to an in-person class as you can get without being on campus. These classes mix recorded video lectures with the usual outside-class reading and problem sets and a live interactive video session with the professor and rest of the class.</p>

<p>It’s these live sessions that are really innovative for online learning.  When a student logs in, they see everyone else in the class including the professor in a virtual classroom.  Imagine a Google Hangout with up to 25 participants.  It requires everyone to have a decent internet connection, but when it works, it’s kind of amazing. </p>

<p>It would be impossible to scale up this type of course to “massive” numbers of students, but the idea is to maximize quality, not minimize price.  I call it a Small Closed Online Course, and while Yale started offering these online classes two summers ago, I’m in the middle of teaching my first one now.  It’s “Econometrics and Data Analysis” and it’s been a real learning experience for everyone so far.</p>

<p>Students can take the class from almost anywhere.  I have students logging in three times a week from China, Singapore, Madrid, Kentucky, Alberta, California, and even a couple from downtown New Haven, CT. They can watch the video lectures when it is convenient for them and they have the power to pause and replay parts that are not clear the first time through.</p>

<p>The live experience is a work in progress. I use it to do three substantive things.  First, I answer questions about the recorded material and the reading.  It seems clear that my students are not taking notes and writing down questions they cannot ask in the moment (as they would in an in-person class) because most days they don’t have any questions. It’s hard to know how if they are really engaging with the recorded lectures or if they have them on while they’re doing something else. For the past couple classes I’ve been asking them basic questions about the material to get a sense for how much is sinking in. I am thinking about requiring them to email questions before the live session begins.</p>

<p>The main thing I do in the live sessions is have my students work through problems together.  The software we are using (<a href="http://watchitoo.com">Watchitoo</a>) allows me to divide the class into groups and send them to sub-classrooms.  I visit each of the groups in turn and push them along when they get stuck. It’s classic <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flipped_classroom">flipped classroom</a> stuff and it works well.</p>

<p>The third thing we do is discuss the material. I haven’t done much of this so far, but I have some future classes planned where we go over new applications of methods and talk in depth about specific points.  Most of Yale’s online classes thus far have been discussion-oriented (e.g., psychology or philosophy), but econometrics is much closer to a math class and thus not as good a match for discussions.</p>

<p>The technology has mostly worked well but has some real rough edges. Some students just don’t have strong enough internet connections and drop in and out during the live sessions. Moving between the sub-classrooms and the full classroom takes several more mouse clicks and time than I’d like. The whiteboard built into the live session software is too buggy to use, but we’ve had great success with a free HTML-based shared whiteboard (<a href="http://awwapp.com">awwapp.com</a>) I have the live session in one window on my laptop and my whiteboard in another window on my Wacom external monitor.  This lets me write with a real stylus and still see all my students.</p>

<p>One of the most successful parts of the class is my office hours.  I hold them in the same virtual classroom and use the same virtual whiteboard.  It’s almost identical to my in-person office hours.  Realtime access to an expert is the biggest difference between this class and a MOOC.</p>

<p>I’m getting a fair bit of feedback on how much they’re learning from their problem sets and the live sessions, but I miss being able to look into their eyes while I’m lecturing. We have our first exam this week, and I honestly don’t know how they are going to do.  My fingers are crossed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Google Reader Replacement: The Nerderati Have Spoken]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/06/30/a-google-reader-replacement-the-nerderati-have-spoken/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/06/30/a-google-reader-replacement-the-nerderati-have-spoken</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For those readers who didn’t know why it was a big deal,
<a href="http://reader.google.com">Google Reader</a> was two really cool but
distinct things. First, it was a web site where you could specify a
large number of other web sites (aka “feeds”) that publish articles you
might want to read. It would then present those articles all together in
a neat list.  It would keep track of what was new, what you hadn’t read
yet, and what you’d already read. And it was far far more efficient than
going from site to site hitting refresh like a rat pressing a lever for
another hit of crack. This is especially true for people (like me) that
read a lot of sites that don’t publish very often or can go through long
dry spells.</p>

<p>I found the Google Reader web site kind of clunky and ugly, but you didn’t
actually have to ever visit it to experience the benefits. Google Reader
also provided a service so that third party apps could access the same
data and keep your subscriptions in sync if you used apps on different
PC’S or post-PC devices. This is what I used to do, and it was
fantastic. I would use the beautiful/fast/powerful
<a href="http://reederapp.com">Reeder</a> app on my phone, Mac, and iPad to browse
my feeds wherever I was. I even used the Google Reader website
occasionally.</p>

<p>And then Google announced they were shutting it all down on July 1.
Panic ensued, but the nerderati told us to be patient–they promised
even better alternatives would quickly blossom to take its place.  It
took a few months, but they were right. Unfortunately, I’ve had a busy
spring and summer and haven’t had the time to try them all to find the
best one.  Luckily, lots of other folks have invested their time
and I think there’s a decent consensus for a winner.</p>

<p>David Sparks at
<a href="http://macsparky.com/blog/2013/6/my-rss-setup">MacSparky</a>, Federico
Vittici at
<a href="http://www.macstories.net/news/readkit-and-slow-feeds-updated-with-feed-wrangler-support/">MacStories</a>,
<a href="http://shawnblanc.net/2013/06/feed-wrangler-smart-streams/">Shawn
Blanc</a>,
<a href="http://www.marco.org/2013/06/28/drang-feeds">Marco Arment</a>, and
<a href="http://www.leancrew.com/all-this/2013/06/feedle-dee-dee/">Dr. Drang</a>
have all settled on Feed Wrangler.  It’s a service that offers all the
features Google Reader did.  It costs $19.99 per year, but that’s a
small price to pay for stability.  With paying customers, they won’t
have nearly the temptation to just turn it off if they don’t feel like
running it anymore.  They won’t be shoving ads down our throat either
which I always felt was just around the corner with Google Reader.</p>

<p>Feed Wrangler has a web site for reading and also provides free client
apps for the iPhone and iPad.  The iPhone client has some serious
flaws. It’s definitely slower to sync new stuff than Reeder was. It
doesn’t support gestures to mark things read or unread.  And worst of
all, the default (unchangeable) font size is too small for me to read
unless I’m wearing my reading glasses. Thank goodness my old standby
Reeder will be supporting Feed Wrangler soon.  I don’t read much on my
iPad, but Mr. Reader already supports the Feed Wrangler service.</p>

<p>Perhaps the best part about Feed Wrangler is the two things it does that
Google Reader never did.  Smart Streams let you define “collections” of
articles based on keywords and sources.  It’s much more powerful than a
folder and will let me sip from the high volume feeds that I would normally
stay away from. Filters are the opposite–you can define key words that
will cause an article to be automatically considered read and thus
ignored.  This way I can subscribe to the ESPN feed and never have to
read another story about hockey or NASCAR.  Bill Simmons’ <a href="http://sports.espn.go.com/espn/page2/story?page=simmonsnfl2010/101105">ESPN
Outsider</a>
has arrived!</p>

<p>Google Reader is dead, but it was stagnant for years.  I’m legitimately excited about
a new era of innovation. Feed Wrangler has just won round one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Photo Management Quest, Part 1: Adobe Revel and Everpix]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/30/pq1-adobe-revel-and-everpix/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/04/30/pq1-adobe-revel-and-everpix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am frustrated and I know I’m not the only one. I want
want a photo management system that requires minimum maintenance and gives me maximum flexibility. I’ve complained about this <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/09/im-not-happy/">before</a>, but I’m tired of waiting for Apple to hand me a gift-wrapped solution.  They didn’t last summer in iOS 6 and I have no faith that they will in iOS 7.</p>

<p>In my household, we take most of our photos with our phones, but we also have a big digital SLR which we break out for big events (if we remember to). Ideally, all our pictures would be automatically whisked away into a shared database in the cloud as soon as they are taken. From there we should be able to browse, organize, edit, and share them from any of our device, be they Macs, PC’s, iPads, or iPhones. In 2013, I don’t think that’s unreasonable to ask for.</p>

<p>In the next few weeks, I’ll be looking at several products and hopefully finding answers.  Today the journey starts with two separate app/service combos.  One is Adobe Revel and the other is Everpix.</p>

<h2 id="adobe-revelhttpwwwadoberevelcom"><a href="http://www.adoberevel.com">Adobe Revel</a></h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-adobe-revel.png"></p>

<p>I was super-excited when I heard about Adobe Revel.  The service stores all your pictures in the cloud, and they give you free iOS and Mac apps to edit and manage them. Pictures are streamed to your iOS devices as needed freeing up a whole lot of space.  The apps are (supposedly) built on top of the same editing/browsing engine powering LightRoom and they are (actually) very well done.  The service is expensive ($5.99/month) but it promises a lot.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, it’s missing some important features.  First, it won’t store video clips and that means I need an entirely different workflow for them.  With two little kids, we take lots of these “long photos” and I like having them mixed in with the traditional photos. Second, my wife lives in a Windows world and Revel doesn’t provide a Windows app or even a web app. That means she can only browse our library on her phone and that’s a show stopper.</p>

<h2 id="everpixhttpwwweverpixcom"><a href="http://www.everpix.com">Everpix</a></h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-everpix.png"></p>

<p>After my experience with Revel, I was cautiously optimistic about Everpix. It also stores all your photos in the cloud and has terrific iOS apps for browsing your collection, but it differentiates itself in three ways:</p>

<ol>
  <li>They automatically import photos from lots of places you might care about including your photo roll, Facebook, Instagram, and Flickr. That’s nice, but not terribly useful for me since I’m not exactly tied into the social network world.</li>
  <li>They have a terrific web app that works well on Mac and Windows.</li>
  <li>They don’t allow you to create albums or tag photos but instead rely on “science” to organize your photos for you.  Since I always plan to do more manual organization than I actually do, it’s nice that this is done for me. I tend to take several pictures of the same thing but never delete the bad ones–Everpix does a decent job picking the good ones and showing you those first.  In fact, I have Everpix configured to email me “random” “reminder” pictures from my collection everyday and it’s a lot of fun.</li>
</ol>

<p>The package is expensive ($4.99/month) if you want them to store more than the previous year’s worth of photos, and I’d be happy to pay if it weren’t for the downsides:</p>

<ol>
  <li>They don’t store video clips.</li>
  <li>You can’t edit pictures within the apps.</li>
  <li>They don’t store original images. Instead, Everpix stores compressed versions. I’m no photo snob, but I also don’t like losing information.</li>
  <li>You can’t easily export pictures. Once your pictures are inside, you can only get them out piece meal. I hate <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vendor_lock-in">lock-in</a>.</li>
</ol>

<p>I’m keeping an eye on Everpix because except for the editing, these issues seem eminently fixable and I’d consider using an external editor if I had to.</p>

<p>The quest continues.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Another Step on My Way to Paperless Nirvana: The Fujitsu ScanSnap iX500]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/03/07/scansnap/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/03/07/scansnap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-paper-folders.jpg" alt="My old paper folder stand" />
<img src="/images/hv-scansnap.jpg" alt="My snazzy new ScanSnap ix500" /></p>

<p>I first heard about how great document scanners are from David Sparks and Katie Floyd on the <a href="http://macpowerusers.com">Mac Power Users Podcast</a>. A little while later I read David’s ebook <a href="http://macsparky.com/paperless/">Paperless</a> where he describes many more ways to use a document scanner and raved particularly about Fujitsu’s line of ScanSnaps. Then just a few weeks ago I read a <a href="http://macsparky.com/blog/2013/1/the-fujitsu-scansnap-ix500">mini review/announcement</a> of the <a href="http://www.fujitsu.com/us/services/computing/peripherals/scanners/scansnap/scansnap-iX500.html">ScanSnap iX500</a> on David’s blog (<a href="http://macsparky.com">Mac Sparky</a>). You may be noticing a pattern here. If ScanSnap owners are a cult, then David Sparks must surely be a high priest.</p>

<p>My current workflow doesn’t generate a whole lot of paper, but that doesn’t mean I don’t have file cabinets full of paper. Most of it just sits there, but occasionally I want to look at an old bill or a marked up article.  In the best case sceneario it takes me a while to find it and more often I’m not even in the office where it resides. I’ve always wanted instant searchable secure access to this stuff from anywhere. This was especially true for the slow steady stream of paper that arrives in the mail and would eventually find a home in a physical folder in one of these cabinets.</p>

<p>After reading David’s review, I pulled the trigger and ordered a Fujitsu ScanSnap iX500.  I liked that it could be plugged into a Mac or a Windows PC or even nothing at all since it could talk to a wifi network.  Alas, David was right that this stuff didn’t matter since at the end of the day it’s just plugged into my Mac and sits next to it on my desk. That said, it’s been great.  I just plop an article on it and press a button. It scans both sides of pages simultaneously and recognizes when one side is blank. When the pages have print on them, it’s smart enough to rotate them right side up. It’s been very robust to some very crinkly drocuments. And it can gobble up 25 pages per minute.</p>

<p>I’ve been using it for three distinct tasks so far:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>When prepping classes or doing brainstorming for a research project, I sometimes use pen and paper.  When I’m done, I just feed it to the ScanSnap and drop the resulting pdf into my carefully engineered hierarchy of documents. The actual paper disappears into the recycling bin. I do the same thing with articles that I’ve printed and marked up in the past. It’s unnecessary with recent articles since I now <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/30/progress-toward-paperless/">do all my markup digitally</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I keep a folder of pdf’s that I want to read and when something paper comes my way that I want to save for later, I just scan it and drop it into this folder.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>My favorite things to scan are bills, reference manuals, receipts, and miscellaneous records that usually (but not always) arrive in the mail. I make the Scanner OCR the documents as it reads them in and just drop them into my “reference” folder. Usually I give them descriptive filenames, but I don’t need to since Spotlight indexes all the OCR’ed text making them remarkably easy to find when I need them. And since the folder is on Dropbox, I can search it on any Mac that shares the folder.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> We still have our file cabinets of paper at home and I’ve still got 5 drawers full of it at work, but very little new paper is entering those drawers and I’m even removing stuff as needed.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/images/hv-printer.jpg" alt="My old HP printer" />
<img src="/images/hv-plant.jpg" alt="My beautiful new palm tree!" /></p>

<p>The scanner hasn’t been my only recent step on the path to paperless. I’ve also evicted my office printer and replaced it with a palm tree. It’s so much prettier and never smells bad. It sequesters carbon and doesn’t use electricity. And watering a plant feels so much better than replacing toner cartridges. Both the scanner and the tree are highly recommended!</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Dropbox will propogate the metadata that stores the OCR’ed text, but won’t search it from their web interface. Someday maybe they will.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
