<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tech | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/tech/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-30T23:44:28-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scratching my nerd itch with Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/29/scratching-my-nerd-itch/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/29/scratching-my-nerd-itch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I started this blog, I chose a platform that would give me a site that looked fine out of the box so I could concentrate on the writing.  <a href="http://www.tumblr.com">Tumblr</a> fit this requirement and even provided several nice features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Built-in search</li>
  <li>Organization with tags so visitors could easily find articles by category</li>
  <li>Easy integration with Disqus comments</li>
  <li>Built-in <a href="http://www.usa.gov/Topics/Reference-Shelf/Libraries/RSS-Library/What-Is-RSS.shtml">RSS feed</a> for those who want to subscribe</li>
  <li>Automatic announcement of new articles to Facebook</li>
  <li>Easy integration with <a href="http://www.google.com/analytics/">Google Analytics</a> (for traffic statistics)</li>
</ul>

<p>Now, a year later, I have more of a vision for what I want to do with the site and I’m ready to tinker a bit. Unfortunately, while there’s some flexibility in how a Tumblr site looks, but they don’t give you any real control. Ever since high school I’ve spent regular chunks of time writing code and bending computers to my will. I’ve done this as a professional software developer, as a research economist, and often just messing around. The last year has been less geeky than usual as I’ve concentrated on teaching and less technical research projects.  It’s time to scratch my nerd itch.</p>

<p>I’ve chosen to switch to a particularly nerdy blog platform (<a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a>) that requires using command-line tools, but it has the huge benefit of total control. Octopress is built on top of <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll#readme">Jekyll</a> which is written in <a href="http://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</a> and I can tweek it as much as I’d like. I’ve always wanted to learn Ruby and reading and modifying other other people’s code is a great way to learn a language.</p>

<p>In addition to Octopress/Jekyll/Ruby, this project gets me up to speed on several other modern nerdy technologies:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://mxcl.github.com/homebrew/">Homebrew</a> is a package manager for MacOS that lets you install all sorts of open source software including the latest version of Ruby.</li>
  <li><a href="http://git-scm.com">git</a> is what version control will look like for years to come–it’s fast, collaborative, distributed, and flexible.</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com">Github</a> is where all the coolest open source projects live these days.  Any new software I write that I want to share will go here.    </li>
  <li><a href="http://sass-lang.com">Sass</a> (Syntactically Awesome Style Sheets) is a powerful layer on top of CSS (Cascading Style Sheets) that allows for powerful adaptive layout of HTML pages.</li>
</ul>

<p>While Octopress is in part an excuse to fiddle with new tech, it also feels very comfortable as articles are written in <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown</a>–a very lightweight text-based markup language that I lately find myself using for almost everything.</p>

<h2 id="whats-new">What’s New?</h2>

<p>On the surface, the site shouldn’t look all that different, but beyond the engine being replaced, there are several subtle changes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A real <a href="http://highvariance.net/about.html">About</a> page</li>
  <li>Links up top for the main categories I tend to write about</li>
  <li>A search bar near the top of every page</li>
  <li>Quick links to my recent posts and my favorite posts.</li>
  <li>Much better layout for mobile devices</li>
  <li>Super-fast rendering since Octopress generates the whole site as static HTML which just sits on the server</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="was-it-easy-to-migrate-from-tumblr">Was it Easy to Migrate from Tumblr?</h2>

<p>Two things helped a lot: The Octopress documentation is excellent and I already had all the articles on my local machine in Markdown. The only thing that was tricky was backwards compatibility as I wanted all my old URL’s to work and all my discussions to transfer over.  I used the <a href="https://github.com/tsmango/jekyll_alias_generator">alias-generator</a> plugin and a little elbow grease to make all my Tumblr URL’s redirect to my new URL’s.   </p>

<p>Disqus (the service that keeps track of comments) says they will crawl your new site and use any redirects it provides to update their database.  Unfortunately, while <em>browsers</em> can understand the redirects that the alias-generator creates<sup id="fnref:fn_ag"><a href="#fn:fn_ag" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> just fine, the <em>disqus crawler</em> does not.  So I had to create a csv file that mapped all the old URL’s to the new ones and upload that.</p>

<p>Announcements of new articles on Facebook are now handled by <a href="http://ifttt.com">IFTTT</a>.  It will likely take a little fine-tuning to get these right.</p>

<h2 id="whats-on-the-horizon">What’s on the Horizon?</h2>

<p>The primary emphasis of this site remains the text, but I do want to integrate a little more media–even just a few pictures here and there would be nice. I want the category pages to have their own looks. Beyond that, all I know is that I’ve now got the power to do anything.  Should be fun!</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn_ag">
      <p>Since the site is static, it can’t actually send HTTP
301 permanent redirects. Instead, the alias-generator creates HTML stub files for all the old URL’s with http-equiv meta tags containing the new locations of the URLs.<a href="#fnref:fn_ag" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Blogoversary!]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/22/happy-blogoversary/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/22/happy-blogoversary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first time I saw the World Wide Web, I was hunched over an 8 lb laptop using a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynx_(web_browser)">text based browser</a> and a 56k modem. There wasn’t much to see and it didn’t seem like a big deal. Then about three month’s later <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NCSA_Mosaic">NCSA Mosaic</a> (the first graphical browser) was released and I “got it.” Within a week <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NaviSoft">we</a> redefined our product line and turned a generic set of “network publishing” tools into a web server and a web authoring tool.  Within a year we were purchased by America Online to show that they “got” the web too. My point is that I’ve been deeply embedded in the web for a long time.  </p>

<p>And yet, not including my professional <a href="http://www.econ.yale.edu/~dm529">web-based resume/cv</a>, I didn’t have my own website until exactly a year ago when High Variance was <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/14573237390/first-post">born</a>. I’m not sure why it took me so long to get here, but after a year of any project, I think it’s important to step back and take stock to see if the original goals are being met. I had three:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Create more:</strong>  As expected, the topics have been eclectic ranging from economic policy to kid book reviews to eighties pop music.  The rate of production has been similarly irregular with a burst of activity last January (17 posts) and a summer hiatus.  But the aggregate rate has been about one post per week.  I’m happy with this.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Learn to write better and more comfortably:</strong> Perhaps my biggest surprise is how enjoyable the whole process has been. I don’t get anxious when I write here and my anxiety level when writing professionally has definitely decreased.  When my mind is spinning about a topic, writing about it actually gets me to calm down and figure out what I actually think about it.  As for the quality of the writing, I think I’m getting better, but it’s hard to tell.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Provide entertaining, useful, and/or inspiring content:</strong> My audience will need to be the judge of this, but I know I’ve given at least a few chuckles, a few bits of helpful advice, and even tugged on a few heartstrings.  And in looking back on what I’ve written, much of the content seems to have aged well.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>I suppose I should also say something about my readership. According to Google Analytics, over the past year I’ve have 2,070 unique visitors (5.7 per day) and 4,000 page views (11 per day). Not much, but if you squint at the chart, it does look like traffic is trending slightly up.  There are even a few posts that get regular search engine traffic–<a href="http://highvariance.net/post/18591130112/why-are-zebras-so-mean-and-horses-so-nice">zebras</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/23166850855/pdf-annotation-on-the-ipad-in-2012">pdf annotation on the iPad</a>, and <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/16047390011/mincer-1958">Mincer 1958</a> are the top three.</p>

<p>As I was about to blow out the candles on my birthday cake a few weeks ago I realized something very special: I didn’t have anything new to wish for.  I have a wonderful wife and two lovely children.  We’re all healthy and happy with our jobs and our house.  I just want what I already have.  That’s kind of true of this blog too.  So here’s to another fun and fulfilling year!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A few comments on Apple's Big October Event]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/10/25/apple-observations/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/10/25/apple-observations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Apple’s big October product announcements are now behind us and I’ve
read more blogger reactions than I care to admit.  Even I’m surprised
that I still have a few somewhat original thoughts of my own to share.
Instead of simply being an “iPad mini” event Apple announced a whole
slew of products.  While some folks predicted some of the “extra”
stuff, I don’t think anyone expected the sheer quantity we saw.  That
said, I’m most excited about two products Apple did not announce:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>A new Thunderbolt display:</strong> The new iMac is beautiful and I can’t
wait until they translate it into a stand-alone display.  Less glare and
pixels closer to the glass will be terrific.  It will also give Apple a
chance to add a few ports that they neglected on the first rev: USB 3
and analog audio out.  And imagine how thin it will be when it doesn’t
have to also house a whole computer?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Fusion Drive:</strong> I know, I know, they DID announce this as an
option for the new iMac and Mac Mini, but I’m hoping they will sell it
separately so I can stick one in my 2010 iMac.  I really like the idea
of having the speed of an SSD and the size of a traditional HD without
the hassle of managing the pair.  We’ll have to wait for the iFixit
teardown to see if it has a new interface (and is thus incompatible) and
something tells me even if it has standard wiring, Apple will want to
reserve this feature as reason for folks to upgrade their old (but
perfectly usable) iMacs.  I can still dream.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>There’s been a lot of talk about how Apple is making a mistake by
pricing the iPad mini at $329 and leaving breathing room for the other
cheaper small tablets in the market.  I think Apple priced the product
as high as possible such that they will sell all the mini’s they can make
before the holidays.  If they didn’t, they would simply be leaving money
on the table.  When their supply chain gets up to speed some time in the
spring, I predict they will drop the price below $300.</p>

<p>I have very mixed feelings about the new iMac.  While it’s gorgeous and
powerful, I’m not sure I agree with the sacrifices Apple had to make to
achieve its super-model-thin curves.  Most iMac owners spend
the bulk of their time in <em>front</em> of their iMac where they never even
see the curves–my own is right up against a wall, and I’d have to lean
over and around my desk to appreciate the sides and back.</p>

<p>Apple loves to be first to cast old standards aside: Remember when the
iMac dropped the floppy drive?  I think they were the first PC maker to
stop using special keyboard and mouse ports and just rely on USB.  And
just a month ago they said goodbye to the venerable Dock Connector.  Now
they want to do the same thing to the optical drive.  For a notebook,
this makes perfect sense: In the last year there was exactly one time
when it would have been nice to mount a CD on my Air and that is
certainly not enough to justify the added weight and bulk of a drive.
At my desk, I do rip the occasional DVD or used CD.  And I’m certainly
not throwing my iMac in my bag when I head out on the town.  But maybe
Apple’s right.  Maybe folks should just keep an ugly old SuperDrive in a
drawer for those rare occasions when they need it.  Then they can
appreciate beautiful design every day.  Even if it means leaning over
their desks to do so.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My thoughts on the iPhone 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/10/02/iphone5-ios6-review/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/10/02/iphone5-ios6-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So I got my iPhone 5 about a week ago (pre-ordered from AT&amp;T) and have
barely been able to brag about it to anyone since most of my local
friends aren’t nearly as nerdy as I am.  Then I remembered that I had a
blog and decided the world needed hear all about my new device.</p>

<p>But first, a little background: Two years ago I started carrying an
iPhone 4 and a year ago I was only slightly tempted to upgrade to a 4S.
The camera was a little better, the cpu was a little faster, and it had
Siri which I didn’t think I’d use much.  And I would have had to pay the
one year upgrade penalty.  I passed.  Fast-forward to this year and I
was champing at the bit for something new.  </p>

<p>And so, without further ado, here’s what I’d say if you saw me on the
street and said “Ooh, is that an iPhone 5?  How do you like it?”</p>

<h2 id="big-stuff">Big Stuff:</h2>

<p><strong>Camera:</strong> It’s way better.  Low light pictures look a lot better, but
 the thing I really notice is the speed.  It launches quickly (the 4 was
 a dog), and you can tap away at the shutter seemingly several times a
 second.  It’s a life-saver when you have an older daughter who loves
 funny faces and chewing on her own hair, but occasionally flashes the
 most beautiful smile you’ve ever seen.</p>

<p><strong>Maps:</strong> I get it that if you live in a place where the coverage stinks,
 the new Maps app stinks too.  But in New Haven, the coverage is fine.
 And it’s huge upgrade over IOS 5 both in terms of features and UI.
 Turn-by-turn voice directions are extremely well integrated–much nicer
 and more functional than either Tom Tom or Navigon.  I love that you
 can flip back and forth between the 2D map of your route and the 3D
 rendering of where you are on the route.  The vector-based tiles are
 prettier and faster to download too.  I’m glad I have the Tom Tom app,
which stores maps locally, for when I’m out of cell range, but let’s
 be honest: that hasn’t happened in years and it will be a while before
 it happens again.</p>

<p><strong>CPU:</strong> It’s way faster.  I have a shortcut on my home screen that launches
OmniFocus and goes straight to “new task” screen.  It used to take about
5 seconds, but now it’s less than a second.  All sorts of other stuff
loads and runs faster too.</p>

<p><strong>64 GB flash:</strong> In this cloud-based age we live in, local storage isn’t
 supposed to matter since your apps should just be able to pull in what
 you need from the net as you need it.  But as I’ve complained bitterly
 about <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/19041134391/photos-iphoto-ios-icloud-im-underwhelmed">already</a>, Apple’s vision of cloud photography is currently
 Photo Stream.  Ugh.  With double the room on my device, both my wife
 and I can stop carefully deciding what pictures and home videos we have
 space for.  Some day <a href="http://www.adobe.com/products/revel.html">Adobe Revel</a> might solve this more elegantly,
 but for now they don’t do video and they don’t have a Windows app.</p>

<h2 id="little-stuff">Little Stuff:</h2>

<p><strong>The physical device:</strong> Yeah, it’s nice.  But my eyes aren’t good enough to
really appreciate the straight lines and shiny camfer.  And it’s really
thin, especially since I’m going caseless for now compared to my old
rubber-clad 4.  It feels great in the pocket but it’s surprisingly hard
to pick up off a counter or desk!  My wife thinks it feels a little like
a Nano, and she’s right.</p>

<p><strong>Screen:</strong> I can’t tell if the colors are more saturated or if the pixels
are closer to the surface but supposedly they are.  It’s nice to have
more text on the screen in portrait mode, but this is partially offset
by the awkwardness of moving my thumb to the opposite top corner.  This
has become easier with time, so I’m guessing I’ll completely
adjust soon.  The extra row of icons is useful as my home screen was
getting a little cramped.  I rarely venture to my other screens now, and
that’s a good thing.</p>

<p><strong>Lightning:</strong> I like it a lot–it’s durable, tiny, and easy since it’s
double-sided.  It’s a little annoying that I now need different cables
for my phone and iPad, but Apple had to upgrade this connector
eventually and I think we’ll have Lightning for a long time.</p>

<p><strong>LTE:</strong> in some ways, this is the biggest new feature of the phone. When
you’re near an LTE tower, it’s crazy fast–the other day SpeedTest gave
me 28Mbps downstream and 12 Mbps upstream.  That’s 3x and 8x faster than
my U-Verse at home!  Of course, per byte, it’s expensive and I’m on wifi
90% of the time.  And right now, AT&amp;T’s coverage isn’t that great.</p>

<p><strong>Siri:</strong> We’re still just getting to know each other, but I like what I
 hear so far.  It’s absolutely the fastest way to enter new appointments
 on my calendar.  Last Friday I asked “What was the score in last
 night’s NFL game?” and got the box score in moments.  I use it to set
 alarms.  I expected to enjoy the novelty of it and then forget about
 it, but instead my usage seems to be increasing.</p>

<h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts:</h2>

<p>This phone did not need a whole bunch of fancy new features (e.g.,
curved AMOLED display, NFC, giant screen) to be fantastic.  The iPhone
has been fantastic since they introduced it in 2007.  I find it amazing
that they’ve been able to make it incrementally better every year by
refining and improving what it already does.  And yet the tech press
keeps wanting the next iPhone to be a quantum leap.  That’s not how
how it works.  Truly revolutionary devices aren’t 5.0’s, they are
1.0’s.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Things Done with Remember The Milk (i.e., GTD with RTM)]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/05/27/gtd-with-rtm/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/05/27/gtd-with-rtm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every year or so I get cranky about my task management system and switch
to something new.  This year it’s particularly bad because I’ve been
hearing the Siren Song of <a href="http://www.omnigroup.com/products/omnifocus/">OmniFocus</a>.  I swear every nerd blogger I read
uses it: e.g.,</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ben Brooks at <a href="http://brooksreview.net/2010/08/omnifocus-v-things-mac-ipad-iphone/">The Brooks Review</a></li>
  <li>David Sparks at <a href="http://www.macsparky.com/blog/2010/7/30/ipad-omnifocus-review.html">MacSparky</a></li>
  <li>Aleh Cherp at <a href="http://blog.macademic.org/2012/04/02/task-management-with-omnifocus-collecting-and-processing/">Macademic</a></li>
</ul>

<p>I even believe John Gruber (<a href="http://daringfireball.net">Daring Fireball</a>) uses it though he’s a
little cagy since they are often a sponsor of his.</p>

<p>BUT, I strongly believe you shouldn’t switch systems unless you’re
solving specific problems.  That is, I invest in my systems and don’t
want to switch just for fun.  Hearing that some other piece of software
is “really good” or even “better” than what you’re currently using
isn’t good enough for me.</p>

<p>Last year when I made the switch from <a href="http://mail.google.com/mail/help/tasks/">Google Tasks</a> to <a href="http://www.rememberthemilk.com">Remember The Milk</a>
(RTM), I had some clear requirements:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Cross-platform</em>: I was spending time on Mac, Windows, iPad, and
 iPhone and I needed to be able to access my tasks from all of them.</li>
  <li><em>Rock solid invisible sync</em>: I never wanted to think about which
 version of my task list I was working with.  There should be just one
 master copy (preferably in the cloud) that gets seemlessly accessed
 and updated from various clients.</li>
  <li><em>Power and flexibility</em>: Google Tasks met the first two criteria, but it was just too
 simple.  I wanted more than due dates and separate lists.  I wanted
 to be able to attach priorities, contexts, durations, and other
 arbitrary tags.  I wanted to  dynamically create lists based on
 these characteristics that showed me just what I wanted (and was
 able) to do at any particular moment.</li>
</ul>

<p>At the time, RTM was the best solution, but the world has changed since
then.  Omnifocus now provides highly regarded Sync Services.  And I’ve
shed my need for Windows now that I carry a MacBook Air with me
everywhere i go.</p>

<p>Stepping up a level for a moment, the overall task management system you
use is far more important than the particular tool you use to implement
it.  I’m a GTD (Getting Things Done) guy, though I’m not the most
orthodox devotee you’ll meet.  There are two things I love about GTD:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>You get the mental to do list out of your head.  Since you’re not
constantly worrying that you’ll forget something, your mind is freed up
for more interesting creative work.  And you’re not forgetting things!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Once your tasks are organized, GTD provides a way to quickly see what
you can and should be doing in any given context.  This is exactly what
I couldn’t do with Google Tasks.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>After a year of experience (and tweeking), I’ve got an implementation of
my GTD system in Remember The Milk that works pretty well.  Before
casting it aside for a new pretty young thing, I’m going to describe my
system and what works and doesn’t work for me.  It’s almost certainly
not a perfect match for anyone else, but it might give you ideas for
things to try or think about.  </p>

<p>RTM is a simple system that lets you build complex systems on top of it.
Basically, you just define a bunch of lists of tasks with
characteristics.  These characteristics include priorities, due dates,
durations, locations, and arbitrary tags–exactly what I want.  The
power comes from defining Smart Lists that are basically saved searches
based on these characteristics.</p>

<h2 id="projects">Projects</h2>

<p>Even though RTM supports multiple lists, I keep almost all my tasks in
the Inbox list and use other lists only for storing things like books
I’d like to read or ideas for upcoming posts.  I define my projects with
tags.  Home-related projects have tags starting with “ph-“ (e.g.,
“ph-basement”) and work-related projects have tags starting with “pw-“.
Most tasks that go into the system have either a project assigned or a simple
“work” tag.  If it’s a single task home project, I don’t take the time
to assign a project tag at all.</p>

<h2 id="locations">Locations</h2>

<p>I assign each task a single location tag: at-desk, at-phone, at-home,
at-econoffice, at-errand, or at-wife.  The last one is special: tasks
that require consultation with my wife.  Someone else that runs a lot of
errands might find it worth their time to set up several locations that
cause tasks to pop up when they go somewhere, but generally I go
somewhere <em>because</em> I need to do something and so don’t need to get
reminded.</p>

<h2 id="contexts">Contexts</h2>

<p>Coming up with the right set of contexts is critical to the system and
it’s the hardest part. In <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Getting-Things-Done-Stress-Free-Productivity/dp/0142000280">The GTD Book</a>, David Allen talks a lot about home,
office, and phone. With smart phones, the set of things you can do “on
the phone” is far larger than it used to be.  Since I usually have my
laptop with me and most of my resources are online, home office,
work office, and even cafe are almost the same.</p>

<p>Right now I have four smart lists that define my contexts:</p>

<p><strong>c-working</strong> </p>

<pre><code>due:today or dueBefore:today or (list:Inbox and (tagContains:pw- or
tag:work or tag:weekday) and (dueWithin:"5 days of today" or
priority:1 or priority:2 or priority:3))&lt;/tt&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>This is the context I look at during the work day or at night when
I’m working.  It includes everything due today or that’s overdue so I
don’t miss deadlines.  It also includes any tasks associated with
work-related projects or that can only be done during the week
(<tt>tag:weekday</tt>).  The most interesting piece is where I drop all
tasks that are due more than five days from now that have no priority
assigned.  These are the tasks I don’t even want to think about until it
gets closer to their due date.</p>

<p><strong>c-weekend</strong></p>

<pre><code>due:today or dueBefore:today or (not tag:work and not
tagContains:pw- and not tag:weekday and list:Inbox and (dueWithin:"5
days of today" or priority:1 or priority:2 or priority:3))&lt;/tt&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>On weekends and any time I want to focus on the non-work part of my
life I check this list.  It’s almost the inverse of my work context
except that it also includes anything that’s due or past due.</p>

<p><strong>c-out</strong></p>

<pre><code>tag:at-errand or tag:at-phone
</code></pre>

<p>This is what I should and can do when I’m out and about.</p>

<p><strong>c-easy</strong></p>

<pre><code>tag:fun or tag:easy or timeEstimate:"&lt; 1 hour"
</code></pre>

<p>When I’m tired or just have a few minutes, I look at this list.  It’s my
newest context, and I might eventually break it into a tired list and a
separate quick-task list.  </p>

<p>All four of these Smart Lists are sorted first by due date and then by
priority.  I often use <strong>high priority</strong> to mark that a task is the
next action for a project.  This way it’s always listed before other
actions that I want to record but might not be ready to do.  A while
back I read <a href="http://blog.rememberthemilk.com/2008/05/guest-post-advanced-gtd-with-remember-the-milk/">another article</a> about implementing GTD in RTM and it
suggested using an <strong>na</strong> tag.  My system allows me to complete a task
for a project and have the other tasks still show up on the list.  The
last thing I want to do is to constantly be tagging new tasks as <strong>na</strong>
as I complete other tasks.</p>

<p>There are plenty of times when I want to focus on a particular project
and in those cases I simply look at the Tag view for the project and
see all the tasks associated with the project no matter when they are
due or what their priority.</p>

<h2 id="weekly-review">Weekly Review:</h2>

<p>Just as David Allen says, I’ve found that if I don’t do a weekly review,
the information in the system drifts away from the information in my
brain and loses its value.  That’s when most folks fall off the wagon.
So support for the weekly review process is super-important.  Here’s
what I do every week:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Look at my untagged Smart List (<tt>not isTagged:true list:Inbox</tt>)
and assign project (if necessary) or location tags</li>
  <li>Look at the tasks for each project:
    <ul>
      <li>Are any upcoming tasks missing?  </li>
      <li>Are priorities and due dates right?</li>
      <li>Can I delete any tasks that are no longer needed?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Add any new projects that didn’t make it into the system during the week</li>
  <li>Quickly look at all the tasks in the system (usually between 100 and 150)
    <ul>
      <li>Do I need to lower / raise any priorities?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Look at what I accomplished in last week (<tt>completedWithin:”1 week
of today”</tt>)–good for setting feasible future expectations </li>
</ul>

<p>One nice thing about this way of doing weekly reviews is that it can be
done in chunks here and there –I don’t have to set aside the
traditional 2-3 hour block.</p>

<h2 id="room-for-improvement">Room for Improvement</h2>

<p>On the whole, I’m pretty happy with my system, but that doesn’t mean
there’s not lots of room for improvement.  </p>

<p>First, my system isn’t that great for capturing or doing long range
planning.  I can’t specify task dependencies and I can’t even specify
start dates for tasks.  If I could, that would let me filter out tasks
that I know I’m not starting for a while.  I try to follow orthodox GTD
practice and only use due dates for when things are really due. That way
I don’t miss these things in a sea of stuff that I’d like to be done on
that day.</p>

<p>Second, while the iOS apps are very good, I’m getting tired of the
clunky RTM web interface.  It’s functional, but pretty ugly.   I use
Fluid to make RTM a pop down menubar app, but I can’t get it to play
well with multiple Spaces.  That is, when I pop down the app, it pulls
me back to the Space I first started it.  And when RTM automatically
logs me out of the website (more often than I’d like), 
<a href="http://support.agilebits.com/discussions/1password-38-for-mac-from-agilebits-website/11718-1password-with-fluid">I can’t use 1Password to log back bin</a>.  I’m still totally dumbfounded that
no one has built a decent native Mac app for the service.</p>

<p>Third, entering new tasks requires me to click on the menubar app and
then put the cursor in the new task text entry box.  It sure would be
nice to have a global hot key for this.  </p>

<h2 id="bottom-line">Bottom Line</h2>

<p>Remember The Milk bugs me, but it also works for me.  And maybe
Omnifocus wouldn’t be uniformly better.  I’m worried that it would
try to force me into new ways of doing things that just don’t match my
work flow.  Maybe instead I need to check out <a href="http://donaldjenkins.com/2012/02/why-i-switched-from-omnifocus-to-things/">Things</a>….  Or maybe I
just need to get back to work!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
