<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tech | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/tech/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-11T12:29:52-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AnyList vs Grocery IQ]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2015/11/20/anylist-vs-grocery-iq/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2015/11/20/anylist-vs-grocery-iq</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>{% img /images/hv-anylist-vs-grocery-iq.png %}</p>

<p>Jason Snell <a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2015/11/ipad-pro-new-tricks-for-old-dogs/">recently wrote</a> that once he invests the time to learn and get comfortable with a tool, it takes something not just a <em>little</em> better, but <em>substantially</em> better to get him to switch. His examples were software he uses to edit podcasts and his overall computer set up: He edits his podcasts with Apple’s Logic even though many folks think he should move to Adobe Audition. Similarly, he really likes a lot about working on an iPad, but it’s not enough to make him sell his Mac and go <a href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/ipad-pro-review/">whole hog on iOS</a>.</p>

<p>I tend to agree with Mr. Snell on most things and this is no exception. About a year ago, I was pleasantly surprised to find we both used the same grocery list app: <a href="http://www.groceryiq.com">Grocery IQ</a>. Sure, it’s kind of ugly and barely maintained and littered with useless coupons, but it worked better than any other list app (general or grocery-specific) I had tried. And yet, when I saw the folks over at <a href="http://thesweetsetup.com">The Sweet Setup</a> chose <a href="https://www.anylistapp.com">AnyList</a> as their <a href="http://thesweetsetup.com/apps/anylist-favorite-grocery-shopping-app/">favorite grocery shopping app</a> I was tempted–Could it be worth the switching cost? On the other hand, this is an app my wife and I both use several times per week so the bar was higher than usual. I bit the bullet and checked it out.</p>

<p>The short answer is that AnyList is way better than Grocery IQ and I couldn’t be happier that I switched. Here’s why:</p>

<ol>
  <li>I can add items to the shopping list with Siri; e.g., “Add bananas to my grocery list.”</li>
  <li>I can reorder aisles (“categories”) to match my store’s layout.</li>
  <li>AnyList makes more efficient use of screen real estate.</li>
  <li>No coupons!</li>
  <li>AnyList has much faster syncing of shared lists.</li>
  <li>It’s under active development. This has tangible benefits relative to Grocery IQ like the fact that it uses the current iOS keyboard instead of a grody old one.</li>
</ol>

<p>From here on out, I’m going to be more open to trying new tools. In this case, I screwed up the cost benefit calculation on both sides: I couldn’t imagine the app could be this much better than what I was already using, <em>and</em> I over-estimated the switching costs–It’s not like a had a whole bunch of muscle memory invested in checking off items as I bought them.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My favorite podcast app: It's not what you think]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/16/network/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/16/network</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.macstories.net/reviews/overcast-review/">whole</a> <a href="http://www.macworld.com/article/2454285/review-overcast-is-a-winning-podcast-app.html">Internet</a> <a href="http://www.imore.com/overcast-iphone-review-podcasts-reconsidered">seemed</a> <a href="http://www.512pixels.net/blog/2014/7/overcast">to</a> <a href="http://daringfireball.net/linked/2014/07/16/overcast-1">go</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=overcast">crazy</a> today about the release of <a href="http://marco.org">Marco Arment</a>’s new podcast app for iOS: <a href="https://overcast.fm">Overcast</a>. He’s a nerd celebrity and he’s been teasing his fanbase (myself included) for what seems like a year as he worked on it and talked about it. Marco is an accomplished entrepreneur and engineer, and this release was <em>highly</em> anticipated. As a fan and a regular podcast listener, you might think I would be one of his first customers, but you’d be wrong.</p>

<p>{% img right /images/hv-network-podcast-app.jpg %}</p>

<p>I’ve been using <a href="http://networkapp.net">Network</a> for the last six months and am very happy. The UI couldn’t have less chrome–All you see in the app is the artwork from your podcasts, episode descriptions, and a plus sign for adding new podcasts. Your interaction with the app is almost entirely through gestures. It’s not <em>completely</em> intuitive, but it makes me smile and reminds me a lot of the <a href="http://realmacsoftware.com/clear">Clear</a> to-do and reminders app.</p>

<p><a href="http://vemedio.com/products/instacast">Instacast</a>, <a href="http://www.downcastapp.com">Downcast</a>, <a href="http://www.shiftyjelly.com/pocketcasts">Pocket Casts</a> and now Overcast all have a lot more features than Network, but I don’t need a lot of features and I certainly don’t want to fiddle with my podcast app while I choose avocadoes and listen to <a href="http://atp.fm">John Siracusa</a> complain about LCD TV’s. Some of Overcast’s features (e.g., Smart Speed) do sound cool and non-intrusive, but for now Network is perfect for me–It plays my podcasts and just melts into the background.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tile, a Geek Love Story]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/03/tile-a-geek-love-story/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/03/tile-a-geek-love-story</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The other day I got this email:</p>

<p>{% img center /images/hv-tile-request.png %}</p>

<p>Indeed, I have a story, but I doubt it will be on Tile’s front page anytime soon. <!--More--> It started almost a year ago when I backed my very first <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com">Kickstarter</a> project and ordered four Tiles. These magical one inch squares promised to keep me from ever losing anything ever again. I immediately envisioned attaching them to my keys, my wife’s keys, our wallets, and my daughters’ favorite toys. And I knew once I had them in my hands I would think of a host of new possibilities. I was in geek love. </p>

<p>{% img left /images/hv-tile.jpeg %}</p>

<p>Each $18.95 tile was a tiny Bluetooth beacon that could talk to any phone nearby that had the Tile app installed. If my keys fell behind a couch cushion, my phone could make their Tile play a little song announcing where they were. If I accidentally dropped my keys in the bushes, the app would remember where it last saw them and show me on a map. And if I left them on a plane, my app would talk to Tile’s cloud servers and let me know when another Tile user went near them and show me their location. The project had already hit it’s funding goal and was rocketing toward production. I couldn’t wait to get my delivery!</p>

<p>{% img right /images/hv-tile-key-basket.jpg %}</p>

<p>Months passed as the Tile Team worked through a series of last minute issues, and my interest started to wane. Then I realized that the batteries inside the Tiles expire after a year and are un-replaceable. That is, you have to buy new Tiles every year when your old ones die. And by the time my Tiles finally arrived, I realized that I already had a pretty good system for keeping track of my keys: They are always either in my pocket or in our kitchen key basket. I haven’t lost track of my keys in years. The same goes for my wallet, and even if I were a chronic wallet-loser, the Tile turns out to be too thick to comfortably slide into it.</p>

<p>Many of my early relationships followed the same pattern: Fall deeply in something with someone that was half a creation of my imagination. As I realized that this person was flesh and blood with flaws and features I didn’t immediately appreciate, I walked away. It wasn’t until much later that I learned that you can’t really love anyone without first understanding that there are no ideal types. You have to recognize that everyone is at least a little messy on the inside and the outside.</p>

<p>After a week with my Tiles, I’m starting to appreciate them. On Saturday my wife lost her keys and we spent several minutes scouring the house before we found them. I quickly attached a Tile, and that shouldn’t happen again. I’m also excited to put one in the car and always know where I’ve parked. Less than $20 for a  bit of magic is actually a pretty good deal even if it doesn’t last more than a year. And imagine how much cooler the next version will be!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Choosing the Right Tool for the Job]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/09/the-right-tool/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/05/09/the-right-tool</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>{% img /images/hv-tools.jpg %}</p>

<p>Every new programming project involves choosing a language early in the process. This choice can be exciting and daunting at the same time, as it always involves weighing several conflicting factors. Based on many years of varied programming experience, here is my advice:</p>

<!--More-->

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Pick a language appropriate to the task. Do you need good numerical optimization libraries? Do you need matrix operations? Do you need to parse HTML files? You don’t need the best language, but you don’t want to be stuck with something too slow or that requires you to write a lot of unnecessary support code. This is what John D. Cook is getting at when he says <a href="http://www.johndcook.com/blog/2014/03/12/dont-be-a-technical-masochist/">“Don’t be a technical masochist”</a>. I always think of this first even though it’s not always the most important criterion. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Take into account the fact that you might have to learn (or relearn) the language. This is the dreaded learning curve and even though I’m a quick learner, I always underestimate the time it takes to achieve proficiency.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Think about the future utility of knowing the language. This is harder than it looks. On the one hand Python is broadly popular and winning in scientific computing. Ruby is a similar language but has better libraries for web development. Both seem like good investments, but I haven’t used Python in more than 5 years and I’ve never written anything in Ruby. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If you are collaborating, think about what the rest of the team knows. Even if your partner isn’t writing as much code as you, it’s pretty valuable if they can read your code.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Don’t forget to have fun. Programming can be a grind–sometimes it’s fun to stretch your brain with something new. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Expertise in a language should not be squandered. It’s a lot of work pouring the core of a language (and it’s standard libraries) into your head, but once you do it, you can write a lot of good code very quickly. This knowledge depreciates quickly when you switch to different “better” tools for a given job.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>I spend a fair amount of my time analyzing data with <a href="http://www.stata.com">Stata</a>, and that involves writing programs in a quirky proprietary language. For example, it has no variables, but it does have local and global macros. To evaluate a local macro, you surround its name with a back quote and a forward quote (`x’). These can be nested. Global variables are prefixed with a dollar sign ($x). That said, it has general file handling and regular expression functions, and you can do interesting programming with it.</p>

<p>Lately, I’ve been trying to maintain and build my expertise in Stata by using it for a broad range of programming tasks even when it’s not the objectively best tool for a job. That was the case a few months ago when I parsed up and analyzed the content on this site. The end result looks a little weird, but it works and my brain is in a better place for it:</p>

<p>{% include_code lang:text analyze.do %}</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploiting Irrationality]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/01/30/exploiting-irrationality/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/01/30/exploiting-irrationality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>{% img right /images/hv-floss.png %}</p>

<p>When I was growing up, none of the several clocks in the house told the correct time. My mother would set them all between 5 and 30 minutes fast in an effort to fool herself into leaving the house when she was supposed to. I thought this was completely insane. Why not just wake up early enough to do what you needed to do, and then do that? Why play these games with yourself when pure rationality would suffice?</p>

<p>The answer (of course) is that my mother is far from completely rational, and this system worked for her in a way that my proposed system just didn’t. And while I like to think that I’m not as crazy as my mother, I’m not an automaton either. It’s taken me a long time to give in to that and start exploiting some of my foibles for good.</p>

<p>A few weeks ago, I read <a href="http://www.macworld.com/article/2085007/the-iphone-habit-apps-that-help-you-keep-your-new-years-resolutions.html">an article</a> by my productivity sensei (<a href="http://macsparky.com">David Sparks</a>) where he recommended an iPhone app called <a href="http://habitlist.com">Habit List</a> for folks trying to kickstart good habits. There’s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Habit">some scientific research</a> that says if you can somehow get yourself to do something regularly for a few weeks, it becomes a lot easier to continue doing it. There’s also some <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Candy_Crush">evidence</a> that games can be addictive. In a nutshell, Habit List makes doing mundane things into a game. By the time you’re bored with the game, the habit has been formed.</p>

<p>Since I installed Habit List, I’ve managed to floss every day except one (thanks stomach flu!). My exercise program has been less successful, but that’s more the fault of the cold weather and that same stomach flu than a failure of the app. You can bet that I’ll be plugging in some more easy-to-ignore-but-good-for-me chores soon.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
