<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tech | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/tech/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-12T04:06:02-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Neutral Podcast: A for Entertainment, B for Effort, and C for Economics]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/12/neutral/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/12/neutral</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I drive a 2002 Honda Civic. It’s an automatic and even though the interior is smeared with a thin layer of toys and crumbs, it hasn’t been vacuumed in months. It could not be less of a “driving machine” or more of a “people mover.” And yet, my favorite new podcast (<a href="http://neutral.fm">Neutral</a>) is all about cars and the tech behind them.</p>

<p><a href="http://marco.org">Marco Arment</a>, <a href="http://hypercritical.co">John Siracusa</a>, and newcomer Casey Liss have teamed up to tell folks on the Internet what they drive, what they would like to drive, what everyone else should drive, and most importantly the reasons behind each in excruciating detail. In just four episodes, I’ve learned about dual clutch transmissions, the appeal of white cars, pricing of used Acura NSX’s, and how hard it is not to generalize from small samples even when we know it’s wrong.</p>

<p>When I was in college, I read <em>Car and Driver</em> and <em>Road and Track</em> religiously. Even though I couldn’t afford a car at all, I could tell you the difference between the latest models of BMW, Audi, and Volvo. So it makes me really happy that a bunch of nerdy guys who now have a bit of money and who have been keeping up better than me can now own nice cars. (Actually, only Marco and Casey are in this situation–John still drives an Accord while he waits for his kids to finish elementary school and middle school and high school and college. It’s going to be a while for John.) </p>

<p>I really only have the tiniest complaint about the show and it starts with a comment Marco made while defending his choice to pay (about) $500/month to lease a “nice” car instead of $250/month to lease an “adequate” car. He said that meant he must get twice as much value from the nice car to make it worthwhile. A reader graciously wrote in to correct his logic, but clearly it didn’t stick because Marco proceeded to wave his hands and say the argument was “semantics.”</p>

<p>Price is not the same thing as value. People buy a thing when the price is <em>*less than or equal to</em> the value they get from that thing. This value (or benefit) is often much higher than the price. The difference between the value and the price is called the consumer surplus. When deciding between purchasing two things (like a nice car and an adequate car), what matters is which one has the higher consumer surplus. In Marco’s case, that means he needs to get at least $250 additional value from the nice car–that’s almost certainly much less than double the value he would get from the adequate car.</p>

<p>Part of being a nerd is sweating the details and getting stuff right. No one wants to ship buggy products and they shouldn’t ship buggy podcasts either. I’ll give them the benefit of the doubt since <em>Neutral</em> is still a 1.0.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crashed disks, imperfect backup strategies, and lessons learned]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/05/crashes-backups-and-lessons/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/05/crashes-backups-and-lessons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I work regularly with two computers. At home, I have an iMac with a big drive that is on all the time. At the office (and everywhere else) I use a MacBook Air. All my documents and data are stored on Dropbox and I use <a href="http://www.subsonic.org/pages/index.jsp">Subsonic</a> to stream my home music collection wherever I happen to be. If I watched movies, I could probably do the same with them. With this setup, I am equally productive on both machines and it doesn’t take that much work to keep apps and preferences in sync.</p>

<p>I used to think I had the perfect backup system. At home, my iMac’s internal drive is backed up to an external disk with Time Machine and to the cloud with <a href="http://backblaze.com">BackBlaze</a>. Since all my documents and data live in Dropbox, they’re duplicated (along with old versions) in Dropbox’s cloud. My Macbook Air has almost nothing sacred outside Dropbox and until recently, I thought that if the disk failed, all I’d have to do is reinstall my apps (just a few minutes work with the App Store) and I’d be back in business.  I was wrong.</p>

<p>About two weeks ago, it happened: my Air’s disk failed: The only thing that showed up on my screen was a blinking Folder icon with a question mark in the center. I quickly dropped off the machine at the local Apple store for service and muddled along for a few days with my old ThinkPad <a href="http://wiki.osx86project.org/wiki/index.php/Main_Page">Hackintosh</a>. When I finally picked up my repaired machine, it had a pristine installation of Lion and nothing else. I brought it home, installed Dropbox, and let <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/help/137/en">LAN Sync</a> work its magic over the local wifi and in a couple hours my documents and data were back. Then, with the press of a button I installed my 25 or so App Store apps.</p>

<p>That’s when I realized just how many apps I rely on are NOT in the App Store.  They fall into four broad categories:</p>

<h2 id="apps-that-break-apples-sandboxing-rules">1. Apps that break Apple’s sandboxing rules</h2>

<p>Several really useful utilities want to insert themselves deeper into the operating system than Apple would like.</p>

<p><a href="https://agilebits.com/onepassword">1Password</a>: Lets me use ridiculously long strings of unguessable gobbledy gook for passwords without having to remember them. Also securely holds all my account numbers, credit card numbers and plugs this stuff into web pages as needed.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alfredapp.com">Alfred</a>: After a simple Command-Space I can type short incantations to make amazing things happen. You really need to check out the web page to see how awesome and productivity-enhancing this is.</p>

<p><a href="http://smilesoftware.com/TextExpander/index.html">TextExpander</a>: I type short things like “;s” in any app and TextExpander fills in long snippets of text.</p>

<p><a href="http://pqrs.org/macosx/keyremap4macbook/">KeyRemap4Macbook</a>: I use it to give me emacs key combinations pretty much anywhere, but the app can do lots more.</p>

<p><a href="http://manytricks.com/moom/">Moom</a>: Makes it easy to move and resize windows to common places and sizes.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.stclairsoft.com/DefaultFolderX/">DefaultFolderX</a>: It expands the File-&gt;Open Dialog to show bigger QuickLook previews and makes it easy to select commonly used paths. It’s super-useful if you have very hierarchical directory structures.</p>

<h2 id="apps-from-companies-that-dont-want-to-give-apple-30">2. Apps from companies that don’t want to give Apple 30%</h2>

<p><a href="http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/">Microsoft Office</a>: The cheese sandwich of software–it does its job competently, but it’s hard to get excited about it.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.stata.com">Stata</a>: My go-to data analysis software. Fast, feature-filled, relatively shallow learning curve, and great documentation. What more do you want?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.mekentosj.com/papers/">Papers</a>: Manages big collections of pdfs and simplifies search for academic literature.</p>

<h2 id="apps-i-think-should-be-in-the-app-store">3. Apps I think should be in the App Store</h2>

<p>These apps are free and frankly I have no idea why they’re not in the App Store:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.skype.com">Skype</a> and <a href="https://www.google.com/intl/en/chrome/browser/">Google Chrome</a>: If you are reading this on a computer screen, then you already know these two.</p>

<p><a href="http://aquamacs.org">Aquamacs</a>: Puts Mac lipstick on an old pig of an editor. That said, I’ve been using emacs for 20 years and I love it.</p>

<p><a href="http://brettterpstra.com/projects/nvalt/">nvAlt</a>: I’ve been using nvAlt for about six months to manage all my miscellaneous notes. It’s super-easy to search and the data are accessible on all my devices.</p>

<h2 id="apps-that-are-just-too-geeky-for-the-app-store">4. Apps that are just too geeky for the App Store</h2>

<p>You’re going to be spending quality time at the command-line if you use <a href="http://mxcl.github.com/homebrew/">brew</a>, <a href="http://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</a>, and <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a>, so you may as well install them by hand.</p>

<p>Once all I installed all these apps, I still had lots of little things to do.  I had to tweek the preferences for most of my apps. I had to set up the finicky network printer in the office. In order to access the secure university wifi network, I had to install the required certificate. I could go on, but this gives you the flavor–The whole process of getting back to where I started took far longer than I had envisioned and I don’t want to go through it again.  </p>

<h2 id="the-solution">The Solution</h2>

<p>The main requirement of any solution was that it back up what wasn’t already safe–i.e., everything outside my Dropbox folder. But any solution also had to need absolutely minimal human intervention. I am not to be trusted to manually mirror drives every week. I also wanted to do as much as possible with hardware I had lying around.</p>

<p>Because we’re only talking about about 40 GB, I was able to repurpose an old 250GB external drive as a Time Machine disk that now lives at the office nestled into a book shelf. It’s plugged into a hub along with my phone charger, iPad charger and USB ethernet adapter. The first thing I always do upon arrival is plug the Air into it’s power adapter, the external display, and the hub. This procedure hasn’t had to change at all. When I leave, I pull the external display cable and close the lid on the Air. <a href="http://www.stclairsoft.com/Jettison/">Jettison</a> automatically waits for any ongoing Time Machine backups to finish and ejects the external disk before sleeping the Mac. As soon as I hear the disk stop, I unplug the hub and my power cable and I’m ready to go.</p>

<p>The other day I took my favorite winter coat to a tailor to have the zipper fixed. The woman very graciously showed me that nothing was actually broken–I’d simply forgotten that it was a <a href="http://www.perfectex.com/two_way_zipper.jpg">two way zipper</a> and both parts needed to be at the bottom in order for it to work. It was embarrassing, but I was still happy since the “repair” was extremely fast and it cost nothing. I feel the same way about this adjustment to my backup system. It’s a little embarrassing that I didn’t recognize the weakness up front, but I’m also really happy that it was so easy to fix.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lectures 2.0: Using online materials to improve off-line courses]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/29/lectures-2.0/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/29/lectures-2.0</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The big lecture is an institution in institutions of higher learning. The professor stands at the front of a hall full of students and talks. Sometimes he or she uses slides and sometimes he or she writes on a board.  And sometimes, he or she is informative and engaging, but it’s almost always a pretty one way affair with occasional questions posed to the class.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>  The experience for students is a lot like watching a good documentary.  And that’s the best case scenario. The vast majority of the time, students sit back and absorb the flow or just check out. They don’t get <em>their</em> questions answered or engage constructively with the material. The average professor talks at their students for an hour and a half twice a week and it’s more like a late night infomercial than a documentary. </p>

<p>Now let’s think about seminars. Students read articles and book chapters ahead of time and then gather in a small classroom to discuss the material with the professor and each other. Often there are in-class exercises or even smaller group activities. In general, students report they get more out of these classes. </p>

<p>So why aren’t all classes structured as seminars? First of all, some material (especially introductory material) is more easily presented visually than textually–that’s one reason why <a href="http://www.khanacademy.org">Kahn Academy</a> is so successful. Seeing someone work through a problem is, for many students, a lot clearer than reading about it in a book. Lecturing allows for this kind of presentation and I believe it complements book learning. The second reason is purely economic: Seminars are expensive. If you have 33-34 students per seminar and you want to teach 100 students, you need three professors.  That’s triple what you’d need to teach a 100 person lecture.</p>

<p>Wouldn’t it be great if we could take the best qualities of the lecture and the seminar and combine them in an economically feasible way?  We can. </p>

<p>I was asked recently why I am excited to teach an online class this summer. Expanding the reach of my teaching was one reason, but it also gives me the opportunity to put together high quality online materials. This won’t simply be recordings of my hour and half lectures. Instead, it will be 3-5m chunks of <a href="https://www.udacity.com">Udacity</a>-style video interspersed with questions to make sure students are following along. The video will mostly be me drawing on slides, working through problems, and presenting new concepts.</p>

<p>Here’s my vision: The 100 person class is divided into three separate groups of students. Each week, all students work their way through about 2 hours worth of online interactive video. At the end of the week, I meet with each group for an hour. I answer questions that they still have. I tie the “timeless” online material to current events. I have them work on problems in smaller groups and float between groups helping them as needed. </p>

<p>I think the experience will be clearly better for students, but what about faculty and the administration? This won’t happen unless it’s a Pareto improvement.  That is, none of the parties involved can be worse off. </p>

<p>Once the materials are in place, they can be re-used by different professors–this radically reduces the amount of prep time. The class itself should be a lot more fun to teach since the professor  can actually have conversations with students and get direct feedback on how well the class is going. If the online materials are high quality (and they should be), the professor doesn’t have to be fantastic to teach an excellent class. Most faculty are not naturally great lecturers, but the small classes give them an opportunity to share their raw intelligence and experience with the material–it’s a much better skill match.</p>

<p>The administration is happy because the same 100 students are getting higher quality education for the same cost.  In fact, far more students get to benefit from close contact with big name professors–that makes the institution look good.</p>

<p>What I’m describing is not a totally new idea–It’s a straight-forward application of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flip_teaching">flipping the classroom</a>. And it’s an idea that gets better and better every day as the education world learns  more about what works online and more high quality materials are made publicly available.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Some professors will use <a href="http://www.engaging-technologies.com/teaching-with-clickers.html">clickers</a> to get real-time multiple choice feedback from his or her audience.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stock prices are not grades for last quarter]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/24/stock-prices-are-not-grades/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/24/stock-prices-are-not-grades</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past few quarters, I’ve noticed a disturbing pattern. At some point near the end of the financial quarter, professional stock analysts predict Apple’s numbers (e.g., profit and revenue) to go up a lot. The market takes these predictions seriously and the stock price adjusts to take them into account. Then Apple does report good numbers (usually record-breaking) but not quite as good as the analysts predicted.  The stock goes down as the market adjusts using the new (factual) information about how well the company is doing.  This is all perfectly normal.  </p>

<p>The disturbing part is that the Apple tech writer blogosphere then complains that it doesn’t make sense.  Their logic seems to be that because Apple just did really well, they should be rewarded for it and the stock should go up. They think the expectations shouldn’t matter.  They don’t seem to understand that stock prices are a function of currently held capital and <em>expectations</em> of future performance. Sigh. If these writers want to be mad about something, they should be mad that the analysts are doing a lousy job at predicting Apple’s performance. They shouldn’t be surprised by basic market behavior.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Siracusa 2016]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/04/siracusa-2016/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/04/siracusa-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-siracusa-2016.jpg" alt="Siracusa 2016" /></p>

<p>Fellow Americans, our country has come a long way in the last 50 years. We have had our first <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_F._Kennedy">Catholic president</a>, our first <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">African-American president</a>, and almost our first <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mormon president</a>. In a few generations we will almost certainly have our first gay president. I say the time has come for our first geek president and John Siracusa is the perfect<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> person for the job.</p>

<p>For those of you who have never heard of him, Mr. Siracusa is a software developer by day and an ace gamer, devoted father, loving husband, and nerd celebrity by night. He’s most known for his <a href="http://arstechnica.com/apple/2011/05/mac-os-x-revisited/">tour-de-force</a> reviews of (Mac) OS X and more recently for his wide-ranging soapbox podcast <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical">Hypercritical</a>.  It is these venues where Mr. Siracusa has demonstrated he has the skills our country needs.</p>

<p>He is the ultimate natural analyst, able to glance at anything and quickly identify its strengths and (especially) weaknesses. While he typically applies his super-power to tech products<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, it will be amazing to see him use it to intelligently dissect and choose among potential public policies.  </p>

<p>Mr. Siracusa is also blessed with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vision_thing">big picture vision</a>, a critical requirement for a successful chief executive.  He can tell you about the future of <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/31">computing</a>, <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/63">software distribution</a>, <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/1">TV</a>, and even <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/18">toasters</a>. His ideas about using <a href="http://the-magazine.org/2/strange-game">artificial worlds as petri dishes for social policy</a> are exciting and promising (if not <a href="http://christakis.med.harvard.edu/pdf/publications/articles/126.pdf">completely original</a>). Once he throws off the corporation-imposed shackles banning political discourse that bound him on Hypercritical, I am certain we will see a beautiful clear vision for the future of America and indeed the planet. </p>

<p>Mr. Siracusa has the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iran–Contra_affair">integrity</a>, <a href="http://www.snopes.com/quotes/internet.asp">humility</a>, and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lewinsky_scandal">moral compass</a> that the American public wants in a president but is so often lacking. He has a warm heart and is unafraid to defend unpopular groups–nerds, cosplaying-wanna-be-nerds, homosexuals, and trans-sexuals are all welcome in <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/96">his big tent</a>.  He’s a humble every-man who is able to <a href="http://vimeo.com/46369728">make fun of himself</a> and his election season cameos on Saturaday Night Live will surely be hilarious. While a presidential campaign always brings out the muck rackers, I’d be shocked if they unearthed any Siracusa scandals.</p>

<p>December 28, 2012 was a sad day as the <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/100">final Hypercritical episode</a> was recorded, but think about it this way: John Siracusa now has a big hole in his schedule to fill.  America needs him!</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>OK, he’s not <em>perfect</em>. I don’t know if he’s ever left the country so maybe he’d have to brush up on foreign policy.  And sure, he has no executive experience and eschews management jobs.  And he doesn’t like risk.  But <em>no one</em> is perfect.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>My favorite example is his obsession with video game controllers which he demonstrates convincingly in episodes <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/49">49</a>, <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/50">50</a>, and <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/99">99</a> of Hypercritical.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
