<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tech | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/tech/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-03-08T18:48:40-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Happy Mosh Pit]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2017/10/08/gojira/"/>
    <updated>2017-10-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2017/10/08/gojira</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/gojira.jpeg"></p>

<p>I don’t go to a lot of concerts, so when I do, the stakes are high. That’s especially the case now that I live in Ithaca where you have to drive three hours to see anyone who’s not sitting on a stool playing an acoustic guitar. Thursday night my friend Kelly and I drove to the Clifton Park Concert Hall to see French heavy metal band <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gojira_(band)">Gojira</a>. The whole experience was awesome.</p>

<p>I fully expected the music to be amazing, and it was. I love Gojira. Their early albums are super-heavy and they’ve become more interesting over time. If you’ve never heard them, I highly recommend their last two albums which are super-catchy and accessible. And then there’s their concept album (From Mars to Sirius) that mixes death metal and whale songs. Sounds ridiculous, but it totally works. The band is from the wild Brittany coast and all their albums are infused with environmental sensitivity.</p>

<p>They played a nice mix of old stuff and new. Joe’s stage banter was fun. Mario’s drum solo was awesome and I thought I was burnt out on drum solos. Really the only disappointment was that they didn’t play <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g9oukr-X4d8">The Axe</a>, my personal favorite Gojira song. I guess I’ll have to see them again for that.</p>

<p>Metal fans get a bad rap. People think we’re all a bunch of aggro meat heads. Well most metal fans are actually pretty nice guys, and the crowd at this show was the kindest and sweetest I’ve every seen. Some evidence:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Lots of smiling throughout.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When anyone would stumble in the mosh pit, <strong>everyone</strong> around him would stop to give him a hand up. It was like competitive helping.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>One dude stopped to tie his shoes in the mosh pit and no one knocked him over. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Another guy was actually drinking a beer in a plastic cup in the pit. He’d get bumped occasionally and splash the people around him, but they’d just laugh.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I saw plenty of fans throwing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sign_of_the_horns">the horns</a> (pinkie and fore-finger), but multiple folks were putting their hands over their heads in heart shapes—Maybe throwing hearts is a thing now?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I noticed a fan wearing a shirt with a big swastika on the back of it and pointed it out to my friend. Then he said wait a second, it’s got a red circle around it with a backslash! </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You know that guy at the metal show who doesn’t seem to know the band’s songs very well and is kind of drunk? He just loves getting violent in a pit. He’s always there, and this concert was no exception. I saw him during the opening act wearing a New England Patriots shirt—a pretty aggressive move in upstate New York. But then I talked to him during the break when he was loading up at the bar and he was super nice!</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>These are the kinds of things that happen when the singer says things like: “I want everyone to be in the moment!” “Put your phones away–I want to feel like I’m playing in the 80’s!” “Let your everyday problems float away and just be present and feel the love all around us!” Gojira is the best.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving from iPhone 6 to 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2016/12/23/moving-from-6-to-7/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2016/12/23/moving-from-6-to-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/iphone-upgrade.jpg"></p>

<p>You might think the world has plenty of iPhone 7 reviews. Maybe even more iPhone 7 reviews than it needs. You’re probably right, but the vast majority are written by nerds who upgrade their phones every year. Upgrading is a totally different experience for regular people who have waited two (or more) years. As a recent upgrader from a venerable iPhone 6+, I am here to tell you that it’s worth moving up to the latest and greatest.</p>

<p><strong>Battery:</strong> After two years of use (including 4 tough months of Pokemon Go), the battery on my 6+ was in bad shape. Now I’m back to making it through a whole day without an external battery pack. Phew!</p>

<p><strong>CPU/GPU:</strong> The 7+ is noticeably faster. Apps start faster and game animations are smoother. Nice.</p>

<p><strong>RAM:</strong> The 6+ had 1GB. This wasn’t enough. Switching apps almost always required the app to start from scratch. Switching web pages meant watching slow reloads. All that’s gone with the 7+’s tripled RAM. I think this is the most noticeable improvement and it’s glorious.</p>

<p><strong>Camera:</strong> The camera is higher resolution, better in low light, and has 2x optical zoom. Live pictures (which store a little bit of video before and after your still) are new since the 6. All this is neat and lots of folks will appreciate it more than me.</p>

<p><strong>Other Stuff:</strong> </p>

<ul>
  <li>Turning it on is faster since it recognizes when you pick it up. This is cool.</li>
  <li>The home button is worse, but the phone is a lot more waterproof than before. </li>
  <li>The vibrate alert is just as vibrate-y and it’s now quieter when the phone is sitting on a table.</li>
  <li>The new colors are fine, but totally not noticeable when the phone is in a case.</li>
  <li>No headphone jack = no big deal.</li>
</ul>

<p>The 6 is a pretty good phone–Unless yours is broken, you don’t need to upgrade. That said, the 7 is a lot better and I notice the improvements every day.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AnyList vs Grocery IQ]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2015/11/20/anylist-vs-grocery-iq/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2015/11/20/anylist-vs-grocery-iq</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-anylist-vs-grocery-iq.png"></p>

<p>Jason Snell <a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2015/11/ipad-pro-new-tricks-for-old-dogs/">recently wrote</a> that once he invests the time to learn and get comfortable with a tool, it takes something not just a <em>little</em> better, but <em>substantially</em> better to get him to switch. His examples were software he uses to edit podcasts and his overall computer set up: He edits his podcasts with Apple’s Logic even though many folks think he should move to Adobe Audition. Similarly, he really likes a lot about working on an iPad, but it’s not enough to make him sell his Mac and go <a href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/ipad-pro-review/">whole hog on iOS</a>.</p>

<p>I tend to agree with Mr. Snell on most things and this is no exception. About a year ago, I was pleasantly surprised to find we both used the same grocery list app: <a href="http://www.groceryiq.com">Grocery IQ</a>. Sure, it’s kind of ugly and barely maintained and littered with useless coupons, but it worked better than any other list app (general or grocery-specific) I had tried. And yet, when I saw the folks over at <a href="http://thesweetsetup.com">The Sweet Setup</a> chose <a href="https://www.anylistapp.com">AnyList</a> as their <a href="http://thesweetsetup.com/apps/anylist-favorite-grocery-shopping-app/">favorite grocery shopping app</a> I was tempted–Could it be worth the switching cost? On the other hand, this is an app my wife and I both use several times per week so the bar was higher than usual. I bit the bullet and checked it out.</p>

<p>The short answer is that AnyList is way better than Grocery IQ and I couldn’t be happier that I switched. Here’s why:</p>

<ol>
  <li>I can add items to the shopping list with Siri; e.g., “Add bananas to my grocery list.”</li>
  <li>I can reorder aisles (“categories”) to match my store’s layout.</li>
  <li>AnyList makes more efficient use of screen real estate.</li>
  <li>No coupons!</li>
  <li>AnyList has much faster syncing of shared lists.</li>
  <li>It’s under active development. This has tangible benefits relative to Grocery IQ like the fact that it uses the current iOS keyboard instead of a grody old one.</li>
</ol>

<p>From here on out, I’m going to be more open to trying new tools. In this case, I screwed up the cost benefit calculation on both sides: I couldn’t imagine the app could be this much better than what I was already using, <em>and</em> I over-estimated the switching costs–It’s not like a had a whole bunch of muscle memory invested in checking off items as I bought them.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My favorite podcast app: It's not what you think]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/16/network/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/16/network</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.macstories.net/reviews/overcast-review/">whole</a> <a href="http://www.macworld.com/article/2454285/review-overcast-is-a-winning-podcast-app.html">Internet</a> <a href="http://www.imore.com/overcast-iphone-review-podcasts-reconsidered">seemed</a> <a href="http://www.512pixels.net/blog/2014/7/overcast">to</a> <a href="http://daringfireball.net/linked/2014/07/16/overcast-1">go</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=overcast">crazy</a> today about the release of <a href="http://marco.org">Marco Arment</a>’s new podcast app for iOS: <a href="https://overcast.fm">Overcast</a>. He’s a nerd celebrity and he’s been teasing his fanbase (myself included) for what seems like a year as he worked on it and talked about it. Marco is an accomplished entrepreneur and engineer, and this release was <em>highly</em> anticipated. As a fan and a regular podcast listener, you might think I would be one of his first customers, but you’d be wrong.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-network-podcast-app.jpg"></p>

<p>I’ve been using <a href="http://networkapp.net">Network</a> for the last six months and am very happy. The UI couldn’t have less chrome–All you see in the app is the artwork from your podcasts, episode descriptions, and a plus sign for adding new podcasts. Your interaction with the app is almost entirely through gestures. It’s not <em>completely</em> intuitive, but it makes me smile and reminds me a lot of the <a href="http://realmacsoftware.com/clear">Clear</a> to-do and reminders app.</p>

<p><a href="http://vemedio.com/products/instacast">Instacast</a>, <a href="http://www.downcastapp.com">Downcast</a>, <a href="http://www.shiftyjelly.com/pocketcasts">Pocket Casts</a> and now Overcast all have a lot more features than Network, but I don’t need a lot of features and I certainly don’t want to fiddle with my podcast app while I choose avocadoes and listen to <a href="http://atp.fm">John Siracusa</a> complain about LCD TV’s. Some of Overcast’s features (e.g., Smart Speed) do sound cool and non-intrusive, but for now Network is perfect for me–It plays my podcasts and just melts into the background.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tile, a Geek Love Story]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/03/tile-a-geek-love-story/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/07/03/tile-a-geek-love-story</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The other day I got this email:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/hv-tile-request.png"></p>

<p>Indeed, I have a story, but I doubt it will be on Tile’s front page anytime soon. <!--More--> It started almost a year ago when I backed my very first <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com">Kickstarter</a> project and ordered four Tiles. These magical one inch squares promised to keep me from ever losing anything ever again. I immediately envisioned attaching them to my keys, my wife’s keys, our wallets, and my daughters’ favorite toys. And I knew once I had them in my hands I would think of a host of new possibilities. I was in geek love. </p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/hv-tile.jpeg"></p>

<p>Each $18.95 tile was a tiny Bluetooth beacon that could talk to any phone nearby that had the Tile app installed. If my keys fell behind a couch cushion, my phone could make their Tile play a little song announcing where they were. If I accidentally dropped my keys in the bushes, the app would remember where it last saw them and show me on a map. And if I left them on a plane, my app would talk to Tile’s cloud servers and let me know when another Tile user went near them and show me their location. The project had already hit it’s funding goal and was rocketing toward production. I couldn’t wait to get my delivery!</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-tile-key-basket.jpg"></p>

<p>Months passed as the Tile Team worked through a series of last minute issues, and my interest started to wane. Then I realized that the batteries inside the Tiles expire after a year and are un-replaceable. That is, you have to buy new Tiles every year when your old ones die. And by the time my Tiles finally arrived, I realized that I already had a pretty good system for keeping track of my keys: They are always either in my pocket or in our kitchen key basket. I haven’t lost track of my keys in years. The same goes for my wallet, and even if I were a chronic wallet-loser, the Tile turns out to be too thick to comfortably slide into it.</p>

<p>Many of my early relationships followed the same pattern: Fall deeply in something with someone that was half a creation of my imagination. As I realized that this person was flesh and blood with flaws and features I didn’t immediately appreciate, I walked away. It wasn’t until much later that I learned that you can’t really love anyone without first understanding that there are no ideal types. You have to recognize that everyone is at least a little messy on the inside and the outside.</p>

<p>After a week with my Tiles, I’m starting to appreciate them. On Saturday my wife lost her keys and we spent several minutes scouring the house before we found them. I quickly attached a Tile, and that shouldn’t happen again. I’m also excited to put one in the car and always know where I’ve parked. Less than $20 for a  bit of magic is actually a pretty good deal even if it doesn’t last more than a year. And imagine how much cooler the next version will be!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
