<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tech | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/categories/tech/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-26T10:15:30-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A few comments on Apple's Big October Event]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/10/25/apple-observations/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/10/25/apple-observations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Apple's big October product announcements are now behind us and I've
read more blogger reactions than I care to admit.  Even I'm surprised
that I still have a few somewhat original thoughts of my own to share.
Instead of simply being an "iPad mini" event Apple announced a whole
slew of products.  While some folks predicted some of the "extra"
stuff, I don't think anyone expected the sheer quantity we saw.  That
said, I'm most excited about two products Apple did not announce:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>A new Thunderbolt display:</strong> The new iMac is beautiful and I can't
wait until they translate it into a stand-alone display.  Less glare and
pixels closer to the glass will be terrific.  It will also give Apple a
chance to add a few ports that they neglected on the first rev: USB 3
and analog audio out.  And imagine how thin it will be when it doesn't
have to also house a whole computer?</p></li>
<li><p><strong>The Fusion Drive:</strong> I know, I know, they DID announce this as an
option for the new iMac and Mac Mini, but I'm hoping they will sell it
separately so I can stick one in my 2010 iMac.  I really like the idea
of having the speed of an SSD and the size of a traditional HD without
the hassle of managing the pair.  We'll have to wait for the iFixit
teardown to see if it has a new interface (and is thus incompatible) and
something tells me even if it has standard wiring, Apple will want to
reserve this feature as reason for folks to upgrade their old (but
perfectly usable) iMacs.  I can still dream.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>There's been a lot of talk about how Apple is making a mistake by
pricing the iPad mini at $329 and leaving breathing room for the other
cheaper small tablets in the market.  I think Apple priced the product
as high as possible such that they will sell all the mini's they can make
before the holidays.  If they didn't, they would simply be leaving money
on the table.  When their supply chain gets up to speed some time in the
spring, I predict they will drop the price below $300.</p>

<p>I have very mixed feelings about the new iMac.  While it's gorgeous and
powerful, I'm not sure I agree with the sacrifices Apple had to make to
achieve its super-model-thin curves.  Most iMac owners spend
the bulk of their time in <em>front</em> of their iMac where they never even
see the curves--my own is right up against a wall, and I'd have to lean
over and around my desk to appreciate the sides and back.</p>

<p>Apple loves to be first to cast old standards aside: Remember when the
iMac dropped the floppy drive?  I think they were the first PC maker to
stop using special keyboard and mouse ports and just rely on USB.  And
just a month ago they said goodbye to the venerable Dock Connector.  Now
they want to do the same thing to the optical drive.  For a notebook,
this makes perfect sense: In the last year there was exactly one time
when it would have been nice to mount a CD on my Air and that is
certainly not enough to justify the added weight and bulk of a drive.
At my desk, I do rip the occasional DVD or used CD.  And I'm certainly
not throwing my iMac in my bag when I head out on the town.  But maybe
Apple's right.  Maybe folks should just keep an ugly old SuperDrive in a
drawer for those rare occasions when they need it.  Then they can
appreciate beautiful design every day.  Even if it means leaning over
their desks to do so.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comments on Blogs]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/01/06/comments-on-blogs/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougmckee.github.com/blog/2012/01/06/comments-on-blogs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's become very trendy on tech blogs to not allow comments on articles.
And at least a couple of folks
(<a href="http://mattgemmell.com/2011/11/29/comments-off/">Matt Gemmell</a> and
<a href="http://brooksreview.net/2011/11/gemmell-comments/">Ben Brooks</a> have been
actively trying to convince other bloggers to turn off their comments too.  I
agree that if you've got a popular blog (and maybe a thin skin), turning
off comments can make your life easier.  I would even agree that on
popular blogs (and websites more generally) many (most?)  comments don't
really further the discussion.  In fact, I read most of my blogs
(including Matt's and Ben's) inside
<a href="http://reederapp.com/">an RSS reader</a> and so I don't even see any of
the comments that might or might not be there unless I click through to
the site itself.</p>

<p>But I have three objections to their position on comments.  First, when
you don't get much traffic (I'm looking at you High Variance) and you
know most of the people reading your blog, it's really nice to get as
much feedback as possible and I think comments are the best way to do
that.  If someone reading my article has something interesting to say
about it, the comment gives them an audience.  They can always email if
they want to say something privately,</p>

<p>Second, I often like to read what other people have to say about an
article (whether I've written it or not), even when I have to wade
through some less than insightful stuff.  Again, the signal-to-noise
ratio is particularly high in the early days of a blog when it's mostly
friends reading, but even on a big messy site like
<a href="http://www.espn.com">espn.com</a> I think it's fun to see the popular
reaction to a story.  And yes, I get it that the sample is not even
representative of the readership let alone the general population.  I
think <a href="http://slashdot.org">Slashdot</a> is a terrific example of how
constructive (and entertaining) discussion of an issue can happen on the
web through comments.</p>

<p>Third, there's this high horse attitude that if people have something to
say about an article, they should just write it up as an article on
their own blog.  And if the original author reads it and wants to
comment back, they will write another article on their blog.  I'm sorry,
but this just doesn't happen.  I mean, I've seen blogs comment on other
blogs, but in almost every case the debate stops there.  And it's
impossible for someone visiting the original site to see the
conversation at all.  And, believe it or not, there are people with
intelligent things to say that don't have a blog.</p>

<p>Maybe I'll change my tune in the future when I'm drowning in haters and
forum-spam, but I have a feeling that's going to be a while.  Until
then, comments will stay turned on.</p>

<p><a href="http://highvariance.net/post/15402930759/update-comments-on-blogs">UPDATE HERE</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
