<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tech | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/tech/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-24T12:49:04-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stock prices are not grades for last quarter]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/24/stock-prices-are-not-grades/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/24/stock-prices-are-not-grades</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past few quarters, I’ve noticed a disturbing pattern. At some point near the end of the financial quarter, professional stock analysts predict Apple’s numbers (e.g., profit and revenue) to go up a lot. The market takes these predictions seriously and the stock price adjusts to take them into account. Then Apple does report good numbers (usually record-breaking) but not quite as good as the analysts predicted.  The stock goes down as the market adjusts using the new (factual) information about how well the company is doing.  This is all perfectly normal.  </p>

<p>The disturbing part is that the Apple tech writer blogosphere then complains that it doesn’t make sense.  Their logic seems to be that because Apple just did really well, they should be rewarded for it and the stock should go up. They think the expectations shouldn’t matter.  They don’t seem to understand that stock prices are a function of currently held capital and <em>expectations</em> of future performance. Sigh. If these writers want to be mad about something, they should be mad that the analysts are doing a lousy job at predicting Apple’s performance. They shouldn’t be surprised by basic market behavior.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Siracusa 2016]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/04/siracusa-2016/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/04/siracusa-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-siracusa-2016.jpg" alt="Siracusa 2016" /></p>

<p>Fellow Americans, our country has come a long way in the last 50 years. We have had our first <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_F._Kennedy">Catholic president</a>, our first <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">African-American president</a>, and almost our first <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mormon president</a>. In a few generations we will almost certainly have our first gay president. I say the time has come for our first geek president and John Siracusa is the perfect<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> person for the job.</p>

<p>For those of you who have never heard of him, Mr. Siracusa is a software developer by day and an ace gamer, devoted father, loving husband, and nerd celebrity by night. He’s most known for his <a href="http://arstechnica.com/apple/2011/05/mac-os-x-revisited/">tour-de-force</a> reviews of (Mac) OS X and more recently for his wide-ranging soapbox podcast <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical">Hypercritical</a>.  It is these venues where Mr. Siracusa has demonstrated he has the skills our country needs.</p>

<p>He is the ultimate natural analyst, able to glance at anything and quickly identify its strengths and (especially) weaknesses. While he typically applies his super-power to tech products<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, it will be amazing to see him use it to intelligently dissect and choose among potential public policies.  </p>

<p>Mr. Siracusa is also blessed with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vision_thing">big picture vision</a>, a critical requirement for a successful chief executive.  He can tell you about the future of <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/31">computing</a>, <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/63">software distribution</a>, <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/1">TV</a>, and even <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/18">toasters</a>. His ideas about using <a href="http://the-magazine.org/2/strange-game">artificial worlds as petri dishes for social policy</a> are exciting and promising (if not <a href="http://christakis.med.harvard.edu/pdf/publications/articles/126.pdf">completely original</a>). Once he throws off the corporation-imposed shackles banning political discourse that bound him on Hypercritical, I am certain we will see a beautiful clear vision for the future of America and indeed the planet. </p>

<p>Mr. Siracusa has the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iran–Contra_affair">integrity</a>, <a href="http://www.snopes.com/quotes/internet.asp">humility</a>, and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lewinsky_scandal">moral compass</a> that the American public wants in a president but is so often lacking. He has a warm heart and is unafraid to defend unpopular groups–nerds, cosplaying-wanna-be-nerds, homosexuals, and trans-sexuals are all welcome in <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/96">his big tent</a>.  He’s a humble every-man who is able to <a href="http://vimeo.com/46369728">make fun of himself</a> and his election season cameos on Saturaday Night Live will surely be hilarious. While a presidential campaign always brings out the muck rackers, I’d be shocked if they unearthed any Siracusa scandals.</p>

<p>December 28, 2012 was a sad day as the <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/100">final Hypercritical episode</a> was recorded, but think about it this way: John Siracusa now has a big hole in his schedule to fill.  America needs him!</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>OK, he’s not <em>perfect</em>. I don’t know if he’s ever left the country so maybe he’d have to brush up on foreign policy.  And sure, he has no executive experience and eschews management jobs.  And he doesn’t like risk.  But <em>no one</em> is perfect.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>My favorite example is his obsession with video game controllers which he demonstrates convincingly in episodes <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/49">49</a>, <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/50">50</a>, and <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/99">99</a> of Hypercritical.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scratching my nerd itch with Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/29/scratching-my-nerd-itch/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/29/scratching-my-nerd-itch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I started this blog, I chose a platform that would give me a site that looked fine out of the box so I could concentrate on the writing.  <a href="http://www.tumblr.com">Tumblr</a> fit this requirement and even provided several nice features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Built-in search</li>
  <li>Organization with tags so visitors could easily find articles by category</li>
  <li>Easy integration with Disqus comments</li>
  <li>Built-in <a href="http://www.usa.gov/Topics/Reference-Shelf/Libraries/RSS-Library/What-Is-RSS.shtml">RSS feed</a> for those who want to subscribe</li>
  <li>Automatic announcement of new articles to Facebook</li>
  <li>Easy integration with <a href="http://www.google.com/analytics/">Google Analytics</a> (for traffic statistics)</li>
</ul>

<p>Now, a year later, I have more of a vision for what I want to do with the site and I’m ready to tinker a bit. Unfortunately, while there’s some flexibility in how a Tumblr site looks, but they don’t give you any real control. Ever since high school I’ve spent regular chunks of time writing code and bending computers to my will. I’ve done this as a professional software developer, as a research economist, and often just messing around. The last year has been less geeky than usual as I’ve concentrated on teaching and less technical research projects.  It’s time to scratch my nerd itch.</p>

<p>I’ve chosen to switch to a particularly nerdy blog platform (<a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a>) that requires using command-line tools, but it has the huge benefit of total control. Octopress is built on top of <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll#readme">Jekyll</a> which is written in <a href="http://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</a> and I can tweek it as much as I’d like. I’ve always wanted to learn Ruby and reading and modifying other other people’s code is a great way to learn a language.</p>

<p>In addition to Octopress/Jekyll/Ruby, this project gets me up to speed on several other modern nerdy technologies:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://mxcl.github.com/homebrew/">Homebrew</a> is a package manager for MacOS that lets you install all sorts of open source software including the latest version of Ruby.</li>
  <li><a href="http://git-scm.com">git</a> is what version control will look like for years to come–it’s fast, collaborative, distributed, and flexible.</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com">Github</a> is where all the coolest open source projects live these days.  Any new software I write that I want to share will go here.    </li>
  <li><a href="http://sass-lang.com">Sass</a> (Syntactically Awesome Style Sheets) is a powerful layer on top of CSS (Cascading Style Sheets) that allows for powerful adaptive layout of HTML pages.</li>
</ul>

<p>While Octopress is in part an excuse to fiddle with new tech, it also feels very comfortable as articles are written in <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown</a>–a very lightweight text-based markup language that I lately find myself using for almost everything.</p>

<h2 id="whats-new">What’s New?</h2>

<p>On the surface, the site shouldn’t look all that different, but beyond the engine being replaced, there are several subtle changes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A real <a href="http://highvariance.net/about.html">About</a> page</li>
  <li>Links up top for the main categories I tend to write about</li>
  <li>A search bar near the top of every page</li>
  <li>Quick links to my recent posts and my favorite posts.</li>
  <li>Much better layout for mobile devices</li>
  <li>Super-fast rendering since Octopress generates the whole site as static HTML which just sits on the server</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="was-it-easy-to-migrate-from-tumblr">Was it Easy to Migrate from Tumblr?</h2>

<p>Two things helped a lot: The Octopress documentation is excellent and I already had all the articles on my local machine in Markdown. The only thing that was tricky was backwards compatibility as I wanted all my old URL’s to work and all my discussions to transfer over.  I used the <a href="https://github.com/tsmango/jekyll_alias_generator">alias-generator</a> plugin and a little elbow grease to make all my Tumblr URL’s redirect to my new URL’s.   </p>

<p>Disqus (the service that keeps track of comments) says they will crawl your new site and use any redirects it provides to update their database.  Unfortunately, while <em>browsers</em> can understand the redirects that the alias-generator creates<sup id="fnref:fn_ag"><a href="#fn:fn_ag" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> just fine, the <em>disqus crawler</em> does not.  So I had to create a csv file that mapped all the old URL’s to the new ones and upload that.</p>

<p>Announcements of new articles on Facebook are now handled by <a href="http://ifttt.com">IFTTT</a>.  It will likely take a little fine-tuning to get these right.</p>

<h2 id="whats-on-the-horizon">What’s on the Horizon?</h2>

<p>The primary emphasis of this site remains the text, but I do want to integrate a little more media–even just a few pictures here and there would be nice. I want the category pages to have their own looks. Beyond that, all I know is that I’ve now got the power to do anything.  Should be fun!</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn_ag">
      <p>Since the site is static, it can’t actually send HTTP
301 permanent redirects. Instead, the alias-generator creates HTML stub files for all the old URL’s with http-equiv meta tags containing the new locations of the URLs.<a href="#fnref:fn_ag" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Blogoversary!]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/22/happy-blogoversary/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/12/22/happy-blogoversary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first time I saw the World Wide Web, I was hunched over an 8 lb laptop using a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynx_(web_browser)">text based browser</a> and a 56k modem. There wasn’t much to see and it didn’t seem like a big deal. Then about three month’s later <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NCSA_Mosaic">NCSA Mosaic</a> (the first graphical browser) was released and I “got it.” Within a week <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NaviSoft">we</a> redefined our product line and turned a generic set of “network publishing” tools into a web server and a web authoring tool.  Within a year we were purchased by America Online to show that they “got” the web too. My point is that I’ve been deeply embedded in the web for a long time.  </p>

<p>And yet, not including my professional <a href="http://www.econ.yale.edu/~dm529">web-based resume/cv</a>, I didn’t have my own website until exactly a year ago when High Variance was <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/14573237390/first-post">born</a>. I’m not sure why it took me so long to get here, but after a year of any project, I think it’s important to step back and take stock to see if the original goals are being met. I had three:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Create more:</strong>  As expected, the topics have been eclectic ranging from economic policy to kid book reviews to eighties pop music.  The rate of production has been similarly irregular with a burst of activity last January (17 posts) and a summer hiatus.  But the aggregate rate has been about one post per week.  I’m happy with this.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Learn to write better and more comfortably:</strong> Perhaps my biggest surprise is how enjoyable the whole process has been. I don’t get anxious when I write here and my anxiety level when writing professionally has definitely decreased.  When my mind is spinning about a topic, writing about it actually gets me to calm down and figure out what I actually think about it.  As for the quality of the writing, I think I’m getting better, but it’s hard to tell.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Provide entertaining, useful, and/or inspiring content:</strong> My audience will need to be the judge of this, but I know I’ve given at least a few chuckles, a few bits of helpful advice, and even tugged on a few heartstrings.  And in looking back on what I’ve written, much of the content seems to have aged well.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>I suppose I should also say something about my readership. According to Google Analytics, over the past year I’ve have 2,070 unique visitors (5.7 per day) and 4,000 page views (11 per day). Not much, but if you squint at the chart, it does look like traffic is trending slightly up.  There are even a few posts that get regular search engine traffic–<a href="http://highvariance.net/post/18591130112/why-are-zebras-so-mean-and-horses-so-nice">zebras</a>, <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/23166850855/pdf-annotation-on-the-ipad-in-2012">pdf annotation on the iPad</a>, and <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/16047390011/mincer-1958">Mincer 1958</a> are the top three.</p>

<p>As I was about to blow out the candles on my birthday cake a few weeks ago I realized something very special: I didn’t have anything new to wish for.  I have a wonderful wife and two lovely children.  We’re all healthy and happy with our jobs and our house.  I just want what I already have.  That’s kind of true of this blog too.  So here’s to another fun and fulfilling year!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A few comments on Apple's Big October Event]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/10/25/apple-observations/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/10/25/apple-observations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Apple’s big October product announcements are now behind us and I’ve
read more blogger reactions than I care to admit.  Even I’m surprised
that I still have a few somewhat original thoughts of my own to share.
Instead of simply being an “iPad mini” event Apple announced a whole
slew of products.  While some folks predicted some of the “extra”
stuff, I don’t think anyone expected the sheer quantity we saw.  That
said, I’m most excited about two products Apple did not announce:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>A new Thunderbolt display:</strong> The new iMac is beautiful and I can’t
wait until they translate it into a stand-alone display.  Less glare and
pixels closer to the glass will be terrific.  It will also give Apple a
chance to add a few ports that they neglected on the first rev: USB 3
and analog audio out.  And imagine how thin it will be when it doesn’t
have to also house a whole computer?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Fusion Drive:</strong> I know, I know, they DID announce this as an
option for the new iMac and Mac Mini, but I’m hoping they will sell it
separately so I can stick one in my 2010 iMac.  I really like the idea
of having the speed of an SSD and the size of a traditional HD without
the hassle of managing the pair.  We’ll have to wait for the iFixit
teardown to see if it has a new interface (and is thus incompatible) and
something tells me even if it has standard wiring, Apple will want to
reserve this feature as reason for folks to upgrade their old (but
perfectly usable) iMacs.  I can still dream.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>There’s been a lot of talk about how Apple is making a mistake by
pricing the iPad mini at $329 and leaving breathing room for the other
cheaper small tablets in the market.  I think Apple priced the product
as high as possible such that they will sell all the mini’s they can make
before the holidays.  If they didn’t, they would simply be leaving money
on the table.  When their supply chain gets up to speed some time in the
spring, I predict they will drop the price below $300.</p>

<p>I have very mixed feelings about the new iMac.  While it’s gorgeous and
powerful, I’m not sure I agree with the sacrifices Apple had to make to
achieve its super-model-thin curves.  Most iMac owners spend
the bulk of their time in <em>front</em> of their iMac where they never even
see the curves–my own is right up against a wall, and I’d have to lean
over and around my desk to appreciate the sides and back.</p>

<p>Apple loves to be first to cast old standards aside: Remember when the
iMac dropped the floppy drive?  I think they were the first PC maker to
stop using special keyboard and mouse ports and just rely on USB.  And
just a month ago they said goodbye to the venerable Dock Connector.  Now
they want to do the same thing to the optical drive.  For a notebook,
this makes perfect sense: In the last year there was exactly one time
when it would have been nice to mount a CD on my Air and that is
certainly not enough to justify the added weight and bulk of a drive.
At my desk, I do rip the occasional DVD or used CD.  And I’m certainly
not throwing my iMac in my bag when I head out on the town.  But maybe
Apple’s right.  Maybe folks should just keep an ugly old SuperDrive in a
drawer for those rare occasions when they need it.  Then they can
appreciate beautiful design every day.  Even if it means leaning over
their desks to do so.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
