<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[tech | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/tech/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-30T22:06:03-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploiting Irrationality]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/01/30/exploiting-irrationality/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2014/01/30/exploiting-irrationality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-floss.png"></p>

<p>When I was growing up, none of the several clocks in the house told the correct time. My mother would set them all between 5 and 30 minutes fast in an effort to fool herself into leaving the house when she was supposed to. I thought this was completely insane. Why not just wake up early enough to do what you needed to do, and then do that? Why play these games with yourself when pure rationality would suffice?</p>

<p>The answer (of course) is that my mother is far from completely rational, and this system worked for her in a way that my proposed system just didn’t. And while I like to think that I’m not as crazy as my mother, I’m not an automaton either. It’s taken me a long time to give in to that and start exploiting some of my foibles for good.</p>

<p>A few weeks ago, I read <a href="http://www.macworld.com/article/2085007/the-iphone-habit-apps-that-help-you-keep-your-new-years-resolutions.html">an article</a> by my productivity sensei (<a href="http://macsparky.com">David Sparks</a>) where he recommended an iPhone app called <a href="http://habitlist.com">Habit List</a> for folks trying to kickstart good habits. There’s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Habit">some scientific research</a> that says if you can somehow get yourself to do something regularly for a few weeks, it becomes a lot easier to continue doing it. There’s also some <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Candy_Crush">evidence</a> that games can be addictive. In a nutshell, Habit List makes doing mundane things into a game. By the time you’re bored with the game, the habit has been formed.</p>

<p>Since I installed Habit List, I’ve managed to floss every day except one (thanks stomach flu!). My exercise program has been less successful, but that’s more the fault of the cold weather and that same stomach flu than a failure of the app. You can bet that I’ll be plugging in some more easy-to-ignore-but-good-for-me chores soon.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Home Music System 3.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/31/home-music-streaming-3/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/31/home-music-streaming-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://daringfireball.net/2013/12/the_year_in_apple_and_technology">John Gruber</a> loves to talk about how technology improves primarily through a series of small steps and the occasional big jump. While the first iPhone was revolutionary, the iPhone 5s is a far better product due to several incremental improvements, none of which got much attention along the way. In the last year, three small things changed in my home music system that make it better than <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/16/home-music-streaming-2/">the last time I wrote about it</a> and a <strong>lot</strong> better than when I <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/02/home-music-streaming/">first wrote about it</a>.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-itunes-radio.jpeg"></p>

<h2 id="itunes-radio">1. iTunes Radio</h2>

<p>Right after releasing iOS 7, Apple updated it’s Remote app to 4.0. This is the app that lets you control iTunes on your computer from your phone. The main changes to the app were to the user interface–it became “lighter,” with thin fonts and textual buttons, and allowed you to move backwards by grabbing the left side of the screen and swiping. Feature-wise, it wasn’t much different from the previous version. This drove me crazy because iTunes Radio had just been launched and the new Remote app had not yet added support for it.</p>

<p>When iTunes Radio was just a rumor, I wasn’t very interested as it seemed like it would be a simple clone of Pandora. The strange thing is that it <strong>did</strong> turn out to be a straight-forward clone of <a href="http://www.pandora.com">Pandora</a>, but I listened to it much more than I ever listened to Pandora. The integration with the iTunes Store is really nice. iTunes Radio keeps track of all the songs I’ve ever listened to, and with one click I can see a song in the iTunes Store, check out the whole album, and <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/02/06/albums/">maybe even buy it</a>. I also like the stations that are built in–tween pop is pretty good (for the kids, of course) and pop country is well curated too. </p>

<p>Like Pandora, I can pick any artist and iTunes will create a custom radio station for them. Since there’s no Metalcore station built-in, I made a station out of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Killswitch_Engage">Killswitch Engage</a>, the prototypical metalcore band. Unlike Pandora (as far as I can tell), iTunes Radio lets me “tune” the station to play more or less popular tracks by related artists by choosing “Hits,” “Variety,” or “Discovery” mode. And the pretty uncluttered UI in the iOS app is just what you would expect from Apple–definitely nicer than Pandora’s.</p>

<p>In early December, Apple released Remote 4.1 with support for iTunes Radio and now I can stream it all over the house. Remote won’t show my Radio listening history and it’s laggier than I’d like, but I still use it all the time.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-pioneer-a4.jpeg"></p>

<h2 id="my-new-pioneer-a4">2. My new Pioneer A4</h2>

<p>Lots of folks are perfectly happy playing music on their iPhone and sending it to a nearby speaker with either Bluetooth or a dock. My Airplay-from-a-server set up has several advantages that in my mind outweigh the small amount of added complexity and expense.  Since my phone is only controlling the music and not playing it, it doesn’t use up any power or need to be close by when the music is playing. That means I can wander to the other side of the house with my phone in my pocket and the music doesn’t come crashing to a halt. The sound quality over Airplay is better than over Bluetooth, and I don’t have to store any big music files on my phone–my whole library just sits on the Mac in my office. </p>

<p>My favorite feature of the set up is being able to stream simultaneously to several speakers around the house, and this just got even better as I’ve added a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Pioneer-XW-SMA4-K-Speaker-featuring-Wireless/dp/B00903HKXI">Pioneer A4 Airplay speaker</a> in the basement. The A4 got an amazingly <a href="http://thewirecutter.com/reviews/the-best-airplay-speaker/">positive review</a> in <a href="http://thewirecutter.com">the Wirecutter</a>, and was just $200, even though it sounds like it should cost much more. The set up instructions are horrific, but the set up itself was not so bad. I’m a little perplexed about why Pioneer would discontinue it without an obvious replacement product, but they did. If you have one or manage to get your hands on one, I highly recommend holding the input button down for 3 seconds to turn on Quick Start Mode. This changes the start up time from 35 seconds to under 5 seconds, and while they don’t tell you how much extra power it burns standing by, it’s definitely worth it.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-airfoil.jpeg"></p>

<h2 id="simplified-configuration-for-spotify">3. Simplified configuration for Spotify</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.rogueamoeba.com/airfoil/">Airfoil</a> is the application on my Mac that grabs output from <a href="https://www.spotify.com/us/">Spotify</a> and sends it to any Airplay destination(s) I choose in the house. When Apple released <a href="http://arstechnica.com/apple/2013/10/os-x-10-9/">Mavericks</a>, the new power management features broke Airfoil. The latest version of Airfoil works around this and also bakes in support for remote control, so I don’t need to run a separate Airfoil helper application anymore. <a href="http://remoteless.no">Remoteless</a>, the iOS app for controlling Spotify on the Mac also released an update recently that supports Airfoil directly, so I no longer need a separate Airfoil remote app on my phone.  The only software programs I need now to play almost any album anywhere in the house are Spotify and Airfoil running on the Mac, and Remoteless on iOS.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PDF Expert 5.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/30/pdf-expert-5/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/30/pdf-expert-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-pdf-expert-5.jpeg"></p>

<p>More than a year ago I wrote <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/05/16/pdf-annotation-on-the-ipad-in-2012/">a quick review</a> of what I thought were the three best PDF annotation apps on the iPad. The clear winner for my needs was <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/app/id743974925?mt=8&amp;ign-mpt=uo%3D4">PDF Expert</a>. Things haven’t changed much since then. <a href="http://brooksreview.net">Ben Brooks</a> just did a <a href="http://thesweetsetup.com/apps/best-pdf-manager-editor-ipad/">super-comprehensive review</a> over at <a href="http://thesweetsetup.com">The Sweet Setup</a>, and the latest version of PDF Expert (5.0) floated to the top. I just upgraded and worked it through its paces grading twenty 15-20 page papers. </p>

<p>All the features PDF Expert had before are still there, and now they all work just a little better. The new annotation toolbar sits on the side taking up very little room. You can have multiple documents open simultaneously in separate tabs. I flipped back and forth between each student’s final paper and their graded midterm draft so I could see if how they incorporated my earlier feedback. The synchronization with Dropbox is more reliable than it was–I used to get the occasional failed sync and 5.0 has been rock solid.</p>

<p>There are lots of new features I haven’t even tried yet. The most intriguing is a review mode that let’s you edit the text and then transforms those edits into MS Word Track Changes style annotations. If I’m working on a document with someone, I would <em>much</em> rather see their changes in a source format (like MS Word) where I can choose to accept or reject the changes. On the other hand, if I’m giving heavy-handed feedback to a student on a draft, this might be just the ticket.</p>

<p>My only complaint about 5.0 is ridiculously minor: when I backspace delete in a text box, the text flickers. That’s it–everything else works great. </p>

<p>For the last several months I’ve done most of my PDF annotation on the Mac. A big screen and a real keyboard are advantages that are hard to beat. PDF Expert 5.0 has brought me back to the iPad. In portrait mode, I can thumb-type fast enough and the new toolbar is very efficient. With my reading glasses and a 12 point font, my iPad’s screen size is fine. It’s nice to be able to spend some productive time on my couch again.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Photo Management Quest, Part 3: Dropbox and Friends]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/13/pq3-dropbox-and-friends/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/13/pq3-dropbox-and-friends</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(Note: You might want to read my other <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/photo/">posts about photo management</a> for context first.)</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-dropbox.jpg"></p>

<p>I am extremely happy to report some actual forward progress in this episode of My Photo Management Quest.  The short story is that all my photos now live on Dropbox in a nice hieararchical folder structure where I can browse and share them from any of my computers or iOS devices. My new system isn’t perfect, but it’s pretty good and I think it’s a solid foundation for the future.</p>

<h2 id="moving-from-iphoto-to-dropbox">Moving from iPhoto to Dropbox</h2>

<p>iPhoto is fundamentally an application for doing light editing and organization of photos on a single computer. Any new system that involves access from multiple different devices is going to require getting your photos out of iPhoto’s black box. My first step was to do <a href="http://www.macstories.net/tutorials/moving-from-iphoto-to-dropbox/">what Federico Vittici at MacStories did</a> through a combination of <a href="http://code.google.com/p/phoshare/">PhoShare</a> and <a href="http://www.noodlesoft.com/hazel.php">Hazel</a>.  The process created a set of year folders, and in each of those, a set of month folders that contain all my photos named and sorted by date. I also followed his lead and created a Hazel rule to move files from the Camera Uploads folder (where Dropbox puts my just-taken photos and videos) into my new Photos hierarchy. That means I need do absolutely nothing after I click my iPhone’s shutter button for my photos to be organized and accessible (by me) forever in the cloud. What a breath of fresh air compared to Apple’s Photo Stream!</p>

<p>My photos currently take up about 20GB, and Dropbox charges $99 per 100GB. Give how rock solid Dropbox is and how many iOS apps support it, I think that’s a great deal. </p>

<h2 id="further-organization-and-editing-on-the-mac">Further Organization and Editing on the Mac</h2>

<p>I’ve been manually adding a bit more organization in two ways. First, I’ve split some months into separate events. For example, I created a “2013-10-halloween” folder (inside the “2013” folder) that contains the requisite costume and pumpkin photos. These photos no longer live in the generic “2013-10” folder. I’ve also created a few special folders (e.g., “yummy-things”) outside the date-based hierarchy that have <em>copies</em> of some pictures in the date-based hierarchy.  That way I can find those pictures by date or subject. I can also easily share these folders (read-only) with friends and family using Dropbox shared links. </p>

<p>The best way I’ve found so far to actually create these new folders is Coverflow view in Finder. It’s <a href="https://discussions.apple.com/message/23562534#23562534">buggy in Mavericks</a> and it doesn’t let me see enough at the same time, but it works. I’m sure there are better ways (maybe <a href="http://unboundformac.com">Unbound for Mac</a> when it’s more stable, maybe <a href="http://www.arcsoft.com/photoplus/">Photo+ by Arcsoft</a>, maybe <a href="http://www.lynapp.com">Lyn</a>) but I haven’t settled on one yet.</p>

<p>One of the biggest advantages of having my photos live in the file system is that I’m not locked into iPhoto for editing–I can now use whatever app I want. <a href="http://www.pixelmator.com">Pixelmator</a> is nice and I’m sure I’ll eventually settle on an even lighter weight app for easy stuff (e.g., cropping/red-eye reduction/brightness adjustment).</p>

<h2 id="browsing-on-ios">Browsing on iOS</h2>

<p>Now that my photos live in Dropbox, I have at least three choices of iOS apps to browse them.  The <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/iphoneapp">Dropbox app</a>’s photo tab lets me scroll through thumbnails of all my photos sorted by date and download full resolution versions as needed. I can also browse the folder structure through the standard file browing UI and grab photos, though I don’t get a pretty set of big thumbnails.  Playing videos and sharing links to files and folders is easy.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/hv-heliog.png"></p>

<p><a href="http://www.heliogapp.com">Heliog</a> is fast and pretty–it preserves my folder hierarchy and shows nice screens of thumbnails. I can share folders or sets of photos and easily move photos between folders. The downsides are that it doesn’t play video and I can’t delete photos from the photo view (have to be in the album view). These both seem easily fixable.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-unbound.jpg"></p>

<p>Right now, I think <a href="http://unboundapp.com">Unbound</a> is the best of the bunch.  Unlike Heliog, it plays videos and let’s me delete photos from the photo view. Like Heliog, sharing Dropbox links is easy and browsing is fast–you can even make the app cache folders for quicker (or offline) access. Unbound will show you all the photo’s EXIF data and even show where a photo was taken on a map. Moving pictures between folders is easy, but I don’t think it’s possible to copy pictures to other albums. It shows me all my folders, but flattens the hierarchy–i.e., my month folders are no longer grouped by year. The ordering is correct, so this isn’t actually so bad.</p>

<h2 id="the-future">The Future</h2>

<p>The next step for my photo management system is to integrate the rest of our family photos. Right now they’re scattered across several computers, folders and hard drives with tons of duplicates. Dropping these photos into my Camera Uploads folder will immediately sort them into my master folder structure, but it won’t remove duplicates. There are lots of apps out there that promise to remove duplicates, but I’m scared to death that they’ll remove too much and the one app I tried (<a href="http://www.duplicatephotofixer.com/PhotoCleaner.aspx">Photos Duplicate Cleaner</a>) didn’t come close to catching everything. </p>

<p>In the early days of the internet, companies like Yahoo tried organizing the web by manually creating big hiearchical lists of sites. Now we just Google for what we want and leave it to racks of servers and fancy algorithms to index it. The same thing has happened to mail. I used to carefully file all my mail into topic-specific folders, but now I just dump it all into one archive folder and rely on search when I need to find something. Photos will eventually be handled the same way. People won’t have to spend gobs of time dividing stacks of photos into events or tagging photos with their friends’ names–that’s what EXIF data and face recognition are for.  Everpix (may they rest in peace) was moving in this direction and I’ve heard <a href="http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2013/12/honan-photography/">great things about what Google+ is doing with pictures</a>. </p>

<p>I am very excited to try some more cutting edge services as they roll out. With our photos safely backed up and accessible on Dropbox, I won’t have to worry about being locked into a deadend or that the service will mess up my photos.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> I’ll have the best of both worlds.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>For the record, Everpix did both: they made export very difficult and compressed photos, losing detail that I might eventually want. <a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Online tech in an in-person seminar: An experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/10/online-tech-in-an-in-person-seminar/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/10/online-tech-in-an-in-person-seminar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve written about <a href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/05/20/seminars/">how I like to run seminar classes</a> before and you may have noticed that my approach is decidedly low tech. My students read the week’s articles before class and fill out a “worksheet” for each one. Before this semester, the most important question on the worksheet was “What didn’t you understand?” I would look over their answers to identify weak spots that we would  cover in class.</p>

<p>This semester I tried something new: I took “What didn’t you understand?” off the worksheet and asked my students to post questions they had about the reading on a <a href="http://piazza.com">Piazza</a> online discussion forum. If two (or more) students have the same question, only the first has to post it–the others could just mark it as a “good question.” They could also answer each other’s questions and I could “approve” answers or provide my own. I had high hopes for the new system. I thought it would be easier for the students, and would make it easier for me to see what the hot button issues were and even provide some feedback before class. </p>

<p>It didn’t work very well. Even with a fair amount of cajoling during the semester, I would only get 4-5 students (of 24) participating in the forum each week. Based on feedback during the last class, it seems there were three primary reasons. First, it wasn’t clear to many of them that they could post their questions anonymously and they didn’t want to embarrass themselves in front of their fellow students by posting potentially “dumb” questions. Second, several students felt they were done with the assignment after they filled out their worksheets. They didn’t want to take the time to go to the Piazza web site for more work. Third, they didn’t like posting questions that weren’t going to get answered on the forum.</p>

<p>I’m not ready to give up on the idea, but I’m also not sure what to do differently next semester. I can try more cajoling on the first day of class and I can let everyone know that they can post anonymously. I can also commit to answering questions before class. The worksheets and questions are due on Monday night, so that gives me plenty of time before Wednesday’s class to provide at least basic answers. I’m still not sure this will be enough to get mass participation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
