<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[conan | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/conan/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-01T00:04:12-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conan the Snowman]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/27/conan-the-snowman/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/12/27/conan-the-snowman</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/hv-conan-the-snowman.jpg"></p>

<p>Conan the Snowman, was a fierce barbaric soul,<br />
With a sword of steel and a battle cry, total victory was his goal.  </p>

<p>Conan the Snowman, is a fantasy, they say.<br />
He was from far North, but the children know, he raided their village one day.  </p>

<p>There must have been some anger in that well-worn blade he held,<br />
For when he swung it round his head, his enemies they were felled.    </p>

<p>Oh, Conan, the Snowman, was alive as he could be;<br />
and the children say he could laugh and slay,<br />
any man and his family.  </p>

<p>Thumpety thump, thump, thumpety thump, thump,<br />
look at their heads roll. </p>

<p>Thumpety thump, thump, thumpety thump, thump,<br />
vanquishing his foe.  </p>

<p>Conan the Snowman, knew the sun was hot that day,<br />
so he said, “Let’s fight, all day and all night, until rain washes the blood away.”</p>

<p>Raging through the village, with his deadly sword in hand,<br />
Running here and there, all around the square,
sayin’, “Kill me if you can.”</p>

<p>Then he wandered east to a fearsome beast and met it eye to eye.<br />
and only paused a moment, when we heard him scream out, “Die!”  </p>

<p>For Conan, the Snowman, made all his enemies pay,<br />
But he waved goodbye, sayin’ “You better cry,<br />
I’ll be back again some day.”</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Expanding the Market for Limited Edition Dishes]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/03/09/dishes/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/03/09/dishes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/conan-dishes/yorkies.jpg" alt="Yorkies!" /></p>

<p>Limited edition dishes have a very limited market for two main reasons. First, they feature a very limited selection of art. Cute dogs, American flags, flowers, and Russian folk tales only appeal to so many people.  These plates are basically baseball cards for grandmas. Second, most of these dishes are designed solely for display and could actually kill you if you ate off them–this is crazy since the last time I checked normal people used dishes for serving food, not decorating their walls.  These companies need to expand their stables of artists and use nontoxic paints. </p>

<p>To get things started concretely, I propose the following set of four limited edition dinner plates by Frank Frazetta.  Imagine the look of wonder on your guests’ faces as they clear their plates and reveal the raw ferocity and masculinity of Conan the Barbarian. I know I would buy them. Click through to see them in their full resolution glory!</p>

<p><a href="/images/conan-dishes/d1.jpg"><img src="/images/conan-dishes/d1-small.jpg" alt="Conan!" /></a>
<a href="/images/conan-dishes/d2.jpg"><img src="/images/conan-dishes/d2-small.jpg" alt="Conan!" /></a>
<a href="/images/conan-dishes/d3.jpg"><img src="/images/conan-dishes/d3-small.jpg" alt="Conan!" /></a>
<a href="/images/conan-dishes/d4.jpg"><img src="/images/conan-dishes/d4-small.jpg" alt="Conan!" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
