<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[politics | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/politics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-09T23:17:43-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Siracusa 2016]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/04/siracusa-2016/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/04/siracusa-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-siracusa-2016.jpg" alt="Siracusa 2016" /></p>

<p>Fellow Americans, our country has come a long way in the last 50 years. We have had our first <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_F._Kennedy">Catholic president</a>, our first <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">African-American president</a>, and almost our first <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mormon president</a>. In a few generations we will almost certainly have our first gay president. I say the time has come for our first geek president and John Siracusa is the perfect<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> person for the job.</p>

<p>For those of you who have never heard of him, Mr. Siracusa is a software developer by day and an ace gamer, devoted father, loving husband, and nerd celebrity by night. He’s most known for his <a href="http://arstechnica.com/apple/2011/05/mac-os-x-revisited/">tour-de-force</a> reviews of (Mac) OS X and more recently for his wide-ranging soapbox podcast <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical">Hypercritical</a>.  It is these venues where Mr. Siracusa has demonstrated he has the skills our country needs.</p>

<p>He is the ultimate natural analyst, able to glance at anything and quickly identify its strengths and (especially) weaknesses. While he typically applies his super-power to tech products<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, it will be amazing to see him use it to intelligently dissect and choose among potential public policies.  </p>

<p>Mr. Siracusa is also blessed with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vision_thing">big picture vision</a>, a critical requirement for a successful chief executive.  He can tell you about the future of <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/31">computing</a>, <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/63">software distribution</a>, <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/1">TV</a>, and even <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/18">toasters</a>. His ideas about using <a href="http://the-magazine.org/2/strange-game">artificial worlds as petri dishes for social policy</a> are exciting and promising (if not <a href="http://christakis.med.harvard.edu/pdf/publications/articles/126.pdf">completely original</a>). Once he throws off the corporation-imposed shackles banning political discourse that bound him on Hypercritical, I am certain we will see a beautiful clear vision for the future of America and indeed the planet. </p>

<p>Mr. Siracusa has the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iran–Contra_affair">integrity</a>, <a href="http://www.snopes.com/quotes/internet.asp">humility</a>, and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lewinsky_scandal">moral compass</a> that the American public wants in a president but is so often lacking. He has a warm heart and is unafraid to defend unpopular groups–nerds, cosplaying-wanna-be-nerds, homosexuals, and trans-sexuals are all welcome in <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/96">his big tent</a>.  He’s a humble every-man who is able to <a href="http://vimeo.com/46369728">make fun of himself</a> and his election season cameos on Saturaday Night Live will surely be hilarious. While a presidential campaign always brings out the muck rackers, I’d be shocked if they unearthed any Siracusa scandals.</p>

<p>December 28, 2012 was a sad day as the <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/100">final Hypercritical episode</a> was recorded, but think about it this way: John Siracusa now has a big hole in his schedule to fill.  America needs him!</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>OK, he’s not <em>perfect</em>. I don’t know if he’s ever left the country so maybe he’d have to brush up on foreign policy.  And sure, he has no executive experience and eschews management jobs.  And he doesn’t like risk.  But <em>no one</em> is perfect.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>My favorite example is his obsession with video game controllers which he demonstrates convincingly in episodes <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/49">49</a>, <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/50">50</a>, and <a href="http://5by5.tv/hypercritical/99">99</a> of Hypercritical.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Morality of Voting]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/01/20/the-morality-of-voting/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/01/20/the-morality-of-voting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My friend Julian is a pretty nice guy.  He’s generous with his time and
tolerant of most social behavior.  He honors his commitments and is
honest in his communication.  But at the same time, he chooses not to
participate in the US democratic government by voting.  For those of us
who see voting as a moral obligation, this is somewhat disturbing.
Julian recently posted a
<a href="http://tunesforbears.com/2012/01/19/no-really-i-dont-vote/">clear statement of why</a>
on <a href="http://tunesforbears.com">his blog</a> (which makes for a good read in general
BTW).  Since he is economic theorist by training, he makes his argument
by laying out a fairly standard economic model of voting and pointing
out how it is perfectly rational for him to vote and many other people
not to.</p>

<p>In Julian’s model, people benefit from voting in two ways: the (slight)
chance they will personally influence the election and the “warm glow”
(WG) they get from the experience.  If the sum of these outweigh the
costs of missing work and traveling to the polling place, then people
will vote.  Julian justifies his personal decision by saying that most
other people must get a warmer feeling inside when they vote since the
chance of any one person changing the election is tiny.  As
models go, this one is pretty empty (as Julian admits) since so much of
the action happens in WG and it says nothing about where WG comes from.</p>

<p>I think utilitarian models are great for describing behavior, but lousy
for defining what behavior is right or wrong.  Just because someone
might find stealing to be individually rational if their chances of
being caught are low, that doesn’t make it right.  Before I go on, I
want to be perfectly clear that I don’t know anything about
philosophy–I couldn’t even make much sense of this
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Philosophy-Beginners-Writers-Readers-Documentary/dp/086316157X">comic book guide to philosphy</a>
when I read it a few years ago.  That said, Julian’s description of
Kant’s categorical imperative really spoke to me.  In his (Julian’s)
words, “citizens are morally obligated to vote if they prefer a world in
which others do”.  I translate this to mean “it’s immoral to free-ride
on other people’s voting behavior”.  This is a statement <em>outside</em> the
model about behavior that may or may not be rational <em>inside</em> the model.
Julian justifies his own action in this context by saying he wants
everyone to act as he would act <em>conditional on the WG they happen to
feel</em>.</p>

<p>If Kant were here, I think he would say that WG is BS and that people
don’t decide whether or not to vote in order to maximize their
utility–they decide between right and wrong.  I vote because I want
to live in a world where everyone (or at least the informed folks vote),
not because it makes me feel warmer than it does Julian.  To be more
precise, I think WG is almost homogeneously distributed and some people
are moral and some are immoral free-riders.</p>

<p>Of course, my statement about Julian being an upstanding moral guy in
the rest of his life still holds.  :) I just think he’s putting too much
faith in
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fundamental_theorems_of_welfare_economics">the first theorem of welfare economics</a>.
Just because there are some (many?) situations where individually
rational behavior leads to a socially optimal outcome doesn’t mean all
situations are like that.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Obama vs Romney 2012]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/01/01/obama-vs-romney-2012/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/01/01/obama-vs-romney-2012</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An old friend of mine
(<a href="http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/philg/">Philip Greenspun</a>) recently
<a href="http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/philg/2011/12/31/election-prediction-barack-obama-wins-5149/">predicted</a> that Obama will win the 2012 presidency in a close election.
I agree, although for very different reasons.  He thinks that even
though the economy will remain poor, the American public won’t
put the blame entirely on Obama and that they will give him some credit for
ending the war in Iraq.  Phil has more confidence in the American people
than I do.</p>

<p>At this point, the Republican nomination seems to be a two man race
between Romney and Gingrich.  Gingrich is a lunatic and it’s hard to
imagine that even a majority of Republicans would vote for him.  I mean,
the guy left his first wife when she was recovering from cancer
surgery.  And more recently he converted to Catholicism and now panders to
the religious right.  Honestly though, it’s his willingness to just
throw the country into chaos (remember the Contract with America?) based on
whatever principles he happens to hold that day that scares the hell out
of me.</p>

<p>So I think Romney gets the nomination.  Right now, everyone knows him as a boring but competent business
guy who happens to be Mormon.  And Americans have a vague idea that
Mormons believe wacky things. But it’s going to become very clear very
quickly just how wacky that organization is.  Here are just a few of quirks:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://i4m.com/think/intro/mormon-tithing.htm">Mandatory 10% tithing</a>.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.mormon-underwear.com/">Secret under-garments</a>.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.religioustolerance.org/lds_race.htm">Institutionalized racism until 1978</a>.</li>
  <li>I almost forgot <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mormonism_and_polygamy">“plural marriage”</a>!</li>
</ul>

<p>And Romney’s been heavily involved as a church leader almost his whole life.  Christopher Hitchens
wrote a
<a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/fighting_words/2011/10/is_mormonism_a_cult_who_cares_it_s_their_weird_and_sinister_beli.html">great summary for Slate</a>
just a couple months before he died–that’s the sort of story we’re
going to see a lot of.  <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Under-Banner-Heaven-Story-Violent/dp/0385509510">Under the Banner of Heaven</a>
is going to start selling like hot cakes.  The story of Joseph Smith
and then Brigham Young is amazing, even without all the crazy polygamy
stuff.  </p>

<p>By he time the summer rolls around, the press is just going to drag the
Mormon church through the mud.  It’s going to be like watching a car
crash.  As someone who views religion as a great spectator sport, I can’t wait!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
