<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[productivity | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-08T15:56:45-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Things Done with Remember The Milk (i.e., GTD with RTM)]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/05/27/gtd-with-rtm/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/05/27/gtd-with-rtm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every year or so I get cranky about my task management system and switch
to something new.  This year it’s particularly bad because I’ve been
hearing the Siren Song of <a href="http://www.omnigroup.com/products/omnifocus/">OmniFocus</a>.  I swear every nerd blogger I read
uses it: e.g.,</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ben Brooks at <a href="http://brooksreview.net/2010/08/omnifocus-v-things-mac-ipad-iphone/">The Brooks Review</a></li>
  <li>David Sparks at <a href="http://www.macsparky.com/blog/2010/7/30/ipad-omnifocus-review.html">MacSparky</a></li>
  <li>Aleh Cherp at <a href="http://blog.macademic.org/2012/04/02/task-management-with-omnifocus-collecting-and-processing/">Macademic</a></li>
</ul>

<p>I even believe John Gruber (<a href="http://daringfireball.net">Daring Fireball</a>) uses it though he’s a
little cagy since they are often a sponsor of his.</p>

<p>BUT, I strongly believe you shouldn’t switch systems unless you’re
solving specific problems.  That is, I invest in my systems and don’t
want to switch just for fun.  Hearing that some other piece of software
is “really good” or even “better” than what you’re currently using
isn’t good enough for me.</p>

<p>Last year when I made the switch from <a href="http://mail.google.com/mail/help/tasks/">Google Tasks</a> to <a href="http://www.rememberthemilk.com">Remember The Milk</a>
(RTM), I had some clear requirements:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Cross-platform</em>: I was spending time on Mac, Windows, iPad, and
 iPhone and I needed to be able to access my tasks from all of them.</li>
  <li><em>Rock solid invisible sync</em>: I never wanted to think about which
 version of my task list I was working with.  There should be just one
 master copy (preferably in the cloud) that gets seemlessly accessed
 and updated from various clients.</li>
  <li><em>Power and flexibility</em>: Google Tasks met the first two criteria, but it was just too
 simple.  I wanted more than due dates and separate lists.  I wanted
 to be able to attach priorities, contexts, durations, and other
 arbitrary tags.  I wanted to  dynamically create lists based on
 these characteristics that showed me just what I wanted (and was
 able) to do at any particular moment.</li>
</ul>

<p>At the time, RTM was the best solution, but the world has changed since
then.  Omnifocus now provides highly regarded Sync Services.  And I’ve
shed my need for Windows now that I carry a MacBook Air with me
everywhere i go.</p>

<p>Stepping up a level for a moment, the overall task management system you
use is far more important than the particular tool you use to implement
it.  I’m a GTD (Getting Things Done) guy, though I’m not the most
orthodox devotee you’ll meet.  There are two things I love about GTD:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>You get the mental to do list out of your head.  Since you’re not
constantly worrying that you’ll forget something, your mind is freed up
for more interesting creative work.  And you’re not forgetting things!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Once your tasks are organized, GTD provides a way to quickly see what
you can and should be doing in any given context.  This is exactly what
I couldn’t do with Google Tasks.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>After a year of experience (and tweeking), I’ve got an implementation of
my GTD system in Remember The Milk that works pretty well.  Before
casting it aside for a new pretty young thing, I’m going to describe my
system and what works and doesn’t work for me.  It’s almost certainly
not a perfect match for anyone else, but it might give you ideas for
things to try or think about.  </p>

<p>RTM is a simple system that lets you build complex systems on top of it.
Basically, you just define a bunch of lists of tasks with
characteristics.  These characteristics include priorities, due dates,
durations, locations, and arbitrary tags–exactly what I want.  The
power comes from defining Smart Lists that are basically saved searches
based on these characteristics.</p>

<h2 id="projects">Projects</h2>

<p>Even though RTM supports multiple lists, I keep almost all my tasks in
the Inbox list and use other lists only for storing things like books
I’d like to read or ideas for upcoming posts.  I define my projects with
tags.  Home-related projects have tags starting with “ph-“ (e.g.,
“ph-basement”) and work-related projects have tags starting with “pw-“.
Most tasks that go into the system have either a project assigned or a simple
“work” tag.  If it’s a single task home project, I don’t take the time
to assign a project tag at all.</p>

<h2 id="locations">Locations</h2>

<p>I assign each task a single location tag: at-desk, at-phone, at-home,
at-econoffice, at-errand, or at-wife.  The last one is special: tasks
that require consultation with my wife.  Someone else that runs a lot of
errands might find it worth their time to set up several locations that
cause tasks to pop up when they go somewhere, but generally I go
somewhere <em>because</em> I need to do something and so don’t need to get
reminded.</p>

<h2 id="contexts">Contexts</h2>

<p>Coming up with the right set of contexts is critical to the system and
it’s the hardest part. In <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Getting-Things-Done-Stress-Free-Productivity/dp/0142000280">The GTD Book</a>, David Allen talks a lot about home,
office, and phone. With smart phones, the set of things you can do “on
the phone” is far larger than it used to be.  Since I usually have my
laptop with me and most of my resources are online, home office,
work office, and even cafe are almost the same.</p>

<p>Right now I have four smart lists that define my contexts:</p>

<p><strong>c-working</strong> </p>

<pre><code>due:today or dueBefore:today or (list:Inbox and (tagContains:pw- or
tag:work or tag:weekday) and (dueWithin:"5 days of today" or
priority:1 or priority:2 or priority:3))&lt;/tt&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>This is the context I look at during the work day or at night when
I’m working.  It includes everything due today or that’s overdue so I
don’t miss deadlines.  It also includes any tasks associated with
work-related projects or that can only be done during the week
(<tt>tag:weekday</tt>).  The most interesting piece is where I drop all
tasks that are due more than five days from now that have no priority
assigned.  These are the tasks I don’t even want to think about until it
gets closer to their due date.</p>

<p><strong>c-weekend</strong></p>

<pre><code>due:today or dueBefore:today or (not tag:work and not
tagContains:pw- and not tag:weekday and list:Inbox and (dueWithin:"5
days of today" or priority:1 or priority:2 or priority:3))&lt;/tt&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>On weekends and any time I want to focus on the non-work part of my
life I check this list.  It’s almost the inverse of my work context
except that it also includes anything that’s due or past due.</p>

<p><strong>c-out</strong></p>

<pre><code>tag:at-errand or tag:at-phone
</code></pre>

<p>This is what I should and can do when I’m out and about.</p>

<p><strong>c-easy</strong></p>

<pre><code>tag:fun or tag:easy or timeEstimate:"&lt; 1 hour"
</code></pre>

<p>When I’m tired or just have a few minutes, I look at this list.  It’s my
newest context, and I might eventually break it into a tired list and a
separate quick-task list.  </p>

<p>All four of these Smart Lists are sorted first by due date and then by
priority.  I often use <strong>high priority</strong> to mark that a task is the
next action for a project.  This way it’s always listed before other
actions that I want to record but might not be ready to do.  A while
back I read <a href="http://blog.rememberthemilk.com/2008/05/guest-post-advanced-gtd-with-remember-the-milk/">another article</a> about implementing GTD in RTM and it
suggested using an <strong>na</strong> tag.  My system allows me to complete a task
for a project and have the other tasks still show up on the list.  The
last thing I want to do is to constantly be tagging new tasks as <strong>na</strong>
as I complete other tasks.</p>

<p>There are plenty of times when I want to focus on a particular project
and in those cases I simply look at the Tag view for the project and
see all the tasks associated with the project no matter when they are
due or what their priority.</p>

<h2 id="weekly-review">Weekly Review:</h2>

<p>Just as David Allen says, I’ve found that if I don’t do a weekly review,
the information in the system drifts away from the information in my
brain and loses its value.  That’s when most folks fall off the wagon.
So support for the weekly review process is super-important.  Here’s
what I do every week:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Look at my untagged Smart List (<tt>not isTagged:true list:Inbox</tt>)
and assign project (if necessary) or location tags</li>
  <li>Look at the tasks for each project:
    <ul>
      <li>Are any upcoming tasks missing?  </li>
      <li>Are priorities and due dates right?</li>
      <li>Can I delete any tasks that are no longer needed?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Add any new projects that didn’t make it into the system during the week</li>
  <li>Quickly look at all the tasks in the system (usually between 100 and 150)
    <ul>
      <li>Do I need to lower / raise any priorities?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Look at what I accomplished in last week (<tt>completedWithin:”1 week
of today”</tt>)–good for setting feasible future expectations </li>
</ul>

<p>One nice thing about this way of doing weekly reviews is that it can be
done in chunks here and there –I don’t have to set aside the
traditional 2-3 hour block.</p>

<h2 id="room-for-improvement">Room for Improvement</h2>

<p>On the whole, I’m pretty happy with my system, but that doesn’t mean
there’s not lots of room for improvement.  </p>

<p>First, my system isn’t that great for capturing or doing long range
planning.  I can’t specify task dependencies and I can’t even specify
start dates for tasks.  If I could, that would let me filter out tasks
that I know I’m not starting for a while.  I try to follow orthodox GTD
practice and only use due dates for when things are really due. That way
I don’t miss these things in a sea of stuff that I’d like to be done on
that day.</p>

<p>Second, while the iOS apps are very good, I’m getting tired of the
clunky RTM web interface.  It’s functional, but pretty ugly.   I use
Fluid to make RTM a pop down menubar app, but I can’t get it to play
well with multiple Spaces.  That is, when I pop down the app, it pulls
me back to the Space I first started it.  And when RTM automatically
logs me out of the website (more often than I’d like), 
<a href="http://support.agilebits.com/discussions/1password-38-for-mac-from-agilebits-website/11718-1password-with-fluid">I can’t use 1Password to log back bin</a>.  I’m still totally dumbfounded that
no one has built a decent native Mac app for the service.</p>

<p>Third, entering new tasks requires me to click on the menubar app and
then put the cursor in the new task text entry box.  It sure would be
nice to have a global hot key for this.  </p>

<h2 id="bottom-line">Bottom Line</h2>

<p>Remember The Milk bugs me, but it also works for me.  And maybe
Omnifocus wouldn’t be uniformly better.  I’m worried that it would
try to force me into new ways of doing things that just don’t match my
work flow.  Maybe instead I need to check out <a href="http://donaldjenkins.com/2012/02/why-i-switched-from-omnifocus-to-things/">Things</a>….  Or maybe I
just need to get back to work!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PDF Annotation on the iPad in 2012]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/05/16/pdf-annotation-on-the-ipad-in-2012/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/05/16/pdf-annotation-on-the-ipad-in-2012</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve always wanted to live life efficiently.  When I was in third grade
I made a list of all the chores I had to do every morning (like make the
bed) and timed myself doing them. I even made my mom assign quality
grades to each task to make sure I wasn’t sacrificing on that margin for
speed.</p>

<p>I don’t make my bed anymore, but I do grade a lot of papers and I like
to give copious feedback. The returns to optimizing this process are
big. That’s why I recently decided to try out several iPad PDF
annotation apps to find the one that best fits my workflow.</p>

<p>My needs aren’t extreme. I mostly want to highlight, strike-through, and
add colored text. Occasionally I want to underline, add a long note, or
draw a shape. And since all my documents live on Dropbox, I want to
easily sync whole folders. It turns out there are at least three apps
that can do all of these things, but they have some important
differences in how they get there.  Here’s what I’ve found:</p>

<h2 id="goodreader-314"><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/pdf-expert-fill-forms-annotate/id393316844">GoodReader 3.14</a></h2>

<p>GoodReader has been my go-to annotation app for the last six months, and
it sets the bar high.  The only real annoyance is that you have to enter
inline comments (i.e., use the typewriter tool) in a popup editing
window before the app drops your words into the document.  Once
there, it’s easy to grab the comment (by holding a finger on it) and
move or resize the text box.  This is critical since you never know
exactly where or how big the text box will be.  You don’t have any
control over the font for these inline comments and the one it chooses
is cheesy typewriter, but I don’t mind.</p>

<p>Syncing folders with Dropbox is great although the sync button can get
hidden way down in in the “Web Downloads” area are under a long list of
“recent” downloads.  In fact, the whole document management interface is
functional, but messy and unintuitive–i.e., once you know your way
around, you don’t waste a lot of time, but it’s never pretty and there
is a learning curve.</p>

<p>One useful feature I haven’t found in the other apps is a Back button
under the scroll bar that (obviously) puts you back where you were after
you scroll somewhere else or move to a bookmark.  This is great when
you’re flipping between text and tables.</p>

<h2 id="iannotate-pdf-21"><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/iannotate-pdf/id363998953">iAnnotate PDF 2.1</a></h2>

<p>iAnnotate PDF has a clunky name and a cartoony interface.  I think it’s
been around the longest and it’s extremely configurable.  People who use
it swear it does everything they want but it takes a little work up
front to set it up.  I believe them.  And when you add inline text, you
do it in the page itself which is much more natural than typing into GoodReader’s
disembodied text box.</p>

<p>On the downside, it’s been crashy for me.  I’ve been using an original
iPad, so maybe it’s more stable on newer hardware.  It doesn’t have a
scroll bar that lets you move directly to the end (or beginning) of your
document.  It doesn’t always highlight the spaces between words and I
can’t get it to autocorrect when using the typewriter tool.  But even if
these things got fixed, I just find the ugly icons too distracting.</p>

<h2 id="pdf-expert-40"><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/pdf-expert-fill-forms-annotate/id393316844">PDF Expert 4.0</a></h2>

<p>Ah, we have a winner!  PDF Expert is a breath of fresh air.  It has
everything I like about GoodReader (except the back button) in a package
that’s just beautiful to look at.  The document management UI is
super-clean, fast, and intuitive.  It even gives you thumbnails of the
first page of each document.  The icons in the document annotation UI
are simple and classy.  When browsing a pdf, the page turns are very
fast.</p>

<p>On top of this, I don’t know how I lived without PDF Expert’s  undo and
redo commands.  They not only keep you from inadvertently junking up
your document, it means the UI doesn’t ever ask “Are you really
sure?” when you delete something because you can always roll back to the
previous state.  </p>

<p>What’s not to like?  Some people complain that it only opens one
document at a time, but I find opening and closing to be fast
enough that this isn’t a big deal.  My biggest complaint (and it’s
minor) is that you only have 9 colors to choose from for markup and
they’re kind of brash.  It’s like they were inspired by the available
colors for Apple’s <a href="http://www.cultofmac.com/95875/which-smart-cover-to-get-get-a-polyurethane-one-heres-why/">cheap Smart Covers</a>.</p>

<h2 id="honorable-mentions">Honorable Mentions</h2>

<p><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/notability-take-notes-annotate/id360593530">PDFpen</a> has been around for quite a while on the Mac, and if Preview
wasn’t as good as it was, I’d probably be using it there.  But on the
iPad, it’s the new kid on the block.  None of the positive reviews on
the app store compares it with the big three, and a few negative reviews
say it’s crashy and has fewer features.  It will probably improve over
time, but considering it costs the most ($15) and seemingly does the
least, I’m skipping it for now.</p>

<p><a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/notability-take-notes-annotate/id360593530">Notability</a> is really a note-taking app that can also annotate PDF’s.
When I’m in a meeting or seminar, I usually use Nebulous Notes and type
right into a text file.  If I have a copy of the slides or the paper
being presented, I now take my notes right on them with PDF Expert.
Notability is particularly strong with drawing, but I find even with my
Cosmonaut stylus, the lag between moving the pen and seeing my picture
is just too unnatural to replace pen and paper.  </p>

<h2 id="bottom-line">Bottom Line</h2>

<p>PDF Expert is fantastic.  I’m so glad I went through this exercise and
have graduated from GoodReader!  Of course, I could have just read Cynical
Babblings’ <a href="http://cynicalbabblings.wordpress.com/2012/04/05/pdf-editing-apps-2012-review/">recent review</a> of same apps.  I found it while I was
in the middle of my evaluation process, and he’s much more thorough than
I am.  And he also likes PDF Expert best.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Progress Toward Paperless]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/30/progress-toward-paperless/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/03/30/progress-toward-paperless</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love paper—wrapping paper, home made greeting cards, paper mâché
piñatas, a good coffee table book, any <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Wonderful-Wizard-Oz-Commemorative/dp/0689817517">Sabuda pop up book</a>, origami,
even (especially?) paper airplanes—it all makes me happy.  And up until
recently, paper played a big role in my workflow.  I read a lot of
research articles and generally, I would print them and write all over
them.  The act of taking notes forces me to engage and extract much more
than I would if I were passively reading.  These hand-annotated articles
would go into my file cabinet so I could refer to my notes next time I
read the article.  I also grade about 100 student papers per semester
and like to provide copious feedback.  Since my work days are spread
between two or three campus offices and a home office, my <a href="http://highvariance.net/post/16921367136/ode-to-my-messenger-bag">bag</a> would
get pretty heavy.</p>

<p>My writing process also involved a fair bit of paper as I would hand
write almost all my first drafts. It just felt more comfortable than
transferring my thoughts directly to a text file via keyboard, even
though it meant eventually typing up those drafts and having a
paper pad in my bag next to my iPad at all times.</p>

<p>Three things have happened that have allowed me to comfortably
transition the bulk of my previously paper-based work to the digital
world: iPad, cloud storage, and my new attitude toward writing. The iPad
lets me bring my research library with me and read it as if I were
reading paper. The screen and software are fast enough that annotation
feels natural, and it’s far easier to read in a variety of positions and
places than a laptop.  The cloud (in particular <a href="http://www.dropbox.com">Dropbox</a>) lets me
edit or annotate on any of my devices and have the results
automatically synchronized with all my other devices without my lifting
a finger.  I love
<a href="http://blogs.hbr.org/schrage/2012/01/tip-for-getting-more-organized.html">technology that works for me rather than vice versa</a>.</p>

<p>My new attitude toward writing has nothing to do with hardware or
software and everything to do with the fact that I’m just writing more.
This includes blogging, writing handouts for classes, writing letters of
recommendation, writing referee reports for journals, and even
occasionally writing up my own research.  I’m getting more comfortable
composing on the computer through simple practice, and the fact that
the bulk of my writing is low-stakes has made the learning curve bearable.</p>

<p>Reading and annotation take place mostly on the iPad in GoodReader.
I’ve yet to see a pdf that it can’t handle and over the past two years
the annotation features have become better and better.  I’m still a
little slower on the iPad than I am scribbling on paper with a red pen,
but the advantages outweigh the current speed penalty. I don’t have to
carry 300 pages of paper around. I don’t have to make photo copies of
anything. I can distribute comments on papers via email as soon as
they’re ready.  Students don’t have to decipher my handwriting.  And
with practice I think I’ll get faster.  There are (several) other pdf
annotation apps for the iPad, but none of them (AFAIK) integrate as well
with Dropbox.  I can specify a folder and GoodReader will download all
the pdf’s in it so I have local copies.  Then, after I’ve made my
changes I just have to press the Sync button and the modified files are
uploaded.</p>

<p>The Preview app on the Mac has always allowed some pdf annotation, but
with the Lion release, it became excellent.  On a desktop monitor (or
two), I can blow up the text nice and big in one window and still have
room to see tables/figures in another.  With a real keyboard and a
healthy dose of keyboard shortcuts, I’m actually pretty fast at marking
up a document.  I’ve heard good things about <a href="http://skim-app.sourceforge.net/">Skim</a> as a Preview
replacement, and at some point I’ll give it a try.</p>

<p>For storage and searching, I use Mekentosj’s <a href="http://www.mekentosj.com/papers/">Papers</a> app.  It integrates
with several online research databases (including ISI’s <a href="http://apps.webofknowledge.com">Web of
Knowledge</a>) and makes it very easy to slurp articles into my own libary.
I’ve also had some success with having it generate bibliographies for my
own papers.  But at the end of day, I spend a lot more time reading and
annotating with Preview or GoodReader that I do searching and organizing
in Papers.</p>

<p>New writing mostly happens on a Mac.  I continue to get faster at typing
on the iPad and iPhone, but I’m still way more efficient with a real
keyboard.  <a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/">emacs</a> (<a href="http://aquamacs.org/">Aquamacs</a> to be specific) is my
editor-of-choice (as it has been for more than 20 years now) but I’ve
started using <a href="http://www.mindnode.com/">Mindnode</a> for initial brainstorming.  I’m not sure it
will stick, but it is fun.</p>

<p>My work world has a lot less paper in it than it did 6 months ago, but
I’m still not 100% paperless.  What’s left is mostly scraps, but there
are two things that I’d like to eventually transition:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Old articles:</strong>  I still have that big file cabinet full of articles
with notes.  Scanning them all or transcribing the notes would be a ton
of work that doesn’t seem worth it.  I could also just throw them away,
but storing them is pretty cheap.  And so for now they sit.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Lecture notes:</strong> I don’t like to put everything I’m going to say on
my lecture slides.  I think it’s confusing when students don’t know when
to listen to me or read the screen. Ideally, my slides just highlight the
organization and important points and include the occasional figure,
table, or dramatic photograph.  I tend to have a bunch of written notes
that go along with each lecture that I refer to while I’m talking or writing on
the board.  Slowly but surely I’m putting these notes into <a href="http://brettterpstra.com/why-markdown-a-two-minute-explanation/">Markdown</a>
documents that I can refer to while I teach, but for now I have a lot of
physical folders.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Mostly paperless has been great for me because my bag is lighter and I
now have access to almost everything I need from almost everywhere.  It
makes sharing documents easier and I can index digital assets on
multiple dimensions.  Those debates about whether aricles should get
stored by author or by topic or by project are long gone since it’s easy
to do all three.  Paperless is also great for trees because they can
stay where they are soaking up sun and CO2 instead of being ground into
pulp and mixed with smelly chemicals.</p>

<p>100% paperless is kind of like enlightenment.  It’s extremely
hard (if not impossible) to achieve, but there are great rewards for
striving to get there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
