<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[economics | High Variance]]></title>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/categories/economics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://highvariance.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-30T23:15:07-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://highvariance.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug McKee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Helping Old Churches Connect with the Community]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/03/16/helping-old-churches/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/03/16/helping-old-churches</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hv-trinity-church.jpg" alt="Trinity Church on the New Haven Green" title="Trinity Church on the New Haven Green" /></p>

<p>Every morning we drop the kids off at day care and walk about 5 blocks to our offices. In those 10 minutes I walk by
<a href="http://www.trinitylutherannh.org/">Trinity Lutheran Church</a>, <a href="http://trinity-baptist.org/">Trinity Baptist Church</a>, and
<a href="http://www.stmarys-priory.com/">St. Mary’s Church</a> (Catholic).  Just a block off our route are the
three big churches on the New Haven Green: <a href="http://www.trinitynewhaven.org/">Trinity Church</a>,
<a href="http://www.newhavencenterchurch.org/">Center Church</a>, and <a href="http://www.newlights.org/">United Church</a>.  All these old churches are
pretty much empty during the day and even on Sundays they don’t get nearly the traffic they used to.</p>

<p>Even with all the excitement about the new Pope, the Catholic Church in particular seems to be in decline.  While membership has held steady at about 25% of the US population since the 1950’s (largely due to the influx of Latino immigrants), the fraction of members attending mass every Sunday has dropped from 80% to less than 25% over the same period.  This has led to huge numbers of parishes closing and lots of hand-wringing on the part of priests and bishops.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>How has this happened?  The economist in me says a big part of the
answer is competition from newer more exciting denominations and
religions.  Fundamentalist churches are doing well.  The Mormon church is growing like crazy.  Around the world Pentecostal and Baha’i faiths are siphoning off members.  It also seems that more and more Americans have issues with some of the conservative stances of the Catholic church on birth control, homosexuality, and evolution/creation.  Of course, many of the popular new mega-churches are also quite conservative and liberal views haven’t helped the more progressive older denominations.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>The financial cost of losing active members is larger for some
denominations<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, but I believe the major concern within most
denominations is a loss of relevance in the community.  I also think most churches don’t want to adapt their principles to gain larger market share.  Instead, they’d like new ways to reach out to the community and let them know what churches have to offer.  And while I personally am not interested in joining a parish, I do like the idea of other people going somewhere once a week where they are reminded to be nice. </p>

<p>I believe these churches should reach out to their communities by renting out their buildings as office space during the week. They would do it in such a way that it could be converted back and forth in a few hours and so have no effect on weekend services.  Imagine office partitions and pews on wheels.  If big arenas can have basketball games during the day and hockey at night, this kind of conversion must be easy.</p>

<p>While these churches are beautiful on the outside, the interiors are often breath-taking and always unique. This would induce serious corporate demand. Bigger companies could rent the whole space and break it up into cubicles that could  slide in on Monday morning and out on Friday afternoon. Another option would be to turn the <a href="http://www.kencollins.com/glossary/architecture.htm">sanctuary</a> into an espresso stand and substitute tables and comfy chairs for the pews in the <a href="http://www.kencollins.com/glossary/architecture.htm">nave</a>. Who wouldn’t rather work there than a cookie-cutter Starbucks or Starbucks-imitator?</p>

<p>This would work out great for the churches too. They would give up almost nothing and get a captive audience for subtle evangelization. The stained glass alone would be a great advertisement for returning on Sunday. The cash infusion to the church would pay for the required capital investment and probably put a fair bit more into the coffers.</p>

<p>In economics there is a concept called a Pareto improvement. This is transaction or change or reallocation of resources that makes at least one person better off without making anyone worse off. It might sound like sacriledge to even talk about turning holy spaces into coffee bars, but it sure seems like a Pareto improvement to me.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Msgr. Charles Pope at the the Archdiocese of Washington has a couple terrific blog posts about this subject <a href="http://blog.adw.org/2010/12/is-the-bottom-really-falling-out-of-catholic-mass-attendance-a-recent-cara-survey-ponders-the-question/">here</a> and <a href="http://blog.adw.org/2010/11/more-church-closings-so-what-is-god-teaching-us-and-how-will-we-respond/">here</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Unitarian Universalists have been holding steady at around half a million since the 1960’s though there was a bump right after the Unitarians merged with the Universalists. (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unitarian_Universalism#Number_of_members">wiki</a>)<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>The Catholic Church can handle declines in contributions better than most since, <a href="http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,833509,00.html">according to Time Magazine</a>, the Vatican is worth between 10 and 15 billion dollars.<a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Neutral Podcast: A for Entertainment, B for Effort, and C for Economics]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/12/neutral/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/02/12/neutral</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I drive a 2002 Honda Civic. It’s an automatic and even though the interior is smeared with a thin layer of toys and crumbs, it hasn’t been vacuumed in months. It could not be less of a “driving machine” or more of a “people mover.” And yet, my favorite new podcast (<a href="http://neutral.fm">Neutral</a>) is all about cars and the tech behind them.</p>

<p><a href="http://marco.org">Marco Arment</a>, <a href="http://hypercritical.co">John Siracusa</a>, and newcomer Casey Liss have teamed up to tell folks on the Internet what they drive, what they would like to drive, what everyone else should drive, and most importantly the reasons behind each in excruciating detail. In just four episodes, I’ve learned about dual clutch transmissions, the appeal of white cars, pricing of used Acura NSX’s, and how hard it is not to generalize from small samples even when we know it’s wrong.</p>

<p>When I was in college, I read <em>Car and Driver</em> and <em>Road and Track</em> religiously. Even though I couldn’t afford a car at all, I could tell you the difference between the latest models of BMW, Audi, and Volvo. So it makes me really happy that a bunch of nerdy guys who now have a bit of money and who have been keeping up better than me can now own nice cars. (Actually, only Marco and Casey are in this situation–John still drives an Accord while he waits for his kids to finish elementary school and middle school and high school and college. It’s going to be a while for John.) </p>

<p>I really only have the tiniest complaint about the show and it starts with a comment Marco made while defending his choice to pay (about) $500/month to lease a “nice” car instead of $250/month to lease an “adequate” car. He said that meant he must get twice as much value from the nice car to make it worthwhile. A reader graciously wrote in to correct his logic, but clearly it didn’t stick because Marco proceeded to wave his hands and say the argument was “semantics.”</p>

<p>Price is not the same thing as value. People buy a thing when the price is <strong>less than or equal to</strong> the value they get from that thing. This value (or benefit) is often much higher than the price. The difference between the value and the price is called the consumer surplus. When deciding between purchasing two things (like a nice car and an adequate car), what matters is which one has the higher consumer surplus. In Marco’s case, that means he needs to get at least $250 additional value from the nice car–that’s almost certainly much less than double the value he would get from the adequate car.</p>

<p>Part of being a nerd is sweating the details and getting stuff right. No one wants to ship buggy products and they shouldn’t ship buggy podcasts either. I’ll give them the benefit of the doubt since <em>Neutral</em> is still a 1.0.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stock prices are not grades for last quarter]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/24/stock-prices-are-not-grades/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2013/01/24/stock-prices-are-not-grades</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past few quarters, I’ve noticed a disturbing pattern. At some point near the end of the financial quarter, professional stock analysts predict Apple’s numbers (e.g., profit and revenue) to go up a lot. The market takes these predictions seriously and the stock price adjusts to take them into account. Then Apple does report good numbers (usually record-breaking) but not quite as good as the analysts predicted.  The stock goes down as the market adjusts using the new (factual) information about how well the company is doing.  This is all perfectly normal.  </p>

<p>The disturbing part is that the Apple tech writer blogosphere then complains that it doesn’t make sense.  Their logic seems to be that because Apple just did really well, they should be rewarded for it and the stock should go up. They think the expectations shouldn’t matter.  They don’t seem to understand that stock prices are a function of currently held capital and <em>expectations</em> of future performance. Sigh. If these writers want to be mad about something, they should be mad that the analysts are doing a lousy job at predicting Apple’s performance. They shouldn’t be surprised by basic market behavior.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is it cruel to raise the retirement age?]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/11/19/raising-the-retirement-age/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/11/19/raising-the-retirement-age</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I like Paul Krugman a lot–we’re both liberals and believe strongly in
the value of big government and thougtful regulation.  Unfortunately, he
sometimes has strong opinions about things he hasn’t thought through.
That’s my only explanation for his <a href="">recent article</a> on the “cruelty” of
raising the Social Security retirement age–a policy I think is smart on
almost every dimension.  </p>

<p>The Social Security system was designed after the Great Depression to do
two things: keep old people out of poverty and insure against disability
that prevents people from working to support themselves.  The disability
insurance part of Social Security is less well-known than its retirement
benefits but is very important and I have nothing to say about it today.
You’ll note that I didn’t mention a third objective: funding a long
retirement for most people after they’ve worked a sufficient number of
years.  The Social Security system is expected to provide this now, but
it certainly wasn’t at the beginning.</p>

<p>In 1930, the average white 20 year old male could be expected to live to
age 66 (<a href="http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0005140.html">source</a>).  If he
made it to age 40, he could expect to live to age 69, and if he made it
to age 50, his expected age of death increased to about 72 years.  During
the bulk of the years he contributed to Social Security, he was
expecting a fairly short (1 to 7 year) period after age 65 when he could
actually retire with full benefits.  Even FDR didn’t see the goal as
funding people’s “golden years”:</p>

<pre><code>"We can never insure one hundred percent of the population against
one hundred percent of the hazards and vicissitudes of life, but we
have tried to frame a law which will give some measure of protection
to the average citizen and to his family against the loss of a job
and against poverty-ridden old age."

-- President Roosevelt upon signing Social Security Act ([source](http://www.ssa.gov/history/briefhistory3.html))
</code></pre>

<p>Contrast this with the experiences of people in 2004 (the latest year I
could easily find data). A 20 year old expected to live to 77 years, a
40 year old to 78 years, and a 50 year old to 79 years.  The expected
duration of retirement ranged from 12 to 14 years.  Krugman is right
that the expected length of retirement upon reaching age 65 has not
changed all <em>that</em> much
(<a href="http://www.ssa.gov/pressoffice/basicfact.htm">from 14 years to almost 20 years</a>),
but that’s irrelevant to people’s expectations during working life.</p>

<p>Other things have changed since the Social Security was enacted too.
While original benefits were high enough to keep retirees out of
poverty, modern levels replace a much larger fraction of income.  Jobs
are a lot less physically demanding today.  In 1940, 26.7% of those
employed worked on farms or did miscellaneous forms of physical labor
relative to just 5.9% in 1990.  And in 1940, only 21.3% of workers were
managers, officials, clerical workers, or professionals.  This ballooned
to more than half the work force by 1990.  (More detailed breakdowns
<a href="http://www.demographicchartbook.com/Chartbook/images/figures/fig16-1.pdf">here</a>).
Finally, I’m pretty sure physical health of those who do survive to 65
is better now than it has been in the past though I couldn’t easily find
data to back that up.</p>

<p>Most people who reach 65<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> are strongly enouraged by the incentives in
the Social Security system to retire even though they are perfectly
capable of being highly productive members of the work force.  I believe
their experience is a huge untapped resource for the economy.  But what
of the people that Krugman is worried about: Those who worked physically
stressful jobs for years and at age 65 don’t expect to live all that
much longer.  I have a heart and I worry about this group too.  Suppose
we let people retire at age 65 but capped their benefits at a relatively
low level.  This constraint would be unbinding for those who worked low
paying (and more likely physically demanding) jobs.  At the same time,
it would encourage relatively wealthier (and healthier) folks to work
until they were, say, 70 years old.  If wealthier people really want to
retire earlier, they can save more during their working lives and rely
on Social Security for what it was designed: insurance against poverty
in old age.  We all win!</p>

<p>benefits at 62 and higher benefits if they wait until the “full
retirement age” of 65.  The amounts are designed to make the people
fairly indifferent between the two dates.  In the next few years, the
full retirement age will be going up to age 67 (details
<a href="http://www.socialsecurity.gov/retire2/agereduction.htm">here</a>).</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Currently the system allows people to retire with some<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Time Preference Puzzles]]></title>
    <link href="http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/02/17/time-preference-puzzles/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://highvariance.net/blog/2012/02/17/time-preference-puzzles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I saw
<a href="http://louisville.edu/faculty/cjcour02">Charles Courtemanche</a> present
<a href="http://www.nber.org/papers/w17483">an interesting paper</a> about how
people react to changes in food prices. Turns out the impatient people
and those who might have trouble with commitment (to diets for example)
are quicker to buy more food when the prices drop.  The paper had some
issues so I wouldn’t immediately go betting the farm on the results, but
it used some measures of how people think about time that got me thinking.</p>

<p>The National Longitudinal Survey of Youth (1979 cohort) interviewed
individuals age 14-22 in 1979 and continued to interview them every year
until 1994 and every two years after that.  It includes great data on
schooling, employment, income, fertility, marriage, and cognitive
skills.  In 2006, they added two particularly interesting questions.
First, they asked about trade-offs between getting money today versus one
year later:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Suppose you have won a prize of $1000, which you can claim
immediately. How- ever, you have the alternative of waiting one year
to claim the prize. If you do wait, you will receive more than
$1000. What is the smallest amount of money in addition to the $1000
you would have to receive one year from now to convince you to wait
rather than claim the prize now?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Based on this question, it’s easy to compute an annual discount rate;
i.e., how much an individual values the present over the past.  If
someone says they would be indifferent between $1000 today and $1100 a
year from now, then their discount rate would be 1100/1000, or about
0.91.  That is, a dollar today is only worth 91 cents a year from now.</p>

<p>In Courtemanche’s paper, they report that the average discount factor of
respondents based on the first question is 0.59.  That is, on average,
people report indifference between $1000 today and $1684 a year from
now.  This is far far lower than any revealed preference measure I’ve
ever seen.  For example, in Keane and Wolpin’s classic 1997 paper, they
estimate that the discount factor is 0.9367, based on career choices of
young men in the same data set.  Rust and Phelan’s 1997 paper reports an
estimate of the discount factor of 0.98 based on retirement decisions of
low income older men in another data set.  And then there’s the fact
that if people really did discount the future at a really high rate, why
would they ever invest their money in assets that return 5-10%?
Strange.</p>

<p>It turns out people sometimes report different annual discount rates
depending on how long they have to wait–that is, they are inconsistent
about how much they discount the future.  You can get at the extent of
this inconsistency by looking at answers to a second (very similar)
question that was added to the NLSY in 2006:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Suppose you have won a prize of $1000, which you can claim
immediately. How- ever, you can choose to wait <strong>one month</strong> to claim the
prize. If you do wait, you will receive more than $1000. What is the
smallest amount of money in addition to the $1000 you would have to
receive one month from now to convince you to wait rather than claim
the prize now?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You could compute an annual discount rate from this question too, and
for many (most?) people it will be lower, because we think that people
are “present-biased.”  That is, as soon as they have to wait at all,
there is a penalty.  The average discount rate in the data based on this
question is indeed lower: 0.28.  Quasi-hyperbolic discounting formalizes the
idea of present bias by saying that individuals discount future payments
that are t periods away by β δ<sup>t</sup> where β is
the measure of present bias and δ is the “pure” measure of time
preference.  </p>

<p>The average estimates reported in the Courtemanche paper are 0.80 for
β and 0.75 for δ.  I don’t have much intuition for what these
numbers should be, but Fang and Sliverman’s 2009 paper (published in
International Economic Review) uses the NLSY 1979 to estimate them based
on labor supply and welfare take-up decisions of single mothers.  They
get a very different number for β (0.34) and a kind of close one
for δ (0.88).  You can look at the glass as half-empty or
half-full.</p>

<p>Personally, I find this inconsistency in estimates of people’s time
inconsistency somewhat disturbing.  It makes me wonder what would happen
if the NLSY added a third question where the time people had to wait was
even shorter.  Like a day instead of month.  This would give us another
estimate of β.  If it was very close to 0.28, I’d feel better about
the theory of hyperbolic discounting.  Perhaps these experiments have
already been done in the lab?  We’ve now reached the limits of my
knowledge of this area.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
